Welcome to the Mycelian Network Podcast, a podcast all about early stage web developers
and the mentors and teachers that helped them along the way.
Hey, welcome Peter.
Welcome to the Mycelian Network Podcast.
Thank you so much.
It's a pleasure.
So, I've taught many approaches to doing this in the beginning.
It's now my sixth recording.
So I think what I'm going to try with this one is instead of me asking a bunch of questions
in the beginning, I'm going to kind of give you the floor and say that what I do know
is that you've been in the industry for a long time.
You've done a whole bunch of things.
We worked together for a long time as well.
But what I think would be interesting is if you could just tell us your journey from when
you started getting into this or actually go as far back as you like, but kind of leading
us up to today.
Yeah, so I don't know what you said about me in the introduction, but I've been doing
web development for 25 years and I don't know if that's a good thing or a bad thing.
Some people have been doing it for 25 years.
They move on to become directors of dev rel something.
I don't know.
I just love it.
I started when basically I found out you can make an HTML page and you put them online.
Me and my friends, when we were teenager, we made a webpage about poop and we uploaded
it to a website, like the telecom ISP's website.
And this was back in the day when people would read magazines about the interlift and the
magazines would often have links to web pages that now suddenly exists and you can actually
go to and serve them.
And I had the smart idea of writing a angry letter to this magazine, complaining, pretending
to be someone else, pretending to be angry that this ISP have a webpage at this certain
URL that talks about poop, hoping that that would be some sort of controversial thing
that people say, what is this horrible thing?
I need to check it out.
So maybe it did drive more traffic.
Maybe we had like three more people visit the site or something.
I don't remember.
Yeah, so I started making HTML and CSS, that kind of stuff back in before the millennia,
but in fact, when I lived in Sweden where I grew up and I actually managed to do a little
bit of work there, like consulting work and we're two companies that needed webpages and
I would do the webpage part of it and then hand it over to the Unix programmers who would
then add CGI to these pretty pages to make them into apps or websites.
And I kept doing that for a few years when I lived in England too, and those were the
days when you'd have designers who make something pretty in Photoshop and then hand them over
to web developers who would then slowly cut them up into webpages by extracting little
gifs, spacer gifs and things like that.
And then I took a little break from web development and went to school.
I did mathematics and throughout my summer breaks and winter breaks, I ended up working
for a little couple of guys at the university who made webpages and as soon as I graduated,
I joined them to become the first employee and together we started a consulting business
doing webpages and web apps and databases and yeah.
And then I did that for 10 years and then I moved to America to work with Mozilla doing
internal web properties where together with you Skulk as you know, that was all sorts
of internal and some external apps by heavy on webpage and then together with you again
Skulk the last couple of years and Mozilla I've worked on the MDN WebDogs page is usually
popular and I'm proud to say that I took a huge fart in rewriting that site from scratch
become a modern kind of a gen stack website and what could say and now I'm at GitHub where
I work on their documentation website maintaining that, that it functioned out and provided.
So that's quick whirlwind on my background.
I'm now based in the East Coast in South Carolina and so that's a little bit about my background.
I'm also and always have been a very early Python coder.
So I started back in 1999 and actually making some commercial Python book which was great
fun and it's kind of cool because I feel in a sense statistically I've been there from
the beginning and it's always fun to look back at that over the years and I swear I
have not seen anything as pretty as Python since I have been missing out the last couple
of years maybe there's been some recent development and Julia and Rust and so on and it always
been a big Python fanboy and I think what drew me into Python was another early interest
which I had when I started the web developer like people find a niche something that they
can attach themselves to.
Some people like aesthetics so they really like the idea of my pretty colors and having
something pleasant for them.
Some people come from types they like pretty fonts the right alignment like a newspaper
kind of that thing and they have many different interests and mine was that of usability like
a little nerd I would read everything I could get my hands on every blog post in the early
2000s but I would always I would always mop that concept of usability it felt like hey
that's something I can maybe become good at I seem to have an interest in it I like it
and it's something I like this burning sort of gut passion for fire for I really that's
something I can contribute with there are other people who really who just have different
passions and it's good like Ryan said and I think that's sort of was my love a little
bit with Python it felt like they made the programming language so you don't have to
think much like it didn't put a barriers it's almost like pave the path for you like a red
carpet and it's famously so that some people say that Python is written down English that
you can run because it reads so well and so that's always stuck with me I think over the
years maybe my interests have come and gone in different topics but the whole usability
piece the Jacob Nielsen research early on was super interesting and you can kind of
walk away with that keeping two simple axioms in mind and it says Steve Krupp he said don't
make me think and so there is so much more to that statement than just web interfaces
or UIs there's also don't make me think to your fellow code reader a fellow colleague
or even yourself so when you write a piece of code people often talk about the either
some other engineers can have to work on this code or it's also you yourself so write it
in a way that it can read as plain English make it almost too simple to be for what you
know put effort into making it super simple and I think that's a very very important ingredient
to multiple things and it's not just about how you make your UI and it's not just about
you type your programming code but there is a huge element of this in your system design
too like you need to always keep that in mind like if you hand this system over to someone
will they scratch their head and have to sort of worry about understanding why I don't think
people have a problem understanding oh this is Postgres oh this is memtest oh this is
PHP whatever they don't struggle with that but they might be wondering why is there a
extra Redis server sitting on the side and why does it have a cryptic name that I don't
understand and I think over the years I think it's become kind of my strain and some of
that might come from a bit of confidence that I don't feel like I need to show off because
if you don't need to show off you are less prone to take out the weirdnesses people sometimes
call out weirdnesses just to show off somehow it's strange I mean we're all a little bit
guilty of it we want to show to our friends that hey look I'm using this latest reactive
CSS framework something that you know that you don't use so I'm cool we all have that
in us there's no denying even people who call themselves masters of simplicity they sometimes
over complicate and kind of thrive a little bit in it I think we're all a little bit guilty
of it yeah that's really true you know I mean that way you said like even for yourself I think
where I learned a little bit about that and it's something that I'm starting to do again
is when I used to do music stall my guitar teacher told me always write the fingering
that you use for your left hand and your right hand write it on the sheet music because this
is not just important for now so that you can see and understand what you're doing but if you pick
up this piece of music again in five years from now you're going to thank yourself that you did
that because you're not going to remember oh in this part I decided to re-finger it like this
because it played easier or it sounded better or whatever the case is so I think leaving the same
kind of hints to yourself and therefore other developers in your code either by writing your
code in a clear and concise way that's easily understandable or when it's a little harder
because just it needs to be leaving comments to explain why it is the way it is so that if you
or somebody else picks it up then you're like oh I see that's why this is specifically like this and
it ties back to this thing and this other component that and that's the reason why this
is decoupled or that's the reason it's not decoupled I think it I think there is a
a lot of people say that mantra write a comment that explains why and that's almost easier too
easy to say and I have another perspective on that is when I used to study for my exams
one of the things I used to do was pretend to write cheat notes I even would write on a piece
of paper would write the text little with a sharp pen I would write the little formulas that I
had to memorize or the little important names or whatever it was I would write them in a small hold
just to make the whole exercise a little bit more special a little bit more mnemonic and I would
write them down the night before or the the days before whatever it was and then obviously leave
the cheat notes at home and so you don't get caught and the whole exercise there it's like
it's cognitive science it forces the brain to think about the things that you don't know
and it kind of goes like that with your code trail and your comment trail you don't
you don't necessarily need to explain everything the why but ask yourself like whoa this is a
little bit surprising I find it a little bit surprising I'm sure someone else is going to find
surprising so work from that don't look at every statement and think of a why comment for it but
look at it like hmm is this gonna be hard to understand for me would I need if this was my
old test would I need cheat notes to remember why this component is different from this or why have
I allowed to repeat some code or something there's got to be like a store and so deep there ask
yourself those questions I think that helps yeah yeah for sure I agree yeah that's super interesting
stuff I was thinking about something now but that slipped my mind so we'll cycle back to that oh
yeah no what it was is so you talked about usability and how that is like a burning passion for you and
I mean I've experienced that with some of the meetings we've had on while we were together
working on MDN where you've asked like really important questions during some of these
brainstorming meetings we had or where we talked about an interface that other people didn't ask
so like how do you is this just experience that that's leading to this or is there any like
material you can point out that you found that really helped you improve the way you think
about how to make good software right so there's there's two factors to that and that what
makes it almost impossible to explain but there's one factor is confidence like you need to feel
somewhat happy in your mind that you can take a punch in the face for looking like an idiot
because if you can't do that you don't want another instance of looking like a fool at work
and then maybe looking like a fool in your day-to-day life so confidence is one part
but the other part is something that stuck with me when I was a young young adult I did a lot of
martial arts and our instructor would insist like come on ask questions you'll only be an idiot once
that's the statement that I think about that too so you're in a work meeting
and as long as you're not completely wasting a bunch of people's time there's a great chance
that you can remove this idiocracy once and for all and then you've got to keep in mind too
that there's a big chance that everyone else is thinking the same so that maybe if you talk about
a tool if you find it a little bit nerve-wracking to kind of admit that you don't understand
you can at least boost your morale internally by thinking it's very possible that right now
I'm going to do a favor for her and him and him by asking this question and oh god forbid
I'm wasting his time and her time because they've already understood that so they were at the other
meeting but maybe if that helps to always think that you know what I'll take this one for the
team because it can multiply so I'll ask this hard question or almost embarrassing question
and so that those other people can also benefit so we can all benefit I think that's a tool that
can help and then you try to like do that with all sorts of other aspects um for example because
the truth is what we do as professional engineers working on computers is we write a lot of emails
slack comments you know relation tracker comments and stuff like that keep that in there too for
example if you see an acronym you don't understand or something you say what does p h p mean I've
never heard this before and you're doing that because a you google it but b now you might be
able to help the other people who are going to come and see this acronym and don't know what it
means now you're maybe saving that googling time for a bunch of other people so I think that's a
great little tool to justify that dip that you need to take by asking those questions because
it is a little dip so they can come out as a winner and I think um I think I so confidence I'm
I'm I'm a moderately confident person I might not have great self-esteem I feel just as much
formal as everyone else in the world but another thing too that I think is very important and you
mentioned meetings is to kind of jump at the elephants in the world the hard questions
because I've learned almost too late that the academic way of the almost the best way of
learning is to like attack the really hard problems maybe you don't know the answers today
but if you jump to the to the last page of your math exercise book and work on those work you're
going to get stuck but your little brain is going to be chugging away at it maybe after the meeting
or the over the night or throughout the day so you're slowly like gather little fragments and
it's the same when you sit down in a corporate world and you're up against some sort of challenge
I think everyone in the room is kind of eager to to find a low-hanging fruit or something that they
can say hey uh I can do the uh the new signup button and then you feel sort of fulfillment like
hey I'm taking something away something that I can do but maybe what you should do is say
why are we building this or who's the user going to be for this or hang on why didn't we
install that other you know like really almost controversial questions and they can be asked in
a way that they don't annoy like like attack those because once you start chewing on those
whilst you may be working on that signup button rather than I'm just going to worry about the
signup button now this easy thing and then you're leaving procrastinating the big problems they're
going away they're just different ways or maybe rearranging them and some of them again maybe
they take a little bit of confidence to be them almost a little bit controversial by asking a
little bit weird questions but I think it really works especially if you mix it up a little bit so
you go some high and some some lows so you chat about like the big tickets that are almost there's
almost an energy in the room or a lack of energy where people don't talk about this
and then you mix that up with some of the easy stuff some of the low-hanging fruits
so that you feel a certain momentum going forward. I heard somebody say the other day
ignoring something doesn't make it go away doing it makes it done so I think that's
same for everyone to remember. Something that you've said a lot and that has an impact on me
personally is you tend to always say writing the code is the easy part understanding the problem
is the hard part do you want to dig into that a little bit? Yeah I remember there was a famous
blog post I forget the name of the author and he talked about planning the importance of planning
and the truth is that planning is awesome like thinking through the problem first
it really helps. The honest truth though just like buy low sell high it's not easy to plan
so sometimes what you need to do is you need to sort of immerse yourself with the challenge
jumping in and I don't know do whatever it takes to like get yourself disgusted by the
problem make it really really difficult and like get that all over yourself and in your brain so
it's all corners of your brain is working with this hard one and do whatever that takes like
some people like to jump into some crazy prototype some people like to write a document a google doc
a word doc where they're all pen and paper writing styles and like that can like jump into it because
once those things start to come out we start to sort of slowly develop a picture and then you're
and then you're like okay shoot we don't need that other database what we do need is the password
thing widget and now I've thought about it I've prototyped about it maybe that code has been
thrown away I have chatted to my friends and colleagues about it all right the work is done
now we just need to type it up so sit down with your JavaScript editor and write it down
and it's almost like taking notes or writing a reflective summary report and so I think
that ties into that topic that writing the code can be easy if you've thought about the hard parts
of it and I don't that's not necessarily an answer but the statement I still stand by that often
writing the code is in there's also the certain element and we're all very very familiar with
that is that you're up against a big challenge and it's usually a very complex challenge in that it's
so much more than just the style sheet it's also getting approval from design and secure database
security folks and you need to have discussion with the product managers or something like that
those are and so there comes a time when you just need to put your headphones down and listen to
some music and just work on something so there is an element of sort of self-peace and happiness
that you take all those challenges which are so energetically draining because they can be
controversial and they force you so you kind of want to save yourself this afternoon I'm just
going to write the code I'm not going to get it right the first time but I'll listen to some music
and I'll type the code and and it gives you like a moment of meditation I think that's important
you need that and also the truth be told if you've been going through the challenges upfront so you
can sit down and relax your brain will still continue to work on those hard problems there
yeah very true so this podcast is a combination so it's a two sides of a coin it's one I speak to
people who are new to web development specifically or software engineering it tends to be that I've
mostly talked to like other web developers and these are people sometimes that young folks that
are literally like starting their career their life but sometimes it's also people that is
switching over from one career to becoming a web developer and so I think one of the things
I'm curious about is for people joining the industry now what do you think what advice
do you have for people like you talk about confidence and I think that's very important
but when you're new and you have this kind of imposter syndrome thing because you see a lot
of these like as they call them the programming ninjas then you kind of feel like I'll never be
able to meet up to those people what are what are some tips you can give people to like build up
their confidence and feel a bit more sure about themselves so that they have the confidence to
step into this world that's a great question and I think I have a very good answer I attribute
a lot of this to shared experience of being a mentor I've been a mentor for many young interns
who come like engineering interns but also maybe the most rewarding mentorship experience that
I've gone through was the outreach program which started in 2015 something like that maybe earlier
which was originally exclusively for women who wanted to gain to tech and non-asserted college
strategies so I was mentoring there and I learned a lot I think there's a huge difference between that
mentoring path compared to young interns especially as you know Skulk a lot of interns we've come
across they are from the top universities in the U.S. and France and Canada and the kind of a reason
why they from the top universities and that's because they're freaking clever cookies who got
into those universities they're the go-getters so they there's a different type of mentoring for
them whereas the more shall we say adult mentees it's 99% of our confidence 1% I'll name it let's
say 90% confidence 9% direction and sort of that and maybe 1% a little bit of coding or some
engineering and I think I can conclude this is like my opinion but maybe one of the best things
you can do is to have a very good mix of professionalism and weaknesses particularly
showing weaknesses there is almost nothing better to give someone a massive boost of confidence
when they can see I'm putting up quotation marks when they can see that someone who's professional
and good at something fails and that you show that and you talk about them and try to be a little
bit more than just this one time I accidentally leaked the password but you know drive on this
point a little bit show that look I am good at A B and C but I am terrible at D I don't understand
it it's so frustrating I get tired I can't believe it I feel like tearing in my hair sometimes and
you know that kind of stuff and also maybe mix in some of those little failure stories that
we all have and they don't always have to be about oh I took down production sir and you dig the
there are many other failure stores and I often sometimes say stores like I wanted to sit down
and learn this new programming language and I just couldn't it didn't work for me my brain
couldn't kick in like I couldn't get it like nothing is more motivating for someone learning
and new in tech so and the other two tips that I have are more guidance and I think your role as a
mentor is to not teach anything but to maybe help the person find their passions their strengths and
like what their heart and their gut goes and and be there for that you know you like tease it out
like hey you seem hmm I get you starting to maybe see you seem like the kind of person you are
maybe see you seem like the kind of person who thrives in speaking to a crowd hmm maybe that
could be your thing you could do talks oh and something like that or or hey you seem like the
kind of person who likes to I don't know get all the ducks lined up like an organizer someone who
likes to finish all the bunk tickets and there's one last hugely powerful tip for people who are
new in the industry and I think in all fairness in terms of wanting to become a better engineer
there is nothing better than making stuff and I think what we all need to do is we need to cool it
with our side projects it's so easy to say for a mentor to a mentee or junior person yeah build
more side projects but it's not that simple people have lives they have passions they have
personalities but here's the thing may can be many different things if you come across someone
who might not be that kind of a side project kind of a gal or guy maybe you can say hey do you know
what you should maybe do write the blog post and they say oh I'm not very good and then you insist
on that like yeah I know it's a hard in the beginning but you know get started you can maybe
write a blog post that shows it just to me and maybe we can edit that if that's your passion
you know like you have to try to find something that they can make because reading will never get
make someone good I mean it will help but making is the true north for everyone that they need to
to do to upgrade their skill set but here's the thing you've got to help them understand what mate
means I've come across mentees who seem to they seem to have a knack for live audience speaking
and they thrive there and so my job as a mentor is to kind of say look there's a conference
this one here's the url maybe you propose a presentation for that and I know it's a small
one and we have to travel and I know you're not an expert of this topic but hey let's figure
something out maybe you can come up with a slightly adjacent topic there they can yeah those are my
my three tips on mentoring or show your own weaknesses and help someone guide them towards
where their heart wants to go and then trigger will force them almost to make things whatever
that means coding and writing presenting so yeah I think it's huge and I think it's an important
thing to to highlight the whole thing about being willing to show your weakness because I think the
world has gotten to that point where people have been actually kind of told the opposite thing
they've always been told to hide your weaknesses and only show the wins don't show the failures
only show the wins until you are some super famous person and then you can talk about your failures
but while you're still coming up hide them hide them and I don't think that that that is a good
approach because you know the first time you fail you're going to feel so alone in that failure
you're going to feel so alone in that failure because you have nobody else that is said me too
I also find it hard I think that is why I still come across people constantly who don't know how
to use get or even get hub and they're too afraid to say that so that they'd rather just not
contribute to a project they'd not contribute to open source because they're too ashamed to say
you know what I can solve this problem but I'm not sure how to use get and get hub to get my
solution to this project but it feels so silly for me to not know that so I'm just going to not do it
yeah it's horribly true it is very much so and now that's the perspective of the particularly
where you started the conversation was like more of junior person and and that is a harsh reality
and that they had to contend with it's easy for a mentor to say show your weaknesses we're talking
about the mentors weakness and but it is and it is a very very difficult thing to be up against
especially when these start to add up like there you have the junior person who realizes oh I still
don't understand get and I don't know how to use it actually that's just one of them you know I'm
also struggling to understand flexbox and I'm also struggling to understand compilation I don't
understand what the difference is between a binary and a plain text or something you know they could
be many of them and but there's not a lot you can do about that we can't know everything and
we can't know everything and this is not necessarily about showing your weaknesses so you need different
mechanisms when you're in that situation when there's too many things and I've always thought
that if I was in I mean it's easy to say no that I'm more experienced but the only really thing you
can do when you're up against that is to try to clear the table so that you can focus on one
little thing at a time and nothing these may be breaking it down into absolute constituents because
you know this and you've come across junior engineers too who honestly they don't necessarily
understand everything and neither do you skull for me but what they do is they go to like the top of
the framework and try to use it and then they get stuck because they don't really understand
the fundamentals and we've all seen shall we say stack overflow posts where they copy and paste
all of their code and it's full of full of their like their business logic and stuff and they're
saying it doesn't work and that kind of stuff and the only way that they can get out of that rut
is to break it down a little scale away and I think the truth be told too here's the thing
there is only one way to solve that and that is to peel it down and that absolutely differentiator
of an experienced engineer and a junior engineer is that the experienced engineer goes there
himself he like oh I don't understand how github desktop works support what they do is they
peel away okay all right let me go back to get the command line tool or I still don't get it
all right maybe they peel away a little bit further they go down to absolute basic commands
then maybe they open up the files or maybe they seek out some documentation about they like the
core of it and they start whereas maybe a junior engineer they don't naturally go to the lower
levels the lower layers themselves they're maybe throwing their hands and so maybe that's it's
something to keep in mind that hey you're a junior the probably the reason why you get stuck is
because you don't naturally go deeper to break it down into add a molecules and then you break down
the molecules into atoms because that is what the seniors do they they don't know it either
but that's what they do and I mean there's a reason why hello world is popular it's because
and that's how the brain can learn you start with something like that print hello world and
we'll work our way up I mean it's easy to sit here and say all of this because there's another
element too that if you're in a junior position and you want to level up it's not particularly
fun to go down to assembly language and learn what a bite is and what you want to do is you
probably want to ship something there are a few things that is rewarding is that you want to like
make something to show your mom and you want to like you want to just download this framework
and put some cool stuff together make a web page or an app for something like that that is what
you want to do right and I don't think there's anything that can be done to solve that other
than maybe try to do both like you start with an objective you say I want to make a whole iOS app
and you come at it a little bit some like the basic tutorials on there but then you're like
all right now I'm starting to get stuck here I need to figure out how do I do a form loop in
potlin wait that's android but anyway that you you can like come at it from the top like the
application and then you can take little breaks and go to the very very smaller components and
just tinker away and I don't know how many times I've done this in the past but it's been an
absolute godsend you're up against a big challenge big system big framework something like that
and it's so confusing there's so many compilers and transformers and transpilers and everything
it's like it's all big blur but you know you've got to ship by next credit and but there's few
things that are as powerful as learning as to like open a new window maybe go down like download the
raw babel like just down or if it's next.js you create a fresh new next.js installation
and you just have this one little thing that you want to do and you can do it maybe your temp
directory or a new computer but you're like just test it out like ah now I understand how lazy
loading css will and like that and then you're like scrap that away kind of like your cheat
notes and then you can go back to the to the beast and to work but that has helped me so many times
and the only thing stopping me from doing it again and again is just sort of human in persia
and laziness but you know that it's what you need to do here is you need to sort of maybe
start a fresh new install of maybe create a brand new database or what a table or something like
that just so you can understand there's one tiny little thing and then jump back at all it's funny
that you mentioned that um the other day on the i listened to shop talk show and they were speaking
to some folks in the agency and they do a lot of wordpress stuff and even though they do a lot of
wordpress it's not really their strong suit so oftentimes what they would do is when they will
want to build a new like component they open up a code pin and like build a component inside code pin
then take that and stick it in into wordpress because now they know they have a version of it
that works so if anything breaks it's something to do with wordpress so now you need to just figure
out what is it in this new environment that's clashing with what i'm trying to do because i
know if i take it out of this situation i put it by itself it works and i bring it into the scenario
it doesn't work so what is different about these two environments and then start teasing it apart
until you find oh it's because it has this extension that does this weird thing and i did
happen to use the same id and it's it's grabbing my element and doing funny stuff with it for sure
i love those tools code pen code sandbox yeah also um when you and i sculpt worked we did a lot of
a lot of complex stuff with the aws system and i got a lot of learning from i used like my private
accounts for that and if there was something i didn't understand i want to create a brand new one
just to test something and then throw it away and so there are lots of tools and they're all
they're really good to have they're good to have and to not be intimidated i think it's an amazing
thing that's happening in the last couple of years now especially in web development where
you file a bug and so saying it doesn't work they say hey can you copy and paste it into a
code sandbox and give us the url and you put it in there and eve what's so amazing too is you
don't necessarily have a perfect story to tell there in your bug that you're going to file or
the rubber duck debugging is simply breaking it down for the sake of maybe putting it into code
pen can help you understand what the hell is wrong so for people who don't know what a rubber duck
debugging means it's uh it's this idea that you are struggling you're stuck something doesn't work
and you ask your colleague over a friend hey can you help me debug what the hell is going on
and so your friend comes over and stand over your shoulder or on zoom as we do these days
that you say all right so i took this fall i tried to copy this i tried to compile this function i
tried to write this style as well i said what the hell no i see what i've done there's my mistake
and you say to your friend like never mind i figured it out as i was breaking it up i figured
it out you can go back to your desk so your friend was just standing there like a rubber duck not
doing anything and so it's quite a famous sort of strategy or anecdotal strategy and hey use that
to your advantage you don't need to disturb a colleague every time what you can sometimes do
is i don't know what's going on i'm going to start a a tiny little atom in say the typescript
playground just the tiniest little function a little type definition and almost as if you prepare
yourself to post the stack of posts or something or show that code pen to your colleagues and
there's big chance that that will inspire your brain to understand it maybe or that you spot
your little mistake on a type or whatever it might be yeah and i think then this ties back to
something you said way back um then writing about this whole thought process you went through
because this can help somebody else again and this ties into your blog which especially when
i search for stuff related to python or something like that more often than not i will land on your
blog and find the answer there so i think blogging is extremely important it's something i've been
neglecting but i'm trying to pick up again but you you do a really good job of running a very
active very there's just so much useful information in that blog what is your approach to to that like
any tips for people want to start blogging i i my approach i mean i wish i could um and i'm jealous
of the people who can pick up a new topic they have observed it and then they almost rewrite it
again in their own words and for example they're the people who keep an eye on say the tc39 spec
discussion so something as it goes through and then they uh they're able to just rewrite it one
more time in a different set of words uh maybe uh less technical and a little bit more of a story
and that's great readership and maybe the truth maybe they do it to get traffic or maybe they're
just as human as anybody else in that maybe if i write it all over again in my words i'll understand
and uh someone else said that if you write an opinion you'll get a lot of negative feedback
but if you write an experience you can never be real and now it's almost maybe a better quality
product uh article if it is an opinion and because it can stir the mind a little bit but hey we're
all the humans so go a little bit for writing your experience and my approach is um a kind of
imagining almost in my head that there was a stack hold for question and let me uh then explain
an answer so you write like all right this is the problem i encountered and it was not easy
eventually i found i can use this function and by the way this function you can read more about on
this page and here's an example of doing it with unicode characters and that's what i did and then
i found that so you write a little bit uh an executive summary about what you just went
through what you learned there like one tiny little micro step that you took in it but you
maybe spruce up the words so that it can be consumable consumable by someone else in my google
across it and i tell you um so my blog is just a loud note taking from my perspective that's what it is and it's
the stack overflow answers that no one asked or something but it is so rewarding uh when someone
posts a column saying hey that really helped me and uh i would encourage everyone to go for that
because in a world where we count likes and hearts and sort of increments like that
there is nothing as rewarding as that feeling of having touched someone's actual progress
so if you can turn around and look at it from that perspective like what can i do to make
someone's life a little bit easier like to make them move on it is so much more rewarding than
getting 20 likes on something keep that in mind that you might touch someone's life by lining
down these loops and it probably doesn't take that long but it's it's hard and everyone struggles
with it because we're all guilty of once this thing your challenge got solved you kind of want
to move on with your life oh that was a stressful thing to figure that out and and i kind of felt
guilty the way i solved it because i i did trial and error i didn't read the spec or something so
it felt sort of like i wouldn't move on but that dirty experience behind me i try in the last while
because like i said look because i want to get back into blogging again well i have been but um
i try and keep like a notion thing open and then when i hit a problem and i start unraveling it
i start just putting little notes in the document like as i go through the process just like maybe
a screenshot of something maybe just a line that kind of can trigger a memory for me later on
and then i work through the problem i solve it and i move on but then maybe over the weekend or
something i'd go back to those notes and i try and flesh them out into an article that explains
properly like this is the issue i hit and these are the steps that i went through so i've got
the basics there and i've got any screenshots that might be helpful in demonstrating how i
went through this little bash outputs like this is what you should probably see in bash after
running this command so i put all of that in and then i run it up sometimes if it's something that
i can do again i'd literally like do it again and this time take the time to actually write down
each and every little step but you don't you don't have that time always so that's why sometimes i
just throw stuff into a notepad thing if you want to call um just i have a reference to go back to
later and say okay let me break this down into an actual readable thing because at this point nobody
understands what the exist yeah i often wonder and so you touched on another interesting excuse
and that is have time and it is an honest uh thing like you it's hard to have time
um i often wonder so that's one excuse the other excuse was the thing i touched on was that when
you did go through this experience was it a bit dirty like did you actually not read the manual
like you should have and which one is the biggest blocker for you taking the time to write down is
it that you don't have time or that you're a little bit guilty feeling for your journey and
so it's i think it's worth keeping that sometimes it's a bit of both or sometimes it's one sometimes
it's the other yeah i guess it also plays into that weakness thing if you had to admit that
that honestly if i just read the docs i probably would have fixed this in a much shorter time but
i was too lazy and you kind of don't want to admit that and then if you look back at it you might
say to yourself that was a stupid thing to do if i just read the docs i could have saved myself
20 minutes now i've gone through a yucky experience and i'm too embarrassed to write about it it's
just double uh double there's another element too which is very very important and so one of
the reasons why we blog is to become a more professional and better engineer than build
better stuff build better more successful businesses so if that is the goal does it matter
if you get punched in the face a little bit here and there i have many a times blogged about
something only to find someone posts a comment where they say hang on did you know that there's
this library or why didn't you just divide by six oh shoot like whoa and now you're confronted
with an almost embarrassing blog post plus comment that kind of makes you look a fool but hey
they wouldn't have mentioned that library in your comment they wouldn't have if you hadn't written
it you would have been completely oblivious about that amazing other thing that is available
and okay maybe you could stumble upon it further all right but you didn't so it was thanks to you
showing your weakness that you stumbled on a new strength now you're like equipped with something
you didn't have before this is amazing library and the internet's too big to spot everything
they give you this and now you can copy and paste that or take that and you can put it back into
your work and you can succeed even better you can now make a better web app that you would have
otherwise you will earn more dollars thanks to this because had they not mentioned it
that no had you not shown what you did they mentioned a comment that makes you look a fool
a little bit you will put more food on the table and that's kind of worth it and things tend to be
forgotten but successes tend to kind of they can live on longer so that is another motivator i think
now for sure and there's there's the other side of it that also happens which kind of happened to me
the other day that's not exactly the same thing but it's it's it's similar in nature so i recorded
a little uh video of using this library that automatically generates all your pwa assets i
think it's even called pwa generator or something like that um so i made a little video of how it
does that and why it's really cool and helpful and saves you a bunch of time and i stuck it on
youtube and the first comment i got was from a person who said you shouldn't use web technologies
to write mobile apps you should just write mobile apps and then i like replied to them i said you
know fair point but the thing is sometimes we don't all have massive teams of developers that
have experience in writing ios apps writing android apps and then this web team sometimes all you have
is a little web team or all you have is yourself and you know web technologies and this is a way
for you to be able to write your write an app for ios or for android or both using your existing
skills and so the person didn't come back and then about two weeks later the author of the package
pwa generator came on to mine and said oh thanks so much for your insightful answer and thank you
so much for writing recording this video about my package i really appreciate it and i was like
ah awesome so yes i got a little pushback i i like i told the person that you know thank
you for your opinion here's why i'm saying this and then i kind of got validation from the author
saying yeah that person was online so these things are also going to happen but it shouldn't stop you
from putting the thing out there because people have different opinions and you're going to have
people indeed we're just going to like say there's a little bit of yin and yang to everything yeah of
course i also think um a lot of people they might look a fool when they're dancing on the dance floor
they go to the i don't know a club or whatever and they do look a fool and it's embarrassing
to dance but that's how they met their husband or their wife had they not gone to look a fool they
wouldn't have met that person and had a wonderful life together so keep that in mind too sometimes
you got a dance uh and it's gonna hurt and then someone's gonna snicker but just wait there's
some gems yeah that's very good uh yeah this has been an awesome chat i only have one thing as a
closing out and i think your comment just now kind of ties into that very nicely which is what do you
do when you are not coding or mentoring or working um i'm an avid swimmer and i swim almost every
morning early i wake up at five o'clock and i know that sounds like annoying to some people who are
not morning people and i'm sorry about that but that's the nature of that sport it's something
you do early in the morning and and i take a lot of fulfillment out of that because it's one of
those things that you can do for your health that isn't too disruptive to family lives and and it's
you don't bang into things like you do with other sport or rip your knees out in certain sports
and then you can't really fall down like you can with a bicycle that's my other thing i think i
think i would have answered side projects as my hobby when i'm not coding but it's too boring of
an answer but it is true it is i mean honest to goodness i look around and i have friends you know
you know they do uh woodwork or they do um they're playing the piano or something like that and
i'm jealous almost like hey look they have a hobby um or what i do with my free time oh i code
side projects but um yeah yeah i remember um forgot his name now same as entrepreneur
uh started linkedin and many other things um and listen to podcast like he does so many things and
they ask how can you be in so many things all at the same time it's easy i don't have any hobbies
and they're like shit man if he can say something like that maybe it's not such an embarrassing fact
to say that i sit in my vs code editor on a sunday they've messed up the end of the world
at all no i don't think so i think as long as you get true god-honest joy out of it then there's
nothing wrong with it yeah and the other truth is that uh why do you swim and are you like smiling
as you're taking your strokes no uh there might be um i don't know there are some exercise moments
where you're actually smiling uh but the truth that we do it for is it's honestly to live a
healthier life over it's like an investment right that's what we love smiling whilst we're doing your
peloton bikes and so why are you working so hard on these side projects are you like sitting there
on a sunday afternoon smiling away having fun like no you're almost me you're grinding away so that
you can have a more sort of a happier years ahead of you because if you're working away on those
side projects and you might not earn many dollars on it through much fame but hey now you actually
understand this new css framework you didn't do that before and it can put little smiles thousands
of little smiles on on your face they barely even move your lips like i actually feel like i
understand this little piece and it's thanks to what i did last last last last sunday and so that's
happiness because we all like to make things and we all like to look good doing what we do for a
living so that's another thing like keep that in mind especially i mentioned earlier that you're
going to make tomorrow keep that in mind that it might not be all like happiness and fun and stuff
you might be frustrated in your free time and and it's hard work and there might not be a big amazing
uh financial success but there will be like spread thin butter on a massive piece of bread like you
won't get a little bit happier trying a little bit every day by the sheer fact that you know
something a little bit better is it's rewarding thanks for that i think is a good place to to end
it thanks again for joining me and uh yeah it was really awesome and thank you so much colt
thank you for listening to this episode of the my senior network podcast if you're not already
please subscribe store and leave a review for us in your podcatcher of choice this helps others
find us and helps us make a better podcast for you on this course you can also find and follow us on
twitter at meet word mysyndium enjoy the community on tesco all the links are available in the show