Welcome to the Mycelium Network Podcast, a podcast all about early-stage web developers
and the mentors and teachers that help them along the way.
Today we're joined by Sharon Rubai-Trade, who is a developer relations professional
and in a volunteering capacity, an open-source community builder having built both the DevOps
Israel and the cloud-native and OSS Israel communities from the ground up.
Today she spends her time building her company, RTFM Please, building their first adoption
strategies to bring excellent technology and people together.
Thanks for joining us, Sharon.
Welcome.
Thank you.
It's my pleasure to be here.
We had quite a journey to make this one happen, a lot of false starts, but in the end, I'm
glad we're here.
Yes, likewise.
It's going to be fun.
So I've given a pretty broad introduction to who you are and what you do, but do you
care to expand on who Sharon Zitzman is and more about these topics that I've already
mentioned?
Yes.
I love when people talk about me and the third person always makes me feel like Sharon Zitzman
is.
So these days, like I said, I run RTFM Please, but I'm doing developer relations as a service,
which is really fun and puts me in front of some of the most exciting developer tools
and trends that are happening in the industry.
And I made my way to this kind of this place.
I went rogue after doing a few roles, consecutive roles in community and developer relations.
So before this, I was head of user communities at Snyk and that's where we met, by the way.
And before that, I was head of developer relations at AppsFlyer and I got to those roles because
I had built the open source developer community around a tool called Cloudify, which was a
cloud orchestration tool.
And when I finished my role there as VP Marketing after seven plus years, I realized that the
thing I enjoyed most was building these developer communities and fostering kind of the collaboration
and peer sharing and all the things that are so important when it comes to really adapting
developer tools and stacks and everything else to make people succeed.
So it's been fun.
I'm glad that when you mentioned all the great developer tools and stuff that you get to
get in front of because of your role on RTFM, that is kind of perfect for what we're talking
about because I think that is one of the areas that has improved so much since I used to
when I started.
And I think, but with that said, I do think it's something that developers aren't exactly
sure how to use when they just get started.
They're not entirely aware of all the tooling that's out there that can help them get up
to speed faster and debug problems faster when they do run into issues.
Are there any tools that you've come across in the recent, I don't know, year or so that
you found is particularly good to bring to the attention of people or tools that you
generally find are really good to help you to develop a journey?
Yeah.
So first and foremost, I'm a big fan of the tools that make things easy and provide a
lot of context and have a very low barrier of entry to adoption.
And that's why the majority of the companies that I work with are PLG companies, product
led growth companies, where they're focused on the developer experience in the meantime
to the low world and making sure that that's a really frictionless process and a well-documented
process and making it very, very easy for even those that are not very familiar with
the domain or the discipline to adopt the tooling.
So a lot of the things that I'm seeing is everything kind of moving as code.
You all know about like kind of shift left and the shift left manifesto and started with
quality and moved on to infrastructure as code.
And now I'm seeing things like product as code and security as code.
And so what's very interesting about all of this is that if before these were kind of
walled gardens that were outside of the development process and developers didn't really have
access to how these processes work and how they natively fit into their workflows, today
a lot of those barriers are being broken down because it's clear that all of these processes
need to start almost as early as the first line of code.
So one of the companies that I work with, JIT for example, is not only building a secure
security as code platform where they help you build security plans as code that focus
on the code and the infrastructure and the runtime and the containers and all the things
that really comprise a real development kind of environment and workflow today, they don't
assume context, right?
It's like assume zero knowledge.
So if we take a look at this mycelium network that is really, really awesome and helping
kind of early and junior engineers kind of find the tooling and find their ground and
find their feet, one of the things that is, I guess, most daunting in the security world,
for example, is that barrier entry, that lack of knowledge, that domain expertise.
And one of the things that they're trying to bridge the gap is by enabling commonly
accepted best practices and plans and checklists and even like industry level ones like SOC
2 and compliance standards through like AppSec programs that are like kind of in consensus
as commonly accepted good practices when securing software or OWASP top 10, which is widely
accepted and baking this into the product from the ground floor for developers who want
to secure their product but don't necessarily have security expertise to be able to do that
from the first line of code based on someone who has done the research, who has curated
the knowledge and made it very, very easy for a young developer to consume.
So that's like just in the context of security, but I'm seeing this from the product perspective
as well.
LiveCycle are trying to break down silos between development product, UX, UI, and bring everyone
into the same platform, like in a single contained collaborative environment.
And I'm seeing also developer experience coming to the center.
And when we talk about developer experience, it's not like a buzzword, it's in the context
of really enabling developers to take ownership and learn quickly and have very little friction
in their processes.
And so some of the things that have arisen over the years, like Git, Git is ubiquitous.
It's ubiquitous to like all of our processes.
And Git is hard.
It's still hard.
For people that have been using Git for years, I open, oh shit, Git all the time, that's
what the website is called, to remember what command I'm running and what I'm, you know.
And so I'm also working with a company that's hoping to do a hard reset on Git because Git
does not have a great developer experience.
They want, you know, auto-complete.
They want, you know, your commands to be saved.
They want so many things that a lot of developers need to make it easy, to make it easy for
us to work, and I constantly have like this cognitive load of what did I need to remember?
What did I need to know?
And why don't I remember this command?
And why is this so hard for me when others think it's easy?
So that's what I'm really liking in the trends around developer tools.
Yeah, no, for sure.
I totally agree because oftentimes I find myself feeling kind of like I am blanking
on the word now, but basically what I'm trying to get at is you tell people when they get
into code that it's not about the code.
The code more often than not is the easy part.
It's the problem solving thing.
So if you're getting into the coding, into the software industry, don't think about what
necessarily what kind of, it's important to know what tools you like and to, you know,
learn them well.
Of course, it's like with anything, carpentry, anything.
You want to know the tools to use, the best tool for the project at hand and be good with
your tools.
But the real clincher for a software industry is the ability to problem solve, the ability
to take a complex problem, break it down into smaller bits, and then define actionable items
that you can address.
Then you start designing, then you start writing the code.
And the harder part is more often than not actually solving the problem, being able to
cognizantly understand what the problem is and having an idea of how you can solve this.
So we talk a lot about that, but then people are like, sure, but crime learning to code
is hard.
What are you talking about?
That's the easy part.
And it's because I think the stuff that you've touched on now is the missing link between
those two things, is that the tools also around the coding, like Git, for example, oftentimes
aren't as easy as we'd like to think they are.
Maybe it's because we've been using it for a long time and we forget about how we struggle.
Or we've gotten into a routine with a set of tools that we are so comfortable with that
it's almost like breathing.
So for us, focusing on the problem solving part is really the hard part and the interesting
part and writing the code is the easier.
But you often have to shift your modality, shift your thinking back to, but what if I
was just starting and I was presented with a problem?
My mind immediately is going to go to, oh, goodness gracious, how do I get this thing
online?
Like I did a live stream the other day where I was talking about atomic design principles,
because I found that a lot of new engineers building websites have this massive CSS file
because they don't understand the concept of breaking it down into components.
And they even don't know that you can import one CSS file into another one.
And back in the day, this is something we used to say, right?
You have one CSS file that you serve because of performance, but with HTTP2, that isn't
that big of a deal anymore, right?
You can potentially have 10 CSS files and it should still be okay.
But I mean, and you have bold tools these days that allow you to work in a way that
is productive by breaking your stuff up into smaller components and then have a bold step
to combine that into one or two or three CSS files that then serve to the end user.
People don't know this.
So they end up with this big CSS file that gets hard to maintain.
And again, this is not knowing your tools well enough.
So that's where the missing link is.
But what I've found is when I talk to these people about it, it's like a revelation to
them.
It's like, oh, that's how you manage to keep your head about you when you're just creating
a simple website.
So I think the tooling is there and I think the developer relations aspect is also what
something that needs to be improved upon.
I think oftentimes we talk to people who already know instead of talking to the people who
are still really learning the thing.
So it's great to know that.
I think GitHub has done a lot here with Git.
It's abstracted away a lot of the complexities of Git to the point where it's like a UI that
you just, a website that you interact with.
But you can only go so far before you have to eventually open the terminal.
And that's where I think a lot of work can be done to improve it.
Like for example, the GitHub CLI, that does help a lot, but it has a learning curve itself.
And I think that, I don't know if you want to expand on that first before I keep talking.
I would like to actually touch on a couple of things that you said there.
So I agree.
So one of the things that's, as you're the person who runs DevOps, you're one of the
people on the team and I've been doing it for nine years.
One of the concepts that I always loved from DevOps is kind of an early piece, an integral
piece of this conference was what they call open spaces.
And what open spaces fostered was this ability for folks to come together around a topic
that they're interested in.
And there's this concept in open spaces called the law of mobility.
So if it's interesting to you, you'll join this session.
And if it's not, you'll move on to other sessions and you'll join.
And you can be either a view, which is the person who kind of buzzes and kind of helps
like lead the session, or you can be a butterfly just listening on the wall and kind of learning
and taking in the information.
But why that's important, that unconference sort of format is that people rally around
a real problem that they're trying to solve or trying to figure out.
I remember in the very early days of DevOps days, people were still talking about chat
ops.
How do you actually even use chat ops?
How do you integrate it?
How do I use it in my Slack?
How do I use it in other tools?
How is it actually actionable?
What can I get out of it?
And people actually felt comfortable in these small circles that rallied around a certain
topic to ask questions about like really simple things that they would be afraid to ask.
Like if somebody's doing your talk on a stage and it sounds so advanced and you're a new
but you're sitting in pride, you want to ask like, hey, how do I, you know, how do I build
my CSS files?
You know, you're not going to ask that.
But if you're sitting in a little like kind of group of people that are talking about
like where CSS has evolved to from then to now, and then, you know, you're in a smaller
group, a safer group, you might actually feel comfortable to ask these questions.
And I feel like more conferences many times talk at you and don't necessarily kind of
include you in the conversation.
And then the people that are sitting in the room that have a lot of questions, they don't
know necessarily how to ask them.
And that's why I like to consider community not one day or not one conference a year,
not one event a year where you can have a place that kind of fosters a conversation
and people can feel comfortable to ask questions and learn from their peers.
And I agree, I think a lot of the time in conferences and tech conferences, they'll
focus on the tech, on the technical side of things.
But sometimes the culture side of things is even that important.
Like, what are the best practices for opening your first XYZ project?
What does this look like?
What's the baseline?
What's the framework look like?
And kind of bringing the more simple fundamentals and primitives in front of folks, because
a lot of things are so abstracted off the stack these days, that it's hard for juniors
to learn what's happening under the hood.
It really is.
Yes.
I hear that a lot.
I'm good until something breaks, then I'm stuck, because I don't know.
I don't know how to find why it's breaking.
I don't know how to fix why it's breaking.
I don't even know what is breaking sometimes.
I just know that...
And error messages are so esoteric half the time.
They're like, this gives me zero context.
I have no idea what this means.
Everything's on fire.
I ran into that just yesterday.
I was helping a colleague with Git, strangely enough.
But it wasn't Git that was the problem.
It was the error message being produced from a build process.
That was the problem.
It was basically saying something along the lines of, I'm able to read property toLowerCase
from undefined.
I was like, wow, that's massively specific.
Okay, cool.
So what can we deduce from the statement?
You're trying to call a function called toLowerCase, cool, that's a web API thing, a JavaScript
function that takes a string and then lower cases it.
So obviously what's on the left is the thing that's undefined.
So instead of saying string.toLowerCase, you're getting undefined.toLowerCase.
You can't do that because undefined doesn't have a toLowerCase function.
Okay, cool.
What is the thing that's undefined?
And that took me down a road of saying, okay, cool, at least here is a little break from
that it happened in this file on this line.
Thankfully, I had that to go with.
So then I had to go and clone the whole thing locally to my local computer, put in some
console log statements around the area where this is happening and try and spit out as
much information to me as I possibly can to find out that in the end of the day, it was
a file that was missing front matter.
And because it was missing the front matter, the string key it was expecting was undefined
and it was trying to call toLowerCase on that.
So and I was like, what would have been super cool is if it said, I'm able to call toLowerCase
on undefined because of missing front matter key in this file.
That would have been like, oh, okay, and you do have that context at that point in the
code, right?
When I was putting in the console log statements, I could get to the problem because the information
was right there.
I could log it out to myself and say, give me the path you're reading, give me the front
matter keys you're trying to read so that I can see which thing is undefined.
So all the information is there, but it wasn't exposed to the user of the API.
And I think that is where a lot of people, new people also, you're like, everything is
an API.
You need to use APIs from day one because that's how everything is done.
And they try to use an API and then the API gives them this like non-deterministic error
message and they're like, okay, something's broken.
I don't even know what's broken and I don't know where, and they throw up their hands
and they think, then you do the thing that humans do is you criticize yourself instead
of saying maybe the documentation is badly written, maybe the API isn't well, they didn't
think about the user, they thought just, I know what's going wrong, so everybody should
know.
And instead of doing that, you're criticizing yourself and saying, I think I'm just too
stupid for tech.
And it's like, no, you're not, you're not.
Don't go there.
Yeah, that's it.
I see that.
I mean, tech is such a high barrier to entry because developer experience is only something
that's happening now, right?
Previously you would have all of these, I don't know, like exceptionally talented people building
tech, but it wasn't at the center of developer experience, the person who's actually using
the product eventually and how they actually get it to, how to ramp up, how to integrate
it into environments.
I remember years ago when I was still building the Cloudify tool, like when I was still building
that developer experience there and doing developer relations and developer experience
and product lead growth and all of these things that didn't have a name or a methodology seven
years ago, but it was clear to me that when I want people to use my product, I want them
to have a great experience and I want them to understand.
I remember just fostering the mindset of, no, the product is not ready if the documentation
is not ready.
Like I would say this to like the developers and they'd be like, no, I shipped the feature.
I'm done.
I'm like, you're not done until you document it.
And then you get documentation.
It's half the time.
It's kind of in the middle of a thought, right?
Because the developer created this feature so they know everything, all of the prerequisites
that come before actually getting to this point.
And that's all of the stuff, those sorts of gaps were the things that I helped this team
overcome and understand.
And I said, then, okay, you built this feature and you have this whole environment set up
and you have all of this stack that you know what it is in order to get to this point.
Nobody else has that information.
Even if that information exists earlier in the documentation, reference it prerequisites
in order to run this new feature are having this set up, having this set up, read it here,
you know, whatever it is, reminding you to set up your environment like this or you know
what I mean?
Whatever it is, having these books in place, but you can't just start in the middle of
the story and expect somebody to know how to work with your product tool feature, whatever
it is.
And that's something that's only now kind of coming to the center stage with the maturity
of developer relations and developer advocacy and developer experience being such a critical
piece in dev tooling.
And that's exciting.
It's an exciting place to be.
But I think that there are still tools that, you know, are existing in our stack that aren't
that are very mature and that, you know, weren't born into like a cloud-muted and kind of world
that we're in right now that still have gaps in that area.
And then that's what happens.
Like a junior developer will feel like, oh, I don't know what I'm doing, I shouldn't even
be here.
And that's not the truth.
The truth is that historically this just wasn't a focus and now it's getting more attention
and that's a great thing and it's a great trend.
We need to do the work to bring our existing tooling up to speed.
Yeah.
And I mean, that's one of the reasons I started the podcast, because I think we don't speak
to the people who are experiencing these problems.
We're not asking them, where are you getting stuck?
Where are you getting burned?
Why do you feel that you don't belong?
And not all of that is tech.
Like I'm technical, some of that is community, some of that is fostering a welcoming community
for people that they feel comfortable in to ask those questions.
Like you said, you said at a conference, it feels like people are talking at you and you're
too scared to ask a question because you think the whole room is going to say, you don't
know how to make CSS into separate files?
Wow.
Sad.
And it's like, no, no, no, that's not the environment we want to create here.
We want to create an environment because we always say no stupid questions, right?
But do we really mean it?
Because it oftentimes feels like we say that, but we don't really mean it.
Because when people do ask, that to us might be an obvious question, the answer we give
is oftentimes like not helpful.
It's kind of like the intent behind it feels like, oh boy, I asked for something really
dumb now.
I should just go away and not, and then, and that's what happens.
People do go away.
They do stop speaking up inside a discord server on Twitter and in all these social
spaces on GitHub.
People are too scared to contribute on GitHub because anybody can see what I'm saying and
they're going to judge everything I say and what if my stuff is not good enough?
We should change the thinking around this.
We should change how we communicate this to people because opening a pull request, having
it closed is not the end of the world.
It is sometimes the thing you proposed was just not the right thing at the right time.
It's probably not your fault.
It's probably because you did not understand the problem because it wasn't documented well
enough.
You thought you found a problem that was actually intended in the way it is, but it wasn't communicated
well to you.
I ran into this two weeks ago where I opened up a request and somebody was like, no, that's
as intended.
I was like, well, that's not super obvious because for me, I was new to your API or to
your library and using it in this way, you didn't tell me how to import the thing into
my node file.
It was nowhere.
I had to figure it out on my own.
That's why I opened the pull request because I thought other people would probably run
into the same situation.
Oh no, that's as intended.
Can you explain why that's as intended?
Yeah.
I love those types of answers.
It's like, okay, that's by design.
Okay, well, can we unpack that?
Yeah.
Would you consider changing the design maybe a little bit as it's non-obvious?
I completely agree.
I actually did want to touch on something that you had mentioned to me a second.
I have to think about it.
There was something good that you had talked about in all of that.
There was a lot of good and there was a lot of gold.
I lost it, but we'll come back to it, but yeah, I completely agree.
So for somebody new, let's take a specific area.
Let's take web development.
What do you think are the important things for people to know when they get started?
If somebody came to you and said, Chiron, I'm doing X and I want to get into web development.
Where would you send them?
What would you tell them?
I know it's a broad topic, but...
I know.
Yeah.
I'll actually be honest, I'm not an engineer.
I work with engineers and I understand developer workflows and I understand technical stacks
and a lot of things.
And I actually myself have tried to learn to code a few times, but then it really is
something that you need to work at and it's not something that comes easy, I won't lie.
And so I feel like it's taking you time and it's taking a lot of energy.
That is the way it is.
It's not an easy process.
There is a high barrier to entry and learning curve to learning to code.
And so you're fine, you're on the right track.
There are a lot of really great communities that help and foster and support engineers
and like, for example, Serenity Barks, Code Newbies community, where it's like a safe
place for junior engineers to ask questions.
There's a lot of good content and resources out there, but there are really a lot of good
communities blanking on the community that I really love, that I started to learn to
code from.
So I know there's Learn with Leon, which is very popular, the 100 Devs one, and then there's
Free Code Camp.
Free Code Camp is amazing and they have a lot of resources and they have a really great
blog and they have a lot of stuff that they have a lot of courses like for on Udemy or
even on YouTube that are free that walk you through a real process.
A lot of the times the code is oftentimes decoupled from an end goal.
And then you don't essentially understand how it applies.
How does it apply in the real world?
What is it doing?
So a lot of the things that I've discovered is building a really small and mean app helps
you have like kind of an end goal and a place that you want to get to like I've ever like
card shuffling apps or things that like, eventually you learn how what this code when I'm writing
here looks like in a final product and why it's important, why all these steps are important
to get to an end place is really important to kind of completing that journey.
So it's not just theoretical, it's actually applied and you can experience that thing
that you learned in, you know, an end kind of well crafted project.
So that's something that I've like is highly recommended.
So if you're starting to learn to code and you're going through like these lessons, try
and find something lean and small.
And I really in the context of DevOps, again, that's the role that I'm like kind of really
active in.
But there's the concept of price and like the small wins in aggregate eventually translates
to big gains.
That comes from the Japanese supply chain kind of mindset.
And I really believe in that as well.
So every time you have like a small win celebrated and kind of see what you've learned, and then
eventually you'll find that all of those like small wins in aggregate, you'll find that
you made a lot of progress and that you know a lot more than you think that you do.
And you've made, you know, you've achieved quite a bit.
So that I think that's also important.
And so there are a lot of really great communities like CodeMovies, F3 CodeCamp, Learn with Leon,
100 Days, and a lot of things like that.
But there are also great tools and like I said, I'm exposed to a lot of really great
developer tools.
And one of the ones that I think is actually extremely interesting and I think that they
have a lot of potential in helping developers skill up is a tool called Wilco that was just
recently unveiled and came out and sell.
And what they're trying to do is create real world modules and environments that help engineers
have true access to production systems or real programs and collaborative workflows
and things that they can't necessarily learn from an Udemy course or from some kind of
self-learning module of some sort.
This provides them kind of more of a real world kind of experience, experiential way
of coding.
They have mock teams, mock data, production systems that they integrate with and other
things that provide you more of a skilling up opportunity for what it would really look
like to work in a real world engineering organization so that you can get to that place where you
feel confident enough to go and interview and talk about the things that you know how
to do in a real world environment.
I think that those are the things that are going to be coming, you're going to be seeing
more trends around how we take theoretical knowledge and get it to be applied in real
systems or help people bridge that gap to making it into the real world because that
is still hard.
There is still a lot of friction there and there's still a lot of self-learning and self-doubt
and don't feel that way.
It's not easy.
It's not a paved road yet.
Yeah, exactly.
I think that's the other thing that we didn't touch on really and that is the fact that
one of the other things that's part of coding is to work on a team and what does that mean?
What does that mean to work on a team?
People that's on GitHub these days kind of talk about GitHub as if everybody knows what
GitHub is and how to do it and how to use it and that's not true.
Not everybody does.
Even when you're just talking about the website itself, you're not even talking about terminal
and the depths of Git, you're just talking about GitHub itself.
What is a pull request?
What is an issue?
Why do I do an issue before a pull request?
What's up with that?
How does pull request review work and what does it mean if somebody is giving me feedback?
How do I incorporate that feedback?
That's often where the terminal has to come in because it's kind of tricky if you've opened
the pull request and now somebody gives you feedback, you have to amend it.
How do I do that?
I think there's a lot of education around that topic that needs to happen and I think
some of that, the only real way that you can get experience is by working on a project.
I feel like that's a loop that a lot of newbies get themselves into.
It's like, oh, I need experience.
How do I get experience?
I need experience, but how do I get the experience?
That's why I think a lot of communities do this and it's also something I constantly
do with the Mycelium Network and that is offering any kind of side project where people can
work together like you would work in a working environment.
Creating a project, defining the problem, defining the solution and then working from
there.
Okay, now what code do we need to write?
Okay, let's assign tasks to people to do and you'll open a pull request for your task and
then we'll have somebody that comes in and do code review for you and then it gets merged
and then it ends up somewhere.
What is that somewhere and how does it end up in that somewhere because that's the thing
I wanted to mention earlier that I find people ask so many times is, okay, I'm on my local
machine and I have this web page that you taught me how to build, how do I get it on
the internet?
Do you think we're in 2022, it should really be that easy and it kind of is if you know
the right tools, but if you don't know the right tools, that is a mystery.
But it's like, wow, I enter a URL and there's this website, how does that happen?
That is something that a lot of people don't know.
Yeah, I agree.
So that's what I was saying, you'll go to these tech conferences, you'll see tech talks,
but sometimes just culture.
What is a real world end-to-end CICV deployment to production process look like?
What does that look like?
What are the gates that are in the process?
What are the guardrails?
Where is the friction?
What is the interaction?
What does branch protection look like?
Why do I need this?
How do I work on a branch?
How do I merge it into, these are the processes that you only gain from real work.
It's not something that, it's the meta information, it's the metaverse of programming and coding
and some of this knowledge is just kind of inherent to senior developers that they don't
even remember that there are these really small gaps of like, yeah, okay, now how do
I actually deploy my local webpage to and connect it to a domain and then have it live
and breathe in the real world?
How do I even do this?
It's like these small little last mile steps that we forget that people need to be onboarded
to as well, even just on the process side or on the simple kind of closing the loop.
Okay, the code is done, everything is set up, the network, we have the cloud, everything
is there.
All right, now how do I bring all these pieces together?
What's the duct tape?
What's the magic?
Right?
People don't always know these things and that also comes back to the name of my company
is RTFM, right?
But that's exactly the problem, RTFMing, everything is just too hard.
There's too much information, right?
There's too many things to learn, there are too many aspects, you talk about people, there's
so many titles these days, these inflators are like full stack engineer and just getting
expertise in the front end or back end is hard.
Now you want somebody to be expert in everything and everything comes between the duct tape
between full stack and there's middle stack now these days, how do you connect front end
and back end?
How does my database actually talk to my webpage?
These are things that are not as intuitive as people imagine and think, right?
And cultivating this expertise takes time, they say that expertise takes about 20 years
to cultivate, right?
It's 20 years of hands-on working knowledge, they say to become an expert at something
you need about 20 years of experience and you are always learning, you're constantly
learning new things.
Even senior engineers like a little bit, oh wow, I had no idea that this new endpoint
could be exposed or this product, this could be used or this feature even exists, so don't
feel like, just because you're new that you're learning new things, you'd be surprised that
there are senior engineers that learn new things every single day.
And the tools are evolving and everything is evolving and everything is evolving under
our feet.
We used to work on servers, now we're in serverless, okay, what does that mean?
Everything needs to now be defined.
It's crazy, it's crazy how fast everything is moving and the expectation that you need
to know everything.
You can't know everything, you just can't.
No, you cannot, it's not possible.
I don't think our brains are made for that and I don't think it's an healthy way to do
it anyway because you'll fill your mind, your brain up with so much information that you
just have to unlearn constantly because this industry is not done, right?
It's not close to being done.
It's evolving, it's growing, we're doing stuff, then doing it differently because we think
it's better and then I need to end up going back to how we used to do it because turns
out this new idea wasn't so great or it wasn't as successful.
That is part of tech because tech is kind of a science, right?
You get a computer science degree and the reason I think, personally, it's associated
with science is because we're constantly experimenting and we're trying to find answers through experimentation
and as with science, oftentimes, it leads you to understand that you were trying to
solve the wrong problem and then you have to go back and say, okay, what is the real
problem because clearly I misunderstood it the first time.
If you think about the whole idea of static site generators and stuff like Dentalify,
that's not really new.
The way it's being offered is new and it definitely helps a lot but I mean, we used to do that
in the days when we FTPed stuff up to a server, you would have the static site on your local
machine.
It takes like two hours, your FTP is just like copying files and in the meantime, somebody
updated the file and it's like you have to restart, you got to restart and see, I remember
those things too.
I remember that.
Those were the days but yeah, so it's true, like the cloud or high speed internet and
all these things made all these processes faster but not many of them have actually
even evolved or changed that much, they just look different because okay, so now my files
are hosted, great.
When I have access to them, very, very easily, so the internet or cloud, but like kind of
the method, methodology, the framework, it's very similar and I think that kind of similarity
helps in that it helps lower the barrier of entry because it's familiar, right?
They say like kind of, even when you talk about like your web experience, right, a lot
of the web pages look the same because people have like this tendency to scroll in a very
specific way and they expect like the menu to be here and they expect the image to be
here and the more familiar it is to them, the easier it is for them to adapt, right?
And that's why Android was a clone of iPhone and I know a bunch of examples like that.
But yeah, so I agree, I think that a lot of the things that we try to change and evolve
and make completely different and do a hard reset on and then we discovered, okay, maybe
the older practices were the right ones, but they just need to be introduced into the new
world or have better experience or better interfacing or better support or backup or
cloud and be hosted and easily collaborated upon and so I think the world is moving to
the right place in terms of how we work together.
I think COVID has taught us a lot about that, but how to work in distributed remote, you
know, collaborative operations and I think a lot of the DevTooling being introduced puts
an emphasis on that and how you collaborate better, how you communicate better, embedding
like kind of communication into tools, commenting, context and a lot of things and I'm hoping
that that's going to be kind of a continuation and just going to get better from there.
I really do think Netlify took a well-known concept and they just implemented it better
and sometimes not the right thing to do.
Yes.
Mm-hmm.
No, for sure.
I take nothing away from Netlify.
I absolutely love what they do.
I love the product I use literally every day and they do a lot to educate people around
how to use their tools because I think that's what's also sometimes missing is people create
a great tool that they know how to use and some of it's obvious, but some of it's not
and I think a lot of questions people need to the industry have is when do I need to
start caring about X, when do I need to start understanding Y and I think that is something
I feel is definitely missing is a pathway to follow and I think one of the reasons why
there aren't very many of those is because it's really hard in tech because it's so diverse
because like you said, there's all these roles like front of the front, front end, middle,
back end, full stack, it's like, okay, cool, so first maybe I need to pick one of those,
do I?
It's like, no, not really, it helps, so it's hard and I think that's part of the reason
why there isn't pathways because it's hard to define a clear pathway, but again like
what Netlify has done, something old made it new and better, I think we need to incrementally
improve that as well, I think one of the other things where there's a lot of work needed
is testing, like even me, as a person who's been coding for quite a long time, how many
of my projects really have good testing, not a lot because it still doesn't feel like it
fits into my workflow, like there's all these modern tools and stuff but it's still some
of, doesn't just naturally fit in, it's still an afterthought and as soon as it becomes
an afterthought, you forget about it because other things take priority and you always
say, I'll still add testing, I'll still add testing but you end up never doing it, I mean
I work with some clients that have really big projects with little to no testing because
it's not easy, it's not baked into my workflow so I'm going to not do it because I need to
land this feature or I need to fix this bug and yeah, sure, if we had testing, we would
have found it earlier, maybe we would have been able to fix it quicker but because it
doesn't fit into my workflow, it's just never getting done.
You're right, that's the kind of thing that I even opened with, that's how oftentimes
people thought about things like security as well and so I'm happy to see that undergoing
a revolution as well and I think testing also needs to find its way and have a more native
and smooth transition into development processes, maybe automate the things that are obvious
but obviously a lot of the things around testing automation makes it feel like it provides too
many, same way as security, false positives, things that are irrelevant and it can never
really be a replacement for a human or manual intervention and then we're like, oh, we hate
testing, this sucks, I don't want it, it's too much friction and I need it.
But it probably also needs to undergo an evolution that makes it a lot more natively integrated
into processes because yeah, quality is important and not even just from the security side which
is like bugs and things like that, that can expose your user experience, wrongfully using
your product, enjoying your product, thinking it works well and those are things that are
critical as well so it's strategic, it's business critical so we have to think about how we
bring that to the forefront as well and there's so many areas that need to undergo this evolution
and I think they will, I think a lot of that is coming kind of to the front, developers,
decision makers and also with the growth and skill and size of everything that's happening,
there is a skill shortage, there's a gap and we need to be able to onboard our engineers
quickly, we need them understanding our tooling rapidly, we need them to bring value rapidly
and all of that can only happen but we simplify our tools and make them easier, easier to
adopt and learn and integrate well into well-known processes and everything needs to undergo
that, everything.
Yeah, this has been great.
I think I have two final things before we wrap up.
The first one is with all of this, like so many things going on, so many areas that need
improvement, so much to learn, how do you stay motivated?
I find it exciting to be honest, I think it's very, very interesting to see all this happening
and to have the opportunity, the privilege to see where we were and where we've gone
into, I'm old, I'm not young, I'm not young in this industry so I have had that privilege
of seeing kind of, yeah like you say, years ago we were copying files to FTP, now we're
working in the cloud and that's way better and so I have the hope that this is what keeps
you motivated and that things are only always improving and getting better.
The experience is something that's at the forefront, whether it's the developer experience,
user experience and making sure that everything is great because that's what matters eventually,
we want people using our product, we want people getting wrapped up easily whether it's
on the build side or on the user side and that keeps me motivated because I think that
it is an exciting thing to watch and see, to be a part of a trend and an industry that's
constantly evolving and changing, you're constantly learning and I like to be in microphones,
that also motivates me but yeah, it gets hard, there's friction, there are things that you
always constantly are learning, you'll never learn everything and like you said, you always
feel like there are gaps and things to overcome but the thing that should keep you motivated
is now a few things, first of all, community has become a really core piece of development
these days, there are almost no developer communities, developer languages or whatever
it is that don't have communities and there are plenty of people that will be happy to
help you and mentor you and once upon a time, we didn't have the internet, we didn't have
forums, we didn't have Reddit, we didn't have communities, we didn't have meetups, people
had to figure it out on their own, now you do have peers in the industry that you can
learn from and I think that's really exciting and that's keeping you motivated and have
friends to the journey that can join you and one of the things, now I'm remembering what
I wanted to say earlier is that I've always loved the Apache Software Foundation sentiment
and maybe they don't apply it as well as they should but the open, friendly, welcoming,
patient kind of mindset, zero tolerance for toxicity and I think a lot of communities
are enforcing these types of things that are being welcoming, friendly, patient, listening,
wanting to help and so I think that that should be motivated, don't think that you're alone
on this journey, don't think you're the only person that's had difficulty, don't think
that you're not good enough, don't let the imposter syndrome win and I think that is
something that I can really, I have so much appreciation for the people that take from
their time like you with this podcast and others and surrounded by and all the things
that have been built in order to make this easier, to make this transition easier, to
make people feel that they have a space and a safe space so that's wonderful and that
keeps me motivated.
That's awesome.
Thanks so much, Sharon.
I'm glad to be finding out this talk because it was really, really good.
Also in closing, is there anything you'd want to bring to the attention of people, any closing
words you'd like to share with the community out there?
Sure.
Yeah, so I run the TLV community, TLV community on Twitter and TLVcommunity.dev right now.
Our upcoming event is DevOps Days Tel Aviv, which is more on the system engineering side
but if you have something to share and you want to get involved, the CopyPapers is open
until August 31st and we'd love to have everyone from the global community, from the, for junior
talks to senior talks, it's from what I call noob to ninja.
Everybody is accepted.
We really want everybody to come and have a good experience and learn things so please
don't hesitate to either get involved and submit a talk or even just join us.
And our community as well, we're very, there are a lot of really great community initiatives
at least coming out at Tel Aviv, like Ops School, which trains junior operations engineers
and other things and if you're looking to get involved and have mentors, there's this
really great mentoring project that was started on Twitter and in the Tel Aviv area if you're
from Tel Aviv, where there's like this spreadsheet of people that have, that have emphasized
their expertise and who they're and the time available that they have for mentoring and
so you can tap into mentoring communities and there's plenty to learn and please don't
hesitate to reach out.
It's really, really important for you to feel like you have a community and you do.
Yeah, for sure.
Thanks so much and we'll put links to all of this obviously in the show notes.
Thanks for taking your time.
I really appreciate it and have a lovely rest of your day.
Thanks so much.
Thank you for listening to this episode of the My Senior Network Podcast.
If you're not already, please subscribe, star and leave a review for us in your podcatcher
of choice.
This helps others find us and helps us make a better podcast for you on this course.
You can also find and follow us on Twitter at MeetWeirdMyCindium and join the community
on Discord.
All the links are available in the show notes.
join the community on Discord at MeetWeirdMyCindium and join the community on Discord.
All the links are available on Discord at MeetWeirdMyCindium and join the community on