Welcome to the Marseillean Network Podcast, a podcast all about early-stage web developers
and the mentors and teachers that help them along the way.
Hey, Alvin.
Thank you so much for joining me today on this Thursday.
I'm always supposed to be on track for time this week.
Thanks so much for joining me.
I'm really looking forward to our conversation.
I am too.
Thank you so much for having me on.
Yeah, pleasure.
So, as I start with all my guests, I'm not going to tell your story.
I think you can do it better than I can.
So instead of that, I'm going to give you the floor and take as much time as you need,
as I always say.
Go as far back into your history as you'd like and bring us up to the current day and
just tell us a bit more about you.
For sure.
So, hey, I'm Alvin.
I've been in the industry for a while.
Primarily, I worked as a front-end type person.
So I was always driven by the same idea of like, how can I make like things that look
and feel nice to the user so that whether it's beautiful, fun, entertaining.
And that took like a few forms, I guess.
I worked on games, I worked on data visualizations, I worked on most recently designed systems.
And now, a new sort of turn in my career is I've been, since the month of May this year,
so about four months, four or five months, a developer advocate at Contentful.
Cool.
Yeah.
I like the design systems angle.
I wonder if you want to dig into that a little bit, because I know that is something that
I'm pretty passionate about.
I had a couple of clients that I was at.
They were playing very fast and loose with their brand.
And it's not, you know, it's not their fault if there isn't any structure.
But then, if you approach them as this idea of a design system, they're a little hesitant
because they're like, how much time is this going to take?
I was like...
Always.
What's the...
What's the value of it?
You know?
Yeah.
It's going to take a little bit of time.
But just let me paint you a picture of the future and what it might be like once you
have this thing in place.
Do you want to dig a little bit more into design systems and what they are and maybe
even try and answer some of those questions?
Yeah, for sure.
So for me, I guess what interested me in design systems is that it's the place where developers
and designers have to collaborate, right?
It's like...
And that's always been the sweet spot for me, where the more design-driven something
is, usually the more I like it.
And I found that design systems were this, but at the larger scale.
As much as I was interested in very large, complex front ends that had lots of moving
parts with 50 people working on something, a design system, on the other hand, is much
more interesting because you have your designers and your developers working together in making
something, right?
And that was always the cool thing for me.
In terms of, again, application for the brand, when a design system is well put together,
it's just really satisfying when you can create a sub page or a landing page really quickly
because you're just putting blocks together and then you're like, okay, I've got the boring
bits, done, and now I can focus on the more bespoke, interactive, interesting things.
Otherwise, if you're always trying to find the same nav and the same sub menu or whatever
and you're having to code that or just lift and shift that in a non-standard way, you
can just waste a bunch of time recoding the same things.
Whereas if you have everything that's ready, you could just say, okay, put the blocks together,
boom, nav, boom, headings.
Everything has the right font size, the right spacing.
You don't have to peer into Figma too much or Sketch or whatever, but everything's already
done for you.
So everything is neat and tidy very quickly.
But the bespoke bit that you need, then you have more time for it.
Did that make any sense?
100%.
No, 100% agree.
I think that is one of the big things about the design system because it's not just the
design, it's also the components that comes out of the design.
And those are actual living, breathing pieces of code that you can then compose together.
And I think maybe React was the framework that really started making friendly people
think about components, but I mean, now it's in everything.
It's actually baked into the web platform.
We have web components, it's in the name.
So I think the next evolution is, what do they call them?
Design tokens.
I think that's the next evolution of design systems.
And there's this ability to cross-share design tokens between systems like Figma, Benpot,
and then like your development environment where you literally export like a JSON definition
and you have these tools that can take that and generate code.
I used this one from Adobe where basically you have that and then you can tell it like
generate me the style sheets for, I put it in quotes because it's more than just style
sheets, for web, iOS, Android, blah, blah, and it's like just root all from the single
JSON thing.
And then once the designers make the changes in Figma, say for example, and they export
the latest version, it like just does like a automatic re-roll and I'm looking forward
to that being more of a thing.
It's still early days there, but at this point you have to do quite a bit of hacking to get
it to work really efficiently, but I'm looking forward to the future of what that can be.
So I noticed a post that you wrote called, learning to code in a time of crisis.
I love the title, it intrigues me, so I automatically want to know more.
And I think that probably ties into one of the other questions I often ask, which is,
what advice do you have for early stage web developers or developers in general on how
to stay motivated?
Right.
So I'm going to start with like the post, the blog post, learning to code in time of
crisis first, and then I'll sort of find advice from that.
So my idea with this post, which was interesting because I started writing it in 2020, in March,
when the whole world shut down, we know what happened, I had a couple of people ask me
whether it was easy to find a job as a coder and if it was something they could break into,
so I started writing it, started outlining it, and then I wasn't super happy with it
and I sort of shelved it because as you know, in 2021, the economy kicked back again, then
we had this boom in tech which seemed was going to last forever, but it didn't.
In 2022, the economy is in a pickle again.
And I had also another person ask me the same question and I was like, you know what, I'm
going to finish it, find another angle to it, and that's what I did.
So the blog post has a couple of things in it.
The first main point is the job market sucks right now if you're trying to break into it
as a beginner, but that doesn't mean it's impossible and you just want to be realistic
with it.
It's like even if you heard these stories maybe a year ago, two years ago, three years
ago of people going from zero to great coding job in three, six months, it may happen to
you again, but it's just less likely.
So just got to be realistic with the state of the tech market right now.
That doesn't mean, as I said, it's impossible, but just want to be realistic.
So that's like with the negatives.
With the positives though, the great thing is the tech industry is used to people coming
from a variety of backgrounds and going from the most random jobs to coding.
I think I have a bunch of examples there.
But yeah, so it's not a foreign thing to do, it's not to say that there's zero elitism
in the tech industry, it exists everywhere, but we're used to people jumping from different
careers so we will not be looked at weirdly or if you think your case is really unusual
like, oh, but I don't know, I'm coming from this very specific background, it's probably
someone else who did something similar.
That's one part and also with developers in particular and designers too, remote work
is definitely a thing now.
So if you think about it in a way that if you're looking for a job, you have access
to companies, of course, you can go as far as you want on the entire planet, some people
work across multiple time zones and everything, but even within your own country, even if
you think, okay, just within my own country, I can apply to pretty much any company there,
not any but like a ton of companies there who do remote work, that's a huge advantage
compared to whatever job, if you're a nurse or something that needs you to move your life
around, what about your partner, what about your children?
And that's amazing.
I mean, there's tons of companies that work across countries, across time zones, like
you in South Africa, you're in the same time zone as Germany, for example, so you could
work with a German company like me, right?
But even if you think at the smaller scale of like, okay, just my own country, that's
already a huge advantage and so they're good and there's bad and it's still a good thing
to learn, but just be realistic that the market is weird at the moment.
Yeah, what do you think is weird about it?
Do you think it's that maybe the opportunities that exist require a certain amount of experience
and that is the problem for early stage folks is they lack that experience and so while
there might be a shortage of skills, it's more a shortage of skills of experienced developers,
not so much new developers, or do you think companies are hesitant towards hiring juniors?
The problem right now is that there were a ton of layoffs, so you have a huge pool of
experienced coders that are on the market, so that's the problem.
If you have one opening, you'll probably get the most experience because you can, right?
Because there was all these layoffs happening, but again, it depends, it doesn't mean it's
impossible, it's just harder than it used to be when you had more of an equal distribution
of people of all levels entering the market.
Now you have this ton of layoffs, you have a ton of people with experience that are being
dumped into the markets looking for jobs at the same time, so it's harder.
I just hope it will balance out in the near future, but at least in the summer, just for
people listening to this in the future, since the spring of 2022, we had basically non-stop
big layoffs happening all the time, and we're recording this in September, early October,
so in the past four months, it's been non-stop, company X laid off 1,000 tech workers, company
B laid off 500, so it's just really hitting it hard, but I hope it will balance out.
But as you said, there's still a shortage of developers, people are still struggling
to find them, so that's not going to disappear, and more, as we know, technology is eating
our lives, so I don't see that stopping, but yeah, the market conditions are a bit weird
at the moment.
Yeah, that's a good point, yeah, I don't think about that, that's a very good insight.
So with that, with that challenge, I think already for early stage developers and people
switching careers and stuff like that, it's already stressful, a little scary, and now
you have this added thing that you just mentioned, where it's like, oh, now I'm competing against
somebody with five years experience, I'm stuffed, how would you, any advice on how to stay motivated
and just keep going, keep trying, don't give up?
For sure, yeah, I think keep at it, as you said, and be consistent, even if you'll, so
it's a bit of a weirdly worded way of saying it, but keep at it, be consistent, even if
you'll see inconsistency like everything else, because learning everything, your progress
will not be linear, so it's like learning a musical instrument or anything, sometimes
you're going to make a ton of progress in a couple of weeks, and then you really struggle
for like three or four, and then it's going to go up and down like this, and it's not
easy, and my own personal failure to be any good at any musical instrument can attest
to that, so yeah, somehow with coding it worked.
I guess with coding maybe it's easier to see progress, because you can visually see your
programs becoming more complicated, whereas maybe with a musical instrument you're just
getting a little bit faster, maybe I'm just making excuses, doesn't matter, but yeah,
so going back to the word of advice, yeah, keep at it, it will be inconsistent, and keep
the end goal in mind, and have an achievable end goal, so if you think, okay, I want to
build up a portfolio of work that includes Project X, make sure you have that in mind,
and you keep thinking, okay, I'm moving towards that goal, rather than just like have this
abstract thing like, I'm going to learn Python, you know, like, yes, you know, but it's very
easy to fizzle out when you have a goal like this, just learn Python, what does that mean,
you know?
Yeah, I'm definitely a very goal-oriented person, I've mentioned it in previous episodes
of the podcast, I find it very difficult to learn something for the sake of learning it,
I always need an outlet for it, like I need, you know, either something I can contribute
to that uses the technology I'm learning, so I can like apply what I learn, or just
scratching on my own itch, or even make up my own little project, even if it's like just
for me, just as a means of using the skills I'm learning, if I feel I'm just like making
the little food app that you're doing as part of the course, it doesn't feel as fulfilling
to me, and because a lot of the courses like feed off each other, which is good, it's like
music where, you know, the music you make today is influenced by the music from the
past, and so sometimes you'll hear a band and you'll say, I hear a little bit of Rolling
Stones in there with weeks with a little bit of Beatles, and it's good, I mean, it's good,
I heard, I don't know, the artist Grimes, I listened to an interview with her, I'm not
a fan of her music or anything, but she's a very fascinating person, and she says, music
is like having a conversation with those who came before you, and I think that was really
just beautiful, and so yeah, I think the same thing here, I do think it's good that these
course materials are feeding off each other and improving through that, but maybe they
should look at expanding the portfolio of examples you build, so it's not like you're
building just another food app, another to-do app, because that can get tedious.
I wanted to jump into a different problem, now I'm thinking if I should first flip to
a different topic or we should just keep going, I think let's just keep going on this road.
So I think you've highlighted some of these things, but maybe we can dig into it more.
From your perspective, what do you think are the biggest problems in the tech industry?
Yeah, so I generally don't like thinking absolute statements like their biggest, but I think
a big problem we have that is recognized still is diversity, even though we've improved a
lot.
Don't get me wrong, the tech workforce of today looks nothing like the tech workforce
of five, six, seven years ago, really improved a lot in that regard, but it's still a problem.
We still know we need to have more diverse voices and it kind of feeds off with what
we were talking about with having people from different backgrounds, right?
The more we have people that come in with a fresh eye from a random job before, the
better our product is going to be, right?
And so this is something that the tech industry knows there's a problem and we're trying to
fix it, but it's more aware that there's still a problem.
And then coming back, I guess, to what we were saying, this is also where it's interesting
where people would hire you because you were talking as a beginner, because when you were
talking about earlier about how the hell do I compete with someone who has five years,
maybe even if you don't have as many actual years, maybe there's something about your
background and about yourself and about the way you see design and accessibility that
is unique to you and someone who's been working on a very specific thing for five years cannot
contribute to the company and the product.
So that also is, I guess, like a beacon of hope, I guess, for people breaking in, trying
to break into the industry.
Yeah, I think that leads me to a different topic also, which is interviews.
And I think there is where we have another problem with tech, and I think this one might
be very tech specific.
I think generally the diversity problem is not just a tech problem, it's very visible
in tech and it's been made very visible and that's good.
I mean, it needs to be visible before anybody's going to do anything about it.
It's like we saw with COVID, like it was very visible that we have a problem, like the world
rallied around it.
So that's important.
But I think the other side with the interviews is if you take a junior through the same interview
process as somebody with five years experience, generally the person with five years experience
are going to win every time.
Because if you don't ask those questions, like what you said, like, why do you bring
to the project that's unique, if you don't dig into that side of it and you just focus
on the wide-forged algorithm things, the junior is going to lose that interview every time.
And I can see how that can be demotivational.
So I think with tech interviews, the one thing that we need to, but I think this is also
a little bit, I don't want to be the person who always puts the burden on the other person
and like give the recruiters an out.
But I do think as an applicant to a job, you need to speak to those things.
You need to speak to what you can bring, not just from a technical perspective, but from
how you think about stuff.
And I think one of the previous folks I spoke to, Adelson Sandoval, he made a point of that,
like how important it is to understand the company that you're applying to, understanding
their technology and maybe even coming to the table with some ideas because you've taken
the time to research what the company does, what their goals are.
And it's easier, of course, if the company has an open source aspect to them, because
you can literally see the code, you can literally see what they do.
And through that, you might see some stuff.
But I think also just in general, companies should be open to the idea that a junior can
bring something to the table that a senior might not, even if it's just in the way that
they're going to ask questions about stuff that other people have stopped thinking about,
because it feels like it's just part of your DNA now.
Yeah, absolutely.
I'm a huge proponent of hiring juniors.
I think there's lots of values.
It's someone with fresh eyes.
That's what it is, really.
And that has a ton of value, especially if you're a company of the same kind of people
who have been building the same product for a while.
It's hard to see what's going on with fresh eyes.
And coming back to what you said about maybe not liking to always throw the burden to someone
else.
But the someone else is us, though.
It's developers when we're hiring others.
It's like when you have an opening in your team.
It's us knowing, do we really want to give them a four-hour take-home test?
Do we really need that?
It's us pushing back.
Or something I'm also a big advocate of is if we do think, because it's a more senior
position or whatever, that a three-hour take-home test is the way to go, then pay the person.
So yeah, I feel like it's on us.
It's on us developers thinking in terms of recruiting.
It's not just the recruiters.
It's how we word our job description as well.
Do we need to have so much like...
There's even internal jargon sometimes.
Sometimes I see this.
And it's like we're part of the Prometheus group within Facebook or whatever.
And I'm like, what the hell is a Prometheus group?
Why do I care?
It's an applicant.
And it's like sometimes you see things like this.
And yeah, it's on us to make sure that we're...
We're always super keen to share our job posting on LinkedIn and whatever and be like, come
work with me.
And I do that too.
Don't get me wrong.
But it's also on us to make sure that the job description we share makes sense.
And that we have our hiring process nailed and we're not like, oh, what are we doing?
I don't know.
Let's give them a three-hour home test.
What?
I don't know.
Let's do a to-do list as well.
Yay.
But then when you're an applicant, if you have three companies giving you that, it starts
to add up and it's...
That's it.
It starts to add up and it starts to be annoying.
Whereas if it's more like, okay, we're just going to come on Zoom for an hour, have them
walk through code or just do a simple code example of like, hey, can you fetch something
from the GitHub API, walk us through it?
Something like that.
That's a way...
In my opinion, that's a way better interview process because you're not requiring a ton
of commitment.
You're still looking at how the person is coding, but you're not placing this huge burden
on them to find three hours spare time and polish an app and do whatever.
And again, that multiplied by every company you're applying to, right?
So yeah, I feel like it's on us as developers with a bit of experience who are going to
be in the position to hire someone else to make sure that our process is as accessible
as it can be.
Yeah.
That's very good.
I wonder with that hour long interview where you do something, would you give somebody
like a hint as to what the question might be?
You don't necessarily will tell them you're going to be using the GitHub API, but maybe
you'll tell them we're going to have this hour long conversation and basically as part
of that, we will have you do a request to an API to get some data and display it on
a webpage.
Would you put that in?
I think it depends on, again, the seniority level, what kind of things you're solving
because for example, sometimes you're more interested in the presentation, right?
So you're like, okay, we'll give you like with that same example, right?
So you can be really interested in how someone writes the tests for this request to the API.
That could be like a primary focus or it could be, yeah, just get something from this API,
but what we really want you to focus on is make sure the, I don't know if you have a
search or something or whatever you're displaying from the API, make sure that it's accessible.
So it really depends what you're looking for in the role, but yeah, I think you drop hints
based on what you're trying to have them focus on versus if it's a pure front end and you
want someone who really knows about accessibility and it's something that they've said in their
CV as well, you don't want them to spend 20 minutes figuring out there's a missing header
to that API or whatever.
You could just help them with that because that's not the primary thing.
Gotcha.
Yeah, that sounds like a very healthy approach.
I really like that.
I'm glad more people did that, more companies.
That's good.
I'm glad you've said that and now it's out there for people to listen to and take note.
This leads us into this next question, which is I noticed a tweet from you about CascadiaJS
and they mentioned that they post all the recordings of their events because they believe
in open sourcing knowledge.
Love that, by the way.
And so I wonder, what are your thoughts with regards to open source, the open source ecosystem
and its role in developer education?
Because especially I think it touches on that topic previously, which we talked about, about
Junior's lack of experience, lack of working experience.
Can open source play a role here?
For sure.
As you mentioned before, with open source, what's great, you can see real code.
You can see if someone has a small project, they open source it.
You can see, okay, this is how this specific app works.
It allows you to explore and to see a real code in action, which is great.
Especially now with things like Netlify and Versailles, it's a lot easier to host things
than it was before because before it was like, oh, I have to do whatever.
People tend to just have a GitHub and that just automatically publishes to Netlify or
something and it makes it easier to say, oh, okay, I got this code and it's powering this
page.
And you know, there's no in between.
This is the build step.
It's all in there and it's all visible.
So that's great.
I feel like in terms of developer education, though, we now have more of a curation problem
than a number of resources problem.
I feel like there's a ton of knowledge and it's fantastic.
We're extremely lucky that we have tons of people writing tutorials in their spare time
on their blogs and stuff.
So there's a lot of knowledge going around.
But we might have more of a, as I said, curation problem in that we need to figure out how
to triage all the tutorials and everything to make sure, okay, this is what I need to
build a specific thing.
But yeah, otherwise, I think it's fantastic.
Yeah, I agree 100% of that.
I think Riku from the very first podcast said, you feel like you're this little drop that
fell into this ocean and you don't know if it's some up or down or left or right.
Because you're like drowning, drowning in information.
I think we are there.
And I think one of the projects that we are undertaking as part of the Mycelium Network
is the web workbook, which is not meant to be, let's try and do a better MDN.
No, it's the opposite.
Let's, let's, let's curate content.
And let's, let's define pathways, topics, technology paths.
And let's as a, as a community, share things that have helped us and let's try and make
it easier for people to know, okay, I've finished this part, where do I go from here?
What are the content that I can trust?
Who are the people I should be following that shares really good, that has a teaching style
that works really well, and also finding different ways of learning because not everybody likes
to read, not everybody likes to watch a video.
Some people like me are very, very practical.
So you want something that has a practical aspect to it.
So kind of trying to curate stuff around topics, technologies and pathways.
It's a big, it's a big undertaking, but I think I'm hearing it more and more and more
that this is what is needed.
Like speaking to, to early stage developers, it's, it's almost, I don't think I've spoken
to one that has not said this.
So the fact that you also brought it up is just like, it's clear that that is something
that's needed.
And I'm really excited about that project, but you know, it's still early days and there's
a lot, there's a lot to do, a lot of planning, there's a lot of planning.
And I think that's one of the things that is interesting about people who are getting
into code is they don't realize how big a part of the job that is, is planning.
Sure, you're going to write a lot of code probably, but you're also going to spend a
lot of time planning before you write all the code.
Friend of mine, Peter has the famous thing where he says, writing the code is the easy
part.
Understanding the problem and finding a solution, that is, that is the hard part.
And then it's almost like you take your crypt notes and you just turn it into code.
It's, it's oversimplified, of course, but I like the statement, I like the way he phrases
it.
Yeah, that's really cool.
So I, another thing that I saw about you, and it makes me think that you are somebody
and I in that same camp that like ethical tech or like are passionate about ethical
tech.
You mentioned on the rise of Signal, I use Signal myself.
I've used it before the web app, the WhatsApp debacle, but I kind of still used WhatsApp
at that point because some of the family and things were on there, you know, that's the
common problem, but like I've gotten off all of that stuff.
I just decided that for me personally, I need to, I need to put my money where my mouth is.
That's not entirely correct, but you know what I'm trying to say?
So I like to hear your views on what you think about ethical tech and its role in improving
the tech world and the world maybe even in general.
Yeah.
So this, so you're talking about the blog post that I wrote as well about like, again,
the rise of Signal and the, again, my thesis there was that when Signal got the spotlight,
it already had all the ingredients to succeed.
Basically it had roughly the same features of WhatsApp.
It was already a polished product because the problem you have with more ethical tech
in general, and you could think of this as in the broadest sense possible of like it's
more ethical because it's open source, because it doesn't have like a giant weird company
behind it or whatever.
So the problem we have with usually with this type of tech is that it's just not as good.
Like it doesn't have like the same level of visual flair or whatever than the mainstream
thing.
So people are kind of stuck with like the old thing because the usability is not right.
And when Signal had its moment, it's what I put in the article as well, it had a big
boost because Elon Musk tweeted just two words, use Signal, right?
And it's credited with like, suddenly all the newspapers were talking about it and like
he already has a huge account, but people also like retweeted it to hell.
But my thesis is that if he had tweeted, use Linux, no one would care.
Because Linux is not there yet in terms of like, oh, I can just, it's just like, I can
just flip a button and suddenly my, I have a perfect, you know, I have the same thing,
I have the same apps, everything looks great.
And it's very easy to install.
Like I know I might get some heat from like Linux users from this, but like, it's not
as easy as, you know, just like a Mac, things are not as intuitive.
Again, there's lots of progress being made there.
I don't want to like, you know, undermine that.
Like this also got a lot more accessible than it was.
Like, you know, in the, if you're talking about like Linux, even 10 years ago or even
the worst in the like 2005 ish, it was impossible.
You had to like go into the command line thing to install whatever, but like, yeah.
So it's getting better, but we're still, we're still have ways to go.
And that was the idea of the blog post about ethical tech in general.
To me, it's usually when like what you want in tech is to as much as possible is for incentives
to be aligned, right?
So to give you a counterexample, that's not the case with social media, right?
They have no incentive to, I don't want not to like, I'm not going to name a specific
company, but they have no incentive to make media that's actually increase, you know,
that is social.
What they want to do is put you on, is for you to stay on the platform for as long as
possible because you can see more ads, right?
And they do this with, you know, by creating outrage, fear, whatever, you know, controversy.
And that's not by making a media that makes people sociable and, you know, people want
to interact.
Because if you just see some funny, you know, good vibe things for 10 minutes and you leave,
that's not what they want.
You know, it's not in their interest, right?
So as a result, the incentives are completely misaligned, whereas I'm going to like use
the example of another company that I like.
And I think I can start to recommend because they're starting to be as good as the alternative,
like with ProtonMail, for example, like they're all about like building an email that's private.
The day they are caught selling ads, everyone of their customer will leave.
So they have, you know, their interests are aligned with what they're preaching to be,
right?
It's like we want to make a private email.
So as a result, we know they can sell data or they can be hacked because the day that
happens, they know they're going to lose like 50% of their customers at least.
And again, like talking, using the example of ProtonMail, like if we had this conversation
two years ago, I would not be able to recommend ProtonMail to you because they didn't have
a calendar, like, you know, it didn't have like things like dark mode.
It still looked a little bit clunky.
Like if you received, again, a Google Calendar invite, you couldn't do anything with it.
Now you could just press the same button that you have in Gmail that says, yes, I would
like to attend.
Boom, you press that and that's it.
So it's a similar enough experience that it's an alternative that's ethical and good, right?
It's like you're not losing too much by like switching to the ethical product.
Yeah, and I think there's another case happening right now with Penpot and Figma.
Yeah, yeah, that's exactly right.
Yeah, Figma was bought by Adobe.
A lot of people are not happy about that, to say the least, and I mean, I think it's
a complicated one because it's not like Figma is not a good fit for Adobe as a company.
It is the history of Adobe and what they've done to products that they've purchased.
That's the scary part here.
And even though the CEO, Figma, said that, no, no, no, we're going to operate as an independent
company and make our own decisions, but we do get access to all of this power of Adobe
that they've developed over the years.
It sounds good, but I don't know how true that really is.
That's what everyone thinks.
It's like, yeah, sure.
Yeah, you got 20 billion for sure.
Sure.
Yeah.
And then yesterday I saw Penpot announced they have an $8 million investment seed round,
which means their blog post literally said, our time has come.
And I'm really excited about that.
And I have personally started using the two tools in tandem because like you said, when
the WhatsApp thing happened, Signal had all the ingredients to just take its place.
Penpot is close, but not quite there.
Like I found some bugs which I'm raising.
Like this is open source.
It's awesome.
I can just go and tell them, this is the thing I'm seeing and maybe I can maybe even help
fix the problem.
Because currently if I drag an SVG into it and some of the elements has color, all the
color disappears and they either render them invisible or white or it renders that it's
all black.
And then you have to go in and edit it in Penpot.
So there's a bug there.
But then the other thing that I miss badly is auto layout.
That is not in Penpot yet and that is a big feature.
And then I think the community plug-in stuff that the ecosystem that Figma has built, that's
something that's missing as well.
But with them having this $8 million investment and being open source and having a community
that's now like, yeah, we need to support this project.
I think all these gaps can be filled very, very quickly.
And they are going to be filled very, very quickly.
So I'm really excited about that and I'm definitely following that and seeing how I can help make
Penpot be the successor of Figma.
But with ProtonMail, I've been actually toying with that idea because I did see their announcement
when they're like, now we have a VPN, we have a drive kind of thing, like Google Drive,
we have calendaring, we have better, our email is better.
And I tried it for a bit and it looks beautiful.
And it has some functionality actually that Gmail doesn't.
And the company I run called Mechanical Ink, I'm in the stage where I'm trying to define
what the company, what I want the company to be because I don't want it to be another
agency.
I don't want that.
At the moment, it kind of is because it pays the bills, right?
But that is not the long-term thing.
What I want it to be is a company that is heavily involved in open source and in ethical
civic tech.
And I need to find a way to be able to do that while creating job opportunities and
being able to sustain my own, me and my family and my children.
But as part of that, I mean, cause on the table, I use Google Workspace, right?
For my company stuff.
And I am considering switching to Proton because with what my future vision for the company
is, I need to, again, put my money where my words are and say, I'm not going to use Google's
product for this.
I'm going to use an alternative, an ethical alternative because one does exist and only
use tools that don't fit that bill when there really isn't an alternative.
And then asking the question, is there a way that Mechanical Ink and the communities I
build can help create this ethical alternative or plant the seeds so that people can come
together and create these ethical alternatives?
Wow, that was fun to talk about.
So in the same kind of vein, has there been any person, book, event, anything like this
that was impactful in your life just in general or maybe tech specific?
Yeah, so just to wrap up what we said about like ethical tech, I think an important point
too is that it doesn't have to be a full culture key switch right now.
Like what you're talking about, like with Penpot, for example, like right now, Figma
hasn't changed, but we know that if one year something really bad happens, like what everybody
is fearing, which is it's being integrated with the Creative Suite, which is what everyone
is like, please don't make me install Creative Suite, right?
But if that happens in a year, Penpot had a year from now to get it stuck together.
And it's kind of the same thing.
You could say, okay, I'm looking at Proton right now, and maybe in a year I'll switch.
And it's kind of the same thing for Penpot for all these things.
So it's important to know that to have them in your radar, to keep checking as opposed
to go, oh, let me see, can I do a culture key switch today?
And you download it, and it doesn't work, and you forget about it forever.
I've done that too.
Don't get me wrong.
But sometimes it's a bit of an easy thing to go...
Because it's easier for your mind.
You don't want to have this thing lingering of like, maybe I should switch to something
one day.
So it's easier to go one day, look at it, and go, okay, right, is this the most optimal
thing today?
You look into it, it's like, nope, moving on.
But you can say, okay, maybe let's check it in six months or a year.
And also, as you're doing, just sharing something, they shipped something, you were talking about
your SVG bug, when they fix it, if you share it, that's it, it's a little boost, even if
you may not be using them already because of what you said, auto layout.
To go back to your question about was there a person or an event or something that really
impacted my career, I think I will say all the managers that gave me a chance, even if
I didn't specifically fit the profile, I did lots of various things.
And I feel like it also comes back to what we were saying about hiring people with diverse
skill sets and not necessarily the perfect background.
It happened to me a few times, I was lucky that someone was like, even if you don't have
the perfect previous experience, I feel like you'll be a good fit here in the team.
And that happened more than once, and every time that really just helped me a lot.
I love that, I love that when people are open to giving you a chance and saying, let's see
what you do, and then let's check back in a month.
And if you show that you are a curious person who's willing to learn, let's keep going.
I think companies need to be more open to that.
So for, like I mentioned, this web workbook project, it's going to be very content heavy.
And so we're going to be building it using Hugo as the static site generators aspect
of it.
But then we've got a community license from Contentful.
And so we intend to use Contentful for our CMS.
So I've read quite a bit about Contentful, and I've used a bunch of other ones like Netlify
CMS, Forestry, and stuff like that.
Can you talk to how Contentful is different, like what sets Contentful apart from all these
other things?
Because I know there's a lot of these things that's jumped up.
Yeah.
So that's the great thing about being a developer advocate and not a salesman, is that I don't
have to give you a big sales pitch.
What I'll say is Contentful, as you said, I'm glad you're going to be using us, but
even if not, that's fine.
So we're a headless content platform that helps all kinds of clients.
So I think what I'll say is the great thing about Contentful is we've been at this for
a while.
It's one of the first companies in that space in having this idea of having something headless,
having blocks of content, rather than moving from the old paradigm of this is a page.
Everything in WordPress, for example, is a page, so you're with that structure, and you're
hacking around with short codes or whatever.
With Contentful, we have these entries and content types, which can be anything you want,
and that gives you the great flexibility.
So yeah, I'm glad you're using us.
Yeah, I'm looking forward to it.
So I'm thinking about which way to go next.
I think I want to switch on, I noticed that you mentioned your coach also at Codebar.
I have not heard about Codebar before, strangely enough, and I had a quick look at it and it
looks interesting, but you know more about it than me, so I'm going to ask you to inform
me about Codebar, what you do there, and what their mission is, and stuff like that.
For sure.
So I'm still a new coach too.
So I started in about November, December of 2021 as a coach.
So Codebar is basically a series of meetups that, historically, before COVID, happened
in specific cities.
So you have one in London, in Berlin, in New York, in Edinburgh, I think there's one in
Paris too, anyway.
So in each of these cities, it's a meetup to help people learn to code.
So people who are learning to code come in with their problem, which could be anything,
and they're like, hey, can I get help?
And someone, a coach, will help them with that problem for two hours.
And that could be anything.
It could be, hey, I'm doing the free code camp, I'm stuck on chapter three, I'm trying
to load an image and it doesn't work, and you're like, okay, sure, we'll fix that.
Or it could be something, sometimes it's way more involved and like, hey, I already have
this React app, but when I do this thing, I'm trying to query this thing and everything
breaks.
And it's like, okay, cool, let's have a look at this.
And they try to pair coaches with skills.
So when people register in advance, they're like, hey, I need help with Python.
And we're like, well, and Codebar tries to make sure that there's someone who knows Python
in the room, which is easier.
Even though you can usually figure it out, because as an experienced coder, especially
if it's an easier problem, sometimes it works across languages, but they try, Codebar tries
to optimize the coach's skills with what the student needs.
And historically, it was very much oriented towards underrepresented people in the industry.
So yeah, the way I coach is on Discord and on Zoom, so you could just rock on to, I think
it's pretty much open to any cities now.
Like I've coached in Berlin, I've coached in London, even though I'm in neither city.
A bunch more meetups are happening in person now.
So I've been coaching less, plus also other engagements made it difficult.
But yes, so that's the idea.
That's interesting.
So it's almost like this group of mentors that is just available to you when you get
stuck.
Yeah.
That's really, really cool.
And sorry, and they try to pair one to one all the time, at least.
So sometimes you might get two students.
It happens when there aren't enough coaches, but usually they're really good at making
sure that if they got 10 students, they'd make sure we have 10 coaches.
That's really interesting.
I'm definitely going to have a look at that a bit more.
That sounds like a good fit for our community, for sure.
Yeah.
Okay.
I want to dig into something different, maybe similar, maybe different.
So when you announced that you were joining Contentful, you pinned a tweet.
And part of that tweet is that you mentioned that this was after the long break.
So it made me curious about what was the reason behind that long break?
Because let me preface this by why I find that interesting.
I personally have had many, many struggles and continue to do with mental health in general,
anxiety, things like this.
And sometimes it gets to you.
It drains you.
It makes you tired and you do feel like you need a break.
Not always possible.
Sometimes you have to grin and bear through it, but sometimes you're either going to take
that break or your body's going to force you to take that break in unpleasant ways.
So I was curious, and I've spoken to other people also where burnout's been real.
Like Ian Douglas is somebody I spoke to that almost quit tech because he was so burned
out.
So I was curious if maybe there are echoes of that in the story.
So if you want to dig into that.
Yeah.
I'm lucky.
It's never been like a forced thing.
I was getting tired.
Like, I mean, let's be real.
Like the world is upside down and has been for two years.
So that doesn't help.
But yeah, I was, yeah, I feel like I just wanted to change.
So before, as I said in the intro, I was like a regular front end developer and I wanted
to become a developer advocate.
So I applied to a bunch of places and then luckily Contentful said yes, which was fantastic.
And yeah, so in between leaving my old job, which was very hard, like I really liked my
team and everything, but I felt like I needed to change.
I was getting a little, yeah, a little tired of the whole thing.
Like, yeah, just like, yeah, like mental health wise, it became harder.
I feel like they're probably, as you said, just like accumulation of the, you know, the
last two or three, the last two odd years.
Yeah.
So in between, I made sure to have some time off in between my last job at the Wall Street
Journal and Contentful.
So yeah, so I had about five weeks ish between, I don't have the dates right, but like about
five weeks between.
So it's not that long.
It's long, especially if you compare it to like in America where they have like two weeks
and that's it.
That's it for the year.
That's all you take off.
But yeah, so it's long, but it's not extremely long.
And during those five weeks, four or five weeks again, I went on the big road trip around
the UK and it was fantastic.
So yeah, that's how it, there was a really clean, may not be that long a break, but it
was a very clean break because I didn't basically didn't, almost didn't code for like three
weeks and it was just a completely, a complete change in that environment as well.
Okay, cool.
Thanks for sharing that.
So I think in closing, and this one leads kind of nicely into it, why do you enjoy doing
outside of the tech world?
I know a lot of times the answer is I still do tech.
If that's the case, that's fine, but I'm curious, like what do you do when you're not doing
tech?
Yeah.
So there's, like everyone else, I really like like traveling.
I'm lucky that I get to do a lot more of that now as a developer advocate, which is fantastic.
I like things to do with music, as I alluded to earlier with like my failure to be good
at any musical instruments, so like playing it, listening to it, attending concerts.
Another thing is, I guess, kind of like your answer a little bit is that I just like learning
about things on the internet in general.
So it's not necessarily coding.
Like I have a side project like everyone else, let's not be, let's not lie there.
Sometimes I have multiple and you know, it happens.
But yeah, I just like getting into like random topics, like in like I think for about like
maybe about a year now, I've got really into like musical theater and I just learned everything
as much as I could about it and like learning the history of it, how different like composers
like relate to each other and like just musically also was just extremely rich discovery.
So like stuff like that, I also really like, which is kind of like doing tech a little
bit, but not exactly.
Yeah.
What is it about travel that you enjoy?
I mean, it's a pretty, I guess, standard answer is like you're, well, it takes you out of
your environment, which is great also for like, you know, it's for your mind and everything
else.
Like that's really good to, you know, to see other things and it's just, you know, learning
about like and seeing just how other cultures work, how, you know, every, you know, every
country works.
You can, you also see a lot of blind spots, which is interesting of like stuff you didn't
think about when you come to another country, you're like, oh my God, they totally fixed
it.
Or like, oh my God, this thing is absolutely terrible in this country.
How did like, we figured this, we figured this out 10 years ago.
How come this country hasn't, but like, it goes both ways.
And yeah, it's just, it's just really good for, you know, just your mind and also just
seeing different things, like, you know, in like seeing completely different nature and
like different people, customs, it's just so interesting.
Yeah.
I agree.
I wish I didn't have as much of an impact on our carbon footprint as it does.
And I mean, sometimes, sometimes you can find beauty and uniqueness within your own country
and you don't have to necessarily get on a plane, not, not unless you're driving an electric
car.
It's not like cars don't have an impact on, but I think they have less of an impact, less
of a carbon footprint than a, than a big ass airplane.
Oh, thank you so much, Alvin.
This has been really a good conversation.
I enjoyed it and I'm kind of sad to be, you have to end it a little early, probably, probably
get going for a while, but yeah, I am going to die without electricity and internet for
a while.
So there's a problem that we haven't solved that a lot of other countries have solved.
Yep.
But yeah, thank you so much for, for taking some time out of your day to speak with me.
I really appreciate it.
And I'm going to look into a lot of these things that you've mentioned and I'll be following
all your work on Twitter and Polywork and everywhere where you are.
Thanks so much.
No, thank you.
And I'm happy to be on again, you know, to have another, another chat for sure.
Thank you so much for having me.
For sure.
It's a huge pleasure.
Thanks, Alvin.
Thank you for listening to this episode of the My Senior Network Podcast.
If you're not already, please subscribe, star, and leave a review for us in your podcast
feature of choice.
This helps others find us and helps us make a better podcast for you on this course.
You can also find and follow us on Twitter at networdmysindium and join the community
on Discord.
All the links are available in the show notes.