Welcome to the Mycelium Network Podcast, a podcast all about early stage web developers
and the mentors and teachers that help them along the way.
Hey Chris, welcome to the Mycelium Network Podcast.
Hey man, thanks for having me. It's good to be on here.
Yeah, thanks. I know you a long time. We knew of each other, I think, for a very long time,
and then we finally met, I think, when you started at Mozilla. Was that it?
I think so. It was 2013, although I seem to remember that we were talking about web
standards and JavaScript and stuff way back when I worked at Opera, because if you recall,
when we did the learning area on MDN, that was pretty much the kind of the next step
from my original educational project, which was the open the web standards curriculum at Opera,
and I got you to write some content for that back in about 2008 or 2009 or something. So,
you know, it's been a very long time. I think the number of grey hairs in our beards are testimony
to, you know, all of the blood, sweat and tears that we've poured into this industry.
Yeah, that's for sure. That's for sure. But it's still a good, I think it's still a good industry
to be in with all the problems that it has. For sure. So, to get us started, tell us about
who is Chris Mills, what you've been up to, what got you to where you are today, and, like,
maybe a little bit of looking forward as well. Okay. So, like all of the best people in the
open standards community, I didn't do any kind of formal education in development or programming
or computer science or anything like that. I was always super interested in technology
from when I was really young. I do remember doing my first bits of programming on a ZX Spectrum 48
plus back in probably the late 80s or something, and that was good fun. Although I do remember
like the sheer amount of lines you had to write just to, like, create, like, an eight by eight
square, you know, an eight by eight pixel character on the screen, and moving it was really,
really challenging. And, you know, you didn't have, like, clever things like events and
moving in terms of mouse cursors and things back in those days. But anyway, this was not intended
to be one of those geekier than thou conversations. But, you know, it's been a bit of a
challenge. But yeah, so at school, I always loved science, and I ended up doing a degree in
biochemistry. And just towards the end of that, I started getting really interested in something
called bioinformatics, which is the study of atoms and molecules and other such things with the help
so we used to download these great big data files off this database in Switzerland, which were like
the exact structural information for different molecules. And then you used to have a local
program which would actually render that to show you like a typical kind of, you know, ball and
socket diagram. And you could do things like you can go, okay, well, if I change this amino acid
in that protein chain, it's got different, you know, attraction, and it's got different positive
and negative attraction values. So how does that change the way that the whole protein folds up
and structures itself? So stuff like that was quite fun and geeky and interesting. But yeah,
didn't really have much luck getting a job in like chemistry or biomedical science type stuff. So I
decided to go for a job at a book publishers instead, and it was Rocks Press. I don't know
if you remember those folks, but back in the day doing books about ASP and ASP.net and stuff.
It was those red book covers with the really ugly author faces all over the covers.
But yeah, that was the place I ended up and did a bunch of books about
web standards and about all sorts of stuff. It was there that I met Bruce Lawson, who has been
one of my long standing partners in crime in the open standards industry. And we started the
Glasshouse imprint, which was one of the first publishing imprints dedicated to open standards
books. And then around 2003 or so this is Rocks Press went horribly bankrupt, and I ended up
working for these nice folks called A Press over in California. And it was there that I ended up
becoming managing editor of Friends of Ed. I don't know if you remember Friends of Ed at all, but
they were. I do, I do. Yeah. Originally did books about Flash and Photoshop, but we kind of turned
it into turn that around and turned it into a an open standards book publisher. So did a whole
bunch of books on HTML and CSS and DOM scripting stuff. We published Jeremy Keefe's first book on
DOM scripting and a number of other great titles. But about that time, I felt it was time to move
past the publishing industry. And my first proper job in web standard stuff was an opera.
And I do miss those days back with folks like Bruce and Patrick Lauker and
Henny Swan and Dan Davis doing open evangelism. It was an interesting time that because
opera never really had much of a market share, but we seem to have a disproportionately large voice in
terms of doing standard stuff. And then after a good few years there, it was time to go to Mozilla
and work on MDN, which is where it started to get really interesting, I think. And yeah, at that
point, I spent eight years working on MDN, doing lots of content on lots of different web APIs and
CSS stuff. After a while, it felt like time to move on. This is getting really boring, isn't it?
And fast forward a couple of years, and yeah, I ended up at the point where I wanted to start
something new again after doing a couple of years at Okta, doing identity and access management
documentation. And at this point, I've started up my own company called Mills Docs Limited, and
I'm now an independent documentation writer specializing in open standards, doing as much of
that good stuff as I can. And funnily enough, one of my first clients is Google, who have got me back
writing stuff on MDN again. So it's kind of a bit of a kind of a weird boomerang situation, but I'm
very happy with where I've ended up, because also it means I get to talk to nice people like yourself
a bit more often. So yeah, it feels like a good place to be right now.
That's amazing. That's a great story. And a lot of that stuff I have no idea about.
That's quite the leap from bioinformatics and protein folding to book publishing.
Did that kind of just like happen? Was it intentional? Was there an interest in that always?
So when I was at university, I can remember sitting there messing about on things like
GeoCities and MySpace playing with HTML and CSS stuff. But I never really had it in mind that I'd
do that stuff for a living. It was more a case of when I left university and went, oh crap,
I need to get a job now, the government aren't paying me to sit around in my student flats,
and even flat anymore. I thought, what the hell am I going to do? So I looked around,
I applied for a few jobs doing biochemistry related stuff, and realized actually,
it's really hard to get a job around here because I don't have a PhD. So I went,
ah, what the hell else am I going to do? And then I think by chance, I saw an advert saying,
trainee technical editors wanted to work on books about programming and HTML and stuff.
And I thought, oh, I know what HTML stands for. So I might be in with a shot for that job.
And it was cool, because whereas the kind of science bodies that I tried to get jobs with
in stuff related to my degree were kind of very formal, you know, had to go in there in a suit
and be quizzed by lots of panels of scientists, this was a much more chilled out, relaxing kind
of outlook. I can remember when I got my interview at Rock's Press being told, turn up in casual
clothes. And I was thinking, whoa, is that like a trap? Am I going to turn up and they're going to
be like, hey, you're not wearing a suit, screw you, man. And I was like, I'm not wearing a suit,
you're not wearing a suit, screw you, man. But I turned it up. I turned up wearing, you know,
ripped jeans and a Sepultura t-shirt and got on very well with them. And they were like, hey,
this guy seems all right. We'll give him a job. So yeah, it was pretty much partially an accident
and partially just like, hey, this sounds cool. Let's try this out. And it turned out being
a really good direction to go in. So that's brilliant. Yeah, it is one of the things I
also enjoy about tech is that it is for the most part, I don't know, I fit more with the
people in tech. I think it's what it boils down to. I wouldn't have made it in a corporate like
wearing a suit kind of thing. Like even in school, I constantly got into trouble because I wasn't
wearing a tie, but I was wearing a jersey. And it's like, you have to wear the two together.
And I was like, that doesn't make any sense. And I'm not going to wear a tie.
So yeah, the fact that I don't have to wear a tie and a suit to do my job,
I think is a good thing. But you mentioned that you have now gone the independent route and started
Mills Docks, which by the way, I love the name. And I'm always super excited when I hear people
doing this. It's very hard. It's scary and all these things. But I think the potential for
entrepreneurship and for startups and these kinds of things to create opportunity for others down
the line is what excites me about it. And that is why I'm doing what I'm doing with my company,
why I decided like, I have this company name that kind of started out as a way to be able to keep
working for Mozilla. But then I was like, well, wait a minute, maybe I should try and do something
with this. I've built up so many connections with so many people. I've been privileged to be able
to do that through the work I did or still do at Mozilla. And I have this burning passion for
open web, open standards, accessibility, all this stuff, and sharing my knowledge and stuff
with other people. So I was like, can I somehow take all these things and build a company around
it? And I've had some failed attempts, but I think it's because I was trying to do, I wasn't doing
what I wanted to do. So what I wanted to do and what I was doing, they were kind of at odds with
each other. But I think I found my way finally during the course of this year. But enough about
me. I'm curious about what made you decide to take this leap of faith and what is your hopes
for Millstocks? So it's something I've wanted to do for at least a decade, but I've always kind of
had the excuses and the fears coming up in the back of my mind. You know, it's like the main fear,
of course, is, am I still going to be able to find work to pay my mortgage, you know,
going to be able to find work to pay my mortgage and feed my family? Or are we going to end up,
you know, painting a colourful cardboard box on the side of the road in three months?
And it's pretty much purely that fear that kept me from doing it for the longest,
longest time. And looking back on it, you know, I keep, I've said to my wife a couple of times,
you know, I wish I'd done this years ago, because it seems great. And she's just like, but you keep
saying that, but you can't say that, you know, because the right time arrives, and it's the right
time, you can't sort of say, oh, well, the right time would have been 10 years ago, because it
obviously wasn't because you didn't do it. But I suppose, like, on that note, I think the main
thing to try and do is to try and make sure that you've got at least a couple of months of money
built up so that if everything does go wrong, you can still pay the bills and things just for a
little while while you're figuring it out. The other option, which I also know that some people
have done in the past is pretty much, you know, work two jobs until you get your own business
like going enough and buoyant enough to be able to then just jack in your regular day job.
I remember talking to some folks like Mark Bolton a long time ago about that,
and being really fascinated by, you know, the idea of how you can have enough tenacity to survive two
jobs, you know, like working your day job, and then like working your own company through the
evening and into the small hours to try and I think, I think that's a great kind of vision.
And it's, I'm really impressed if anyone that can do that. But I think really, I'm just too old and
knackered to do that now, you know, I'm getting old, I just can't cope with working 16 hours a
day anymore. Although I have done it from time to time in the past when there's been crunch periods,
don't get me wrong, we all have, but it's not a sustainable, sensible way to try and live your
life at any age, really. I think the next thing to think about really is that the best time really
is when you can kind of, again, we have advantages, you know, we have immense privilege in the
opportunities we've had for a whole number of reasons. And, but I think anyone can build up a
number of connections, regardless of what walk of life you come from. You just have to have been
around for a while, had a little bit of luck, met some good people, but really the best way to do
that is to go out there, be happy and friendly and helpful and just be positive and kind in as many
situations as you can, because that kind of thing really does get paid back to you in droves.
And then, you know, once you've done enough of that stuff for a few years, you'll then
start to see opportunities, you know, I think that's one thing, regardless of how much crap that
life throws your way, just never stop being kind and empathic and helping others, because
I really think that stuff will come back eventually, even if it doesn't seem like it sometimes.
You know, I sit here saying that, but I'm white and male and incredibly privileged.
But it's not as if I haven't worked hard to get where I am, you know, I've done a ton of work
for a very long time. And I think that stuff has resulted in me eventually being in a situation
where I have enough contacts that a couple of really good contracts were brought up through
the contacts I had, that allowed me to think, hell, this stuff will be what I need to last me
at least a year or so, you know, and this is the time that the time is now right to start my own
company. So that's that's kind of how I eventually arrived at that. It wasn't as if it was a great
plan for a long time, but just in a in about maybe a six month period, I kind of went from
going well, I feel like I want to move on from my current job. A couple of jobs that I applied for
didn't really work out for a couple of reasons. And then from that I kind of went well, there's
the combination of that and a couple of opportunities that are looking likely and let's
just take that chance and jump kind of thing. It always feels frightening, but you know,
I'd like to stress to anybody listening that once you've done it, provided that you're hard
working, and you've got integrity, and you've got a few contacts, and you've just got that
discipline to really work hard to begin with, and really sort of get all of that stuff built
up that you need to make a good go of it, I think you should succeed. And after a few months,
you'll be sitting there like me thinking, why the heck didn't I do this like years ago?
So it feels good. I mean, it particularly feels good to hardly attend any meetings anymore,
and to be your own boss and to really be able to just decide what you want to work on all the time.
And yeah, I think the other thing for me as well is that, you know, I did a whole bunch of management
in my employed career. But I kind of felt like I wanted to take a bit of a rest from that and
just sort of get back to individual contribution again. I think one of the key issues behind
management is just making sure that you understand the problems that all of your direct reports are
going through and be able to understand what they're doing. And to do that, really, you have
to have a bunch of experience in actually doing the job yourself. But I started to feel like I was
getting a bit too far away from the job itself. And I wanted to get back to that. But yeah,
at the end of the day, I just love discussing and writing great documentation. That's what
I'm here for. And it feels great to have got back to a much purer form of that.
And the other thing that you asked about was future plans. I think what I really want to do
is, you know, I'm working hard for the first year or so just to build up some great connections and
to do some great work. And also, you know, just as importantly, to build up a bit of cash in the
company so that I can start to then chill out a bit after that. But I think my longer term plans are
I want to get to the point where I don't have to work quite as much every week. So
I can hopefully start to spend some time teaching some people, mentoring some people and start to
give back to the community that way. One thing that I've always found a bit sad in the companies
that I've worked for, you know, you get a lot of great people, you get some companies doing some
great work, but there rarely seems to be that much time for mentorships and to actually get juniors
on board and skill them up and help with that kind of thing. Companies always seem to want stuff done
really quickly. So they always hire really experienced people and pay them loads of money
to do the work really fast. But it'd be great just to chill out a bit and just take that sort of
more chilled out longer term view of, you know, let's do this a little bit more slowly, but
actually skill up some people into the bargain. That's really what I want to head towards eventually.
Yeah, that's great. I love that. So when I get somebody on the podcast, I spend some time like
researching on them as much as I can to find topics that I know they might be interested in
talking about or things that I didn't know and I'd like to learn more about stuff like that.
You made it really easy because you sent out a tweet a while back in response to Bruce Lawson,
I think it was. And it's like the question was, what can you talk about with any heads up that
you're going to have to talk? And you posted a couple of topics that you can talk about without
being prompted. So I want to dig into some of those topics. The first one I find particularly
interesting because I think people don't really know what technical writing is. And I think there's
more people that would actually find it super interesting and we love doing that. But because
I don't know what it is, they might think that, oh no, these are like people who've gone and done
doctorates and PhDs on how a computer functions. I will never be able to do that.
So can you, from your perspective, break down what is technical writing and what does somebody need
if they are thinking like, okay, this is starting to sound interesting to me. What is the road
you follow to becoming a technical writer? Oh, that is a really interesting question.
I mean, that could be a very short or a very long answer. I suspect we haven't got time here to make
it a really long answer. So I'll try and get it somewhere in the middle. So I guess my short to
medium length answer would be that I think with technical writing, there's two main parts to it.
One of which is investigation and research. That's one thing that you've got to have an
aptitude for. And the other thing is being able to break down complex subjects and explain them
clearly to people to help them understand them. So that's really the two sides of the story.
So with everything that you need to write some documentation about, you first need to do a bunch
of research. You need to go, okay, for a start, what's the target audience here? What's the target
audience for the technology or the product that I'm about to write something concerning?
Is it a developer? Is it a DevOps person? Is it a designer? Is it a variety of different people?
Is it maybe even someone that's not very technical, someone who has no technical knowledge
and wants to sort of get started in this particular technology or field? There's also other things to
consider such as what is the prerequisite knowledge? Is this for complete beginners or is it for
advanced level people who just want to get better at stuff and they already know the basics?
What are the other technologies that you need to already know before you start using this
particular thing that you're writing about? So there's all of that stuff. When you've got that
figured out, it's usually a good idea to sit there and put yourself in the mindset of that person
that you're writing this document. Think to yourself, okay, what are the questions they're
going to have about this thing I'm writing about? What is it that they're going to want to know?
At that point, you can start to think about what to write about the actual technology,
and you've got to scope the work carefully, as you do with any task that you're doing,
whether you're a developer or a bricklayer or a plumber or whatever. Think to yourself, okay,
so I could write all of this stuff about this technology, but what do I actually need to do
first? As with any complex task, it's a good idea to break it down into different phases to go,
okay, first of all, I'm going to write down, I'm going to create just the quick start for this
particular technology, just the one or two articles that help someone get into it in 10 minutes flat.
Then after that, I'll start to do further phases to create reference material which explains
everything you could possibly want to do and allow you to look up things or
other advanced tutorials to write. Once you've got the scope of the work, you then need to go
and start investigating exactly what do I need to put into each of these documents that I'm going
to write. Usually, this involves a lot of hard self-reflection where you realize how little you
actually know about this stuff versus what you thought you knew about it. That's one of the main
reckonings to come up against, and you just have to go through it and figure out what you need to
do. I'll give you an example, so today I was attempting to create a load of documentation about
some new options to do with the Screen Capture API on MDN, and I sat there and I read through loads of
blog posts to help me just to understand the API in the first place because I'm not hugely familiar
about screen capture, and I was trying to figure out what I was going to do with the screen capture
to help me just to understand the API in the first place because I'm not hugely familiar with it.
Then I went through and looked through the Google Chrome source code to try and figure out
exactly which bits of it they implement and exactly which bits they don't, and which classes
are all of these different properties and options that I'm wanting to write about? Which classes
are they hanging off? What constructor are they involved with? Where do I need to put this
documentation on the site? And then another thing I tend to do at this point is that I write myself
a great big research document just to record all of that information so that I can then look back
on it and go ah that's what I need to write about. Another thing at this point to do which I think
is a really good idea is start off by writing one or two paragraphs about each thing that you're
trying to document just to make sure you understand what it is that you're writing about, because if
you can't explain to yourself in a few words what you're going to be writing about you sure as hell
won't be able to do that for other people. So I think I'm starting to waffle a bit so I think
I'll leave that in terms of the research and investigation part, but then onto the actual
writing of the stuff. When you're writing this involves of course a decent amount of aptitude
with language, whichever language it is that you're writing documentation in. You need to be able to
explain things really clearly. A general good rule of thumb is that you need to you need to write
so that you're trying to explain this to like you know maybe like a high school kid or something
like that. You know there's going to be quite a lot of complex terminology that you're going to
need to use, but you should make sure that you only use the term the complex terminology that
you have to use. Make sure you explain to it, explain the stuff you're talking about in as
clear language as you possibly can. Don't use jargon unless you absolutely have to.
So there's the language part of it. I think also there's the style part of it. You know you need
to make sure that the stuff is grammatically correct in terms of the language you're writing,
but you also need to add some style and some fun into it to make it so that not only can it be
understood, but it also makes the technology exciting to learn and interesting. It makes
people want to actually read the stuff you're writing about. I mean that comes with practice
and comes with quite you know a few years of building it up. But yeah I think I'm going to
stop there of the writing as well because I mean I really could talk for hours about this stuff,
but yeah really investigation and writing. Notice that I haven't mentioned programming ability or
web development ability or anything like that. I think really that stuff is all incidental to
the stuff that you're going to be documenting. So obviously it really really helps and you do kind
of need to be able to understand the technologies that you're writing about. But in a way that's
kind of like a background detail I think to just the first two which are really the more important
focus. So you'll be able to pick up the technologies gradually as you go along,
but your focus should really be the sort of the passion to investigate
and explain and to teach the stuff that you want to write about.
I hope that answered the question. Yeah no it totally did. Do you think it can be a good
way to learn? Like if you, not pretend, but if you play the role of a technical writer in your own
learning journey and so as you learn stuff you write about it in a way that maybe helps you
understand it better yourself? Totally. I think that's another great use of
blogging or tweeting as it's kind of become, although hey maybe not for much longer.
But yeah you know I think it totally helps. Like I've had, I've talked to loads of people
about this, like I remember talking to Estelle about this who now works for OpenWebDocs documenting
stuff on MDN and she was kind of saying that you know before we contracted her originally to work
on MDN she was saying hell this is great you know I really enjoy playing with technology,
I really enjoy writing about it on my blog and explaining it to other people so that they can
use it and it sounds like now you're going to basically pay me for something that I really
enjoy doing anyway and it's kind of like well that's totally cool to be able to get in roads
but I mean the salient point there is that I think that's basically what her and a lot of other
people have done you know it's like well I want to understand this technology so rather than just
writing a bunch of code examples and messing about with code which is, let's face it that's
also a great way to learn you know don't just stop there, create a code example but then also
explain how that works in a blog post and it helps you understand it even better so yeah I would
absolutely agree with that. Cool yeah I agree I think it's helped me differently and it still does
if I learn something new I often find it good to after the fact kind of try and write what I learned
or how I got to the answer of like this is the problem I faced this is how I got there
and then fill in the gap. Not only now do I have an artifact that I can look back at
but I have kind of proved to myself that I do understand it actually.
I think yeah absolutely I think one problem that does tend to come up from time to time is
the kind of scoping of the writing and the examples so you know you can if you want to
document a single property then you can do that and the code example might just be like a single
line of JavaScript but then you've got to think about well actually does that help me use this
in the real world what context do I need to use that in to actually make real use of it in a real
application and what scaffolding code has to sit behind it before that's actually effective and
useful and then you've got to kind of play with the scoping and figure out okay you know that's
just one line of code but to actually make it useful it's got to sit inside this giant
application that does all of this other stuff in the background but in terms of teaching someone
how to use these individual properties you can't show them like an entire application's worth of
code on every page you've got to kind of structure the examples so that you're making each individual
piece understandable while still kind of providing that useful real world context in how you're going
to use it so that's a bit of a balance that you need to achieve as you as you go through technical
writing and it's something that you just learn to do as you go forward you know there's
there's one one danger that I see people do a lot in technical writing is too many kitchen sink
examples so too many examples that show you how to do everything when actually you're just trying
to show someone how to how to use one single property you know the the best code examples
for technical writing just show how to do one thing well but they also show how show it how to
do it in a way that's transferable into the real world yeah yeah I I think writing good examples
is really a art form because I oftentimes the the examples you see people use aren't really
connected to any real world use case and so it's almost like you're learning something in the
abstract and you're so now you kind of understand on a technical level better what this thing is
but you still find it a little hard to understand how do I use this to solve an actual problem so
I think being able to connect those two things is really important yep no absolutely I think
the second biggest mistake I always see in code examples for technical writing is when people write
a code snippets that's really really clever but really hard to understand you know so it's like
fair enough you're a fantastic programmer this thing that I wrote in 10 lines you've
shown me how to do in two lines but actually my thing is a lot easier for people to understand
what's actually happening you know it's like you know when I when I return the value of that
property what object does that return and then I need to use a method that's hang that's hanging
off of that particular object and you know usually and you get some sort of chain like
that and you go well actually even though you could do that with one line it's often helpful
to sort of separate that out into the individual steps across three or four lines just so that
people can actually grok the chain of the chain of events that's a terrible term which will
be completely misconstrued the the different happenings that's going from start to finish
at that one line because otherwise it's just too difficult to get it if you've only seen that for
the first time yeah I completely agree so um I think well I don't think I know because I've
heard this many times and experience with myself that documentation is often the what makes the
difference between a successful open source project and a failure and you've been involved
in quite a number of open source projects that has really good documentation for example web
docs mdn web docs what has been some of the takeaways some of the stuff that you've learned
that you think is key to running a successful documentation project be it for an open source
project or closed source doesn't really matter but more of a focus may be on the open source side
okay um I think one of the number one important things is having really really clear processing
guidelines because if you don't have clear guidelines then you just end up with really
really bad inconsistency everywhere and it's okay if you've only got 10 pages but when you build
it up to a behemoth of a sort of size of mdn you then realize that you've got so many documents
so much documentation debt sat there that it's going to be nearly impossible to fix it all
and then it requires some passionate dedicated people to spend hundreds of hours fixing stuff up
just to get things not even particularly being that much better but just being consistent
but then again you know it's not so it's not so obvious what the improvement is when you just
fix a small number of those kind of paper kit paper cut inconsistency fixes but then when you
start to look at the whole project from a much higher level you then realize actually this is
just improving the quality and the polish of this thing so much but really it starts to become the
difference between the project living and dying um so in terms of guidelines this can be things
like you know exactly how do we take an image what size does the image need to be does it need to be
centered on the page or left aligned do i need to make sure that i capture it at a high enough
resolution so it doesn't start to look really pixely and crappy on high-res screen devices
all of these kind of things well what what kind of language guidelines do we use do we
do we have sentence case capitalization on headings you know all of this kind of stuff
it's just good to keep that stuff in mind and make sure you try and apply it
as consistently as possible now i also mentioned process so particularly in terms of things like
open source projects process is things like okay if i've submitted submitted a pull request
who's responsible for reviewing that how long can i expect to wait for a review
what am i expected to do to make it as easy as possible for other people to review
um these kind of things are also very important you know and not only is it good to have process
and guidelines to make the work better itself and the flow of work better but it's also great for
covering covering your own back as well if somebody starts to complain and say hey well
that thing's like that you can just you can just point to the process doc and say hey that's
because it's outlined in the process doc or it's outlined in these guidelines rather than
rather than just kind of making stuff up on the fly every time you get asked that question which
can lead to bad feeling when people see that you're making inconsistent decisions or
doing things that look like you're favoring one contributor over another contributor
so i'd say all of that stuff is really really important
it processes also when you start to get something where you get the number of
contributions that you do on mdn web docs and you know speaking to you as the community manager
of mdn web docs you know only too well just how much work it is to do that and try and manage
the community and manage who's doing what issue who's fixing what problem um you know process is
also hugely important for just trying to make sense of an enormous great big volume of issues
and pull requests flying at you all the time um so i think those are the two main things really
um in terms of other things that are important to think about for open source projects um i think
also part of the process and really this is coming into governance you need things like code of
conduct to make sure that people are treated as fairly as possible and anybody that comes
into the community and is a bad apple and starts being unconstructive or or you know god forbid
abusive um is dealt with using a firm but fair process to make sure that you can keep positive
feeling up um i think also this comes back to mentorship as well you know um as well as making
sure that everything's fair for people you also need to make sure that there's good beginners
documentation to help people get started but then also people to help mentor people and skill them
up so but they can start doing things more autonomously i think the biggest fear with
open source projects is you sit there and you go okay there's three or four of us that are
really autonomous and are getting loads of stuff done but if we stop and start spending some time
mentoring people instead that's going to take up all of our time so how on earth is all of the work
going to get done it's just going to grind to a hole but you need to have a balance don't you
need to carry on doing the good stuff but you also need to spend maybe a little bit of time skilling
people up so that you can then start to see the benefits of that later and then of course as
people start to move on from that project you need to make sure that you've still got people
to carry on the good work there and it doesn't just grind to a hole
yeah so yeah i think that's good advice yeah i think that's the main stuff that i've learned from
open source stuff i think a lot of those are all very good points a lot of big more enterprisey
companies could really benefit from those kind of open source project philosophies i've seen too many
kind of companies which are doing their documentation for their project on github
but mainly just because you know it's convenient to use something like a static site generator
type setup to publish your documentation but then failing to take advantages of
all of the kind of good open source magic that you could get by just opening up that documentation
and encouraging outside contributions you know if you've got your stuff on github but you're
not allowing external contributions then hell what you're doing you know it's just it doesn't
make any sense not to really yeah that's that's very true do you have any like examples of
either companies or open source projects that do this really well
well aside from the obvious you know mdn which is contributed to by loads of companies
um i'm just trying to think um i'm trying to think of a good example of like a company which is
you know pretty much a closed source product but it also takes lots and lots of contributions from
the open source community in terms of its documentation
um amazon from what i can tell seem to be quite good at doing that in terms of aws documentation
i've got a few friends there and they seem to have quite an active kind of
um contributions from the community um i'm not so sure if it's worth really mentioning
google and all of the community contributions they get to their docs because i mean that's like an
open source project anyway you know if you look at chrome it was an open source project
yeah yeah i'm drawing a bit of a blank i'm afraid but i'll have to think about other good examples
have you looked at how getup does their getup docs project because that's been open source now
since mid last year i think oh no i've not really looked at that so much
cool yeah it'd be interesting to know your thoughts on that one um because we have somebody that we
mutually know that works on that project now uh peter benkson he works at getup on the getup docs
project so um you know he's taken a lot of the learnings from mdn there and he's done a lot of
um you know he's taken a lot of the learnings from mdn there but he's also said that
there's also some stuff they do that web docs don't and um there's actually a quite a lot of
uh cross-pollination opening at the moment between uh web docs and getup um to learn from each other
especially now that their docs project is also open source and they are they're starting to
they're starting to experience some of the problems that we've already had and sort of kind of solved
or are more um used to or we're almost at a point where we are kind of solving it uh but they know
the technology we use much better than what we do like getup itself so you know they can help us
again from that perspective so it's quite interesting um how that that kind of relationship
is building up and being mutually beneficial yeah that's that's absolutely great like i'd
completely forgotten that peter had gone over to github but yeah i do remember that now i will have
to look into it yeah yeah interesting to know what you think so um you kind of touched on this when
you mentioned stuff like code of conducts and things like this but um a slightly harder topic
i guess um challenges facing the tech industry like you've been in tech industry quite for quite
some time the tech industry has changed but also stayed the same in many many respects you've worked
at everything from like big open source kind of companies like mozilla but also at octa now recently
um what have you found in your career so far to be like challenges that we just haven't dealt with
with properly yet i mean one of the things that i find fascinating is to learn that of all
contributions made to open source only 13 percent is women and only 17 from africa it seems
disproportionate and i wonder what your thoughts are on on those things it's really hard isn't it
you know the whole um equal opportunities and dni stuff is something that i do care about a great
deal and i would love to be able to help to fix this problem um but i don't think it's something
that can be very easily fixed um you know we have we have a society that's largely set up so that
that it advantages men and white people you know let's just you know and that's me speaking as a
white male i'm i'm painfully aware of that but then again at the same time i'm not because i think if
you don't suffer from prejudices that come from not being white and male you you don't notice them
and you can't even really imagine what effect that has um one thing that i would love to do
um going back to the idea of mentorship is deliberately give mentorship opportunities to
non-white non-males um just to basically try and give a bit back and to help with this whole issue
because you know that the number of times i've heard people complain about oh well you know
it's ridiculous like the amount of effort that's expended expanded on you know trying to give
trying to give opportunities for like you know non-whites and non-males haven't they had enough
and it's like yeah but actually as white males we get those advantages every day of our lives
by default as soon as we wake up without even trying and that's why we can never stop thinking
about this stuff and that's why you know in my own small way i want to do as much as i as much
as i can as i can about this and really i don't think this is a subject i can say too much more
about because i'm painfully aware that as a white male i don't understand it enough yet
and i don't think i'll ever understand it perhaps enough but i can just understand it as much as i
can being in the position that i am yeah so yeah you know yeah i don't even know if it's
i don't even know if it's got particularly that much better in the 20 plus years i've
been in the tech industry i certainly think it's got a bit better but least companies kind of
notice it now but then again i mean i was quite impressed with octa when i worked there but it
seemed octa seemed to be a company that recognize diversity and inclusion challenges but actually
really try and do something about it rather than just kind of paying lip service to it you know
having having a lame-ass little black lives matter sticker in the corner of your
site and then doing absolutely nothing about it apart from that you might as well please
just don't bother it's just pathetic but yeah octa did do a lot more than your average company
in terms of having like focus groups for women lgbt people of color inside the company and really
helping them to get advantages and get opportunities and then they have the whole
octa for good site as well which is their donations in philanthropy type movement which i was quite
impressed impressed by as well so yeah they definitely did more than the default but i'd
like the default just to be more i think that's yeah yeah something that's quite a painful truth
really yeah no for sure no i agree i i do think there's there's a lot of talk but not a lot of
action and this is generally a problem that i have with most of these kinds of things and it
plays into politics we won't go there but um it's always a lot of talk but when it comes down to
doing doing something constructive about it then you know it just goes quiet it's like oh okay
cool so we just like talking about it but we don't actually want to do anything about it
but um yeah no i i mean i've spoken to a couple of folks um who've been directly affected by
these kinds of things and some of these stories are just terrific it's like you can't believe that
this actually happens like here's a person sitting in front of you telling you that this has happened
to me but you still just can't can't wrap your head around the fact that stuff like this happens
to people like where people are um sexualized and stuff like that just openly in an office setting
and you're like i don't i don't understand how does this happen uh so yeah it is something that
i'm also um like uh it i don't know it plays the same kind of role to me as accessibility
um the accessibility of the products we build but also how accessible we make it to actually
enter the industry itself and then um how accessible we make it to get employed um i think
that in itself is a struggle and in africa um trying to build your own business is really
really hard because i i listened to a talk uh interview with a woman from africa she's from
legos but she so she built a business in africa and then she built a business in the united
states and she was talking about the the difference between her experience of these two scenarios and
what it boils down to is the system in the u.s for all the problems the united states have
the system is set up for you to succeed whereas in africa the system is set up to see you fail
and that is a hard truth to acknowledge me being from africa myself i can um corroborate her
experience you're definitely you're fighting constant bureaucracy and red tape to get the most
simplest things done like i'm sitting here speaking to you um but i'm actually connected to a big
battery on the left because our power is currently out and it's going to remain out for the next 30
minutes going to be out for about two hours and then in four hours from now it's going to happen
again because our power grid is just unmaintained and the company running it is completely corrupt
and so you know these are the things you face so you have to luckily i'm in a position where i can
go out and buy that expensive battery to allow me to be able to do this while it's pitch dark around
me um but not everybody is um a lot of people in this country are losing their jobs having to
close their companies simply because the system is set up for them to fail um and so yeah that
that's a very hard thing so for me from my part that is why stuff like accessibility is so important
to me because i know how hard it can be to do the most simplest thing and if i can do something to
make it a little easier for you to do get something done then by all means i think it's my responsibility
to do that absolutely absolutely i think um accessibility is you know just from a more
technical perspective is also another thing that's a major issue in the industry you know i think
this does have quite a lot of similarities to draw across like another thing i've noticed is
just that it seemed to get better for a while um you know with all of the action that um
accessibility advocates did through teaching even basic stuff like just writing proper semantic html
and actually using a freaking button when you mean to use a button and not a stupid div style to
look like a button how many times do we have to say it you know bang head against brick wall
um but it kind of seems to have got slightly worse again of late and i think this is because
the new generation coming into the industry a lot of them tend to do it through
less organically just kind of like right you know there's i'm not saying this is a terrible
thing it's great to give people opportunities to work but the number of college courses and
code boot camps and things that are just like well to get a job you just need to learn react
because that's the most popular library right now so run you through this quick course to teach you
how to build a react app boom you're gone go and get a job and you're like well that's great but
what about all of the sort of html css and javascript knowledge that underpins that
that you really ought to need to know to build a truly accessible effective application i mean
one kind of one anecdote that i can that springs to mind is i i was
asked by a friend of mine to come in and speak at his company about accessibility basics
um to all of his teams and there was quite a few people in his teams that were like fairly young
fairly new coders that were building a bunch of react apps and i thought to myself is it really
useful for me to just walk into here and just give like a 25 minute talk about all of this real basic
nuts and bolts accessibility stuff surely in 2021 but people were absolutely amazed and astounded
by it and we're just like what you mean it's actually important to use html elements other
than div what if something's inaccessible it isn't always the designer's fault it's actually
down to the code as well i was just i couldn't believe like this the sheer lack of knowledge
of this whole company about accessibility and yeah it's just weird to me i suppose again you
you live inside certain bubbles don't you so things aren't always like that everywhere but at
the same time i was quite shocked just by how little there was in terms of accessibility
knowledge there so i think that's another thing that we need to kind of ramp up again
and yeah so i agree i agreed i just last night watched a video where a person was talking about
using vue js and he was talking about okay we're going to create this list of products
and then i was like okay cool and then it's like a list of nested divs and i was like you
you use the word list just now html has lists you know it has different kinds of lists even i think
we should make this list of products with an ordered list maybe maybe that makes sense and
it helps people with accessibility to know this is a list of five items that's useful
useful information for them yeah so no i agree i agree i think it has it has slipped
out but i do see people talking about it but again i think it's again the thing where we need
more than just talk we need examples out there we need courses that teach a library like react
like view like swell like whatever is popular but made by people who care and so who use the proper
semantic structure when they show so they're not just like i'm going to show it to make a
view app but i'm going to show it to make a view app using the power of the open web i'm going to
show you how to use the proper html the proper css and think about stuff like color contrast and
the order of your document and what the outline of your document looks like and all of these good
things and by doing that show you that hey guess what more often than not your application is going
to be more performant because you're not going to reinvent the wheel don't build a select drop down
in react use the one the browser gives you i know it's not super pretty but you can style it
to some extent and at least it's accessible to a much much bigger audience and you're going to
have a lot less of a headache trying to maintain your own little select drop down because you're
now having to reinvent things that the browser has already implemented years ago
yep amen to that brother it's um it's a really difficult one though like i've i've done several
talks at universities where i've just had some person stand up in the back and utter some
immortal words like why not just use native apps for this because this is a pain in the ass and
i'm just like right well you can do that if you want to but the web has so many ways to do it
so the web has so many advantages so much easier in terms of distribution so much easier in terms
of not having to reinstall the damn thing every five minutes whenever there's an update
so much less in terms of weight of um files to get down the pipe to the users there's so many
reasons why the web is a great thing um you know depending on which you what use case it might not
be the best but you know it's good for so many use cases and it's getting better and better so
yeah um it does it it winds me up the number of courses you see that just teach you how to do
great applications but with terrible semantics and no thought at all to that side of things
but you know it's it's kind of it's turning web development into an a sort of very
it's almost bringing it back towards being a computer science discipline where whereas really
it isn't that it's so much more than that and that's why i find the web more interesting than
something like you know developing c++ apps because it's like well you've got this mixture of coding
and design and psychology and all sorts of different things that you have to bring into
this big melting pot of skills to produce something that's great for your users and it just makes
just makes life more interesting yeah for sure i mean that is that's the one reason why
moving from being a musician to being a web developer was not as painful because i didn't
feel i left so that much on the table um i still have a way to express myself um in creative ways
in creative ways um with the web because it is this amalgamation of many different things it's
you know it's not it's not just a science it's an art as well absolutely
so i have two questions remaining and um the one is light-hearted and the other one is really also
but it's also a little philosophical here we go i got it right um so first one um tough one but
um what is your top three artists and favorite album and maybe it doesn't have to be all time
maybe it can be in the last two years or maybe it is all time there that's a really hard question
it's one of those questions that every time i get asked it i come up with a completely different
answer because i listen to so much music i'm completely and utterly obsessed with music
in a really quite some people would say unnatural way my wife certainly seems to think so um although
i'm getting one of my daughters to be similarly obsessed with music which i'm quite proud of
um so for those of you listening that don't know me i'm completely obsessed by horrible noisy music
so heavy metal hardcore punk um but i also like a whole bunch of other stuff i'm pretty much into
anything that has a bit of soul and a bit of passion and isn't just soulless manufactured
disposable chart crap um and what have i what have i been listening to recently um i'm just trying
to think so my my favorite horrible noisy band currently is a us band called full of hell who
play really horrible kind of punk grindcore death metal type stuff interesting set of imagery and
artwork um some of their lyrical content seems to be quite philosophical and interesting it's not
just that kind of metal stereotype of gore and guts and horror movie type stuff you know which
is not the kind of thing that i'm really that into anyway but yeah i'd certainly recommend full of
hell um one of my all-time favorite bands is uh converge again us based kind of another band that
sort of straddles the line between punk and metal um they started off by uh playing what i think
they themselves described as slayer core which was really punk but with slayer riffs um interesting
and they progressed into something a lot more interesting from there so yes converge are very
good i i saw them recently at the damnation festival in the uk along with full of hell as
well um but yeah converge played the whole of their classic album jane doe which is really
really really good um so yeah that's great um what else in terms of uh less metal stuff um
um i quite like a lot of dance music um but again not kind of chatty commercial dance music i quite
like breakbeat and glitch and that kind of stuff so i really like afex twin so great artist from
the uk that's been doing weird glitchy stuff for a long long time um also really like square pusher
which is also in the same kind of vein um and there's a there's a fairly famous uk band called
orbital who do lots of really really great dance stuff um in a way i sometimes find dance music
easier to code to than really noisy metal stuff you know something that's just like a
a solid beat and a bit of an ambience in the background that you can really get into
um another one of my favorite bands another one of my favorite bands is the osric tentacles who
are another uk band that play kind of like a mixture of dance music and prog rock and
kind of weird kind of ethnic instruments and things they're really cool they're quite a
special band for me because i actually met my wife as an osric tentacles gig um and i'm going
to go and see them this weekend play in manchester uh along with another one of my favorite bands who
are gong i don't know if you've heard of gong g-o-n-g but they're a uh no they were originally like an
english slash french band that started in the late 60s and they sort of invented ambient music
before it was really a thing um so yeah they play another sort of strange mix of excuse me a mix
of kind of ambient and prog and quite a lot of silly whale noises and flutes and saxophones as
well so i'd suggest them and then again this list could go on forever but probably my favorite band
of all time at least my favorite band of all time this week is another uk band called the cardiax
who play a mix of kind of a mix of prog and punk so a lot of their stuff sounds a bit aggro-y and
punk but they're also really really really impressively technical musicians who play really
complex time structures and things but it sounds really quite punk they're not really around so
much anymore sadly sadly their frontman and main creative force tim smith died a couple of years
ago after battling a long-standing illness but yeah their music certainly lives on it's a it's
another one of those bands that kind of no one's ever heard of them and they certainly didn't have
any great commercial success but whenever they used to play a gig they could fill out like a
few thousand person arena you know they were like you know a massive massively popular band but
really underground at the same time so yeah that's a little bit of a uh a little bit of a snapshot
into what i've been listening to recently what about yourself man couple of things i'm going
to check out yeah i've been getting into ginger a lot like not ginger like j i n j e r um the
musicianship in that band is just unbelievable like the drummer the guitarists the bassist is
self the stuff he does is mind-blowing and then the lead vocalist she is something else she goes
from high to growls that you can't imagine um is possible um i've really been digging i've been
digging them quite a lot and then i learned they're from ukraine as well and so i've been
following them throughout the war and i'm thankful that they are all okay and safe and all that kind
of stuff but they've been sharing some stuff on their youtube channel so i've i've really
gotten into them i have to say and there's like another band that's kind of similar called spirit
box it's also a female um lead that also goes from melodic to full-on growl and again the
musicianship is just amazing um and some uh instrumental stuff like um animals as leaders
some of these people that play these eight string oh yeah electric guitars it's just like mother
it's so impressive and yeah yeah so a bunch of like stuff like that i've been getting really into but
then i've been getting back into some old good old things like in tombs blander stein album
um and some of the old sepultura and stuff like that just the rhythmic stuff and that just gets
me every time i'm a sucker for a good rhythm oh big time yeah no that's absolutely fantastic
now i mean i i've got uh sepultura's beneath the remains album on vinyl i put that on the other
day like sometimes i haven't listened to it for a while but it's a it's a super super brilliant
you know anybody that likes thrash it's just a brilliant album it's really more kind of thrash
death but it's it's it's it's absolutely superb um if you're it sounds like you're getting quite
into a bunch of kind of you know interesting female-fronted metal bands and i i also really
like ginger i think they're really really impressive really really good stuff but
there's a there's a uk band called rolo tamasi who are also like a a metal band
but with a female vocalist and she also does like really good melodic singy stuff as well as
growling uh they're really great they they also go into a lot of really weird disturbingly strange
kind of sort of techie screamo prog crazy stuff yeah they're they're they're really really great
yeah i'll definitely check them out so in closing what are your hopes for the future
and now from two perspectives one for tech and then on a more philosophical perspective
for the world crikey that is a big question um i think i could probably sum it up in four
in in six words um better climate less war less fascism
you know we could we could get into that a bit more i'm a i'm i'm very much
quite seriously committed to environmentalism so my my wife and i have done quite a bit of activism
with various groups um not just stop oil but we did do a bunch of stuff with extinction rebellion
we've been to quite a lot of protests and done quite a lot of activism activity with them
for me that's the key to everything really is the whole environmental
catastrophe that the world is facing because you know if we don't have a planet to live on anymore
everything else we could possibly discuss is just completely and utterly null and void there's not
even really it's not really worth talking about um yeah of course one big issue with that i you
know i can say that but at the same time another problem that you tend to get is that a lot of
the issues affecting tackling the climate catastrophe so climate change denial all of
that kind of stuff tends to be um tends to be connected to uh fascism as well unfortunately
there's a lot of fascist politicians out there that really really don't care about environmental
issues they think it's all a hoax they think it's all a load of rubbish made up by woke lefties like
me to try and steal a piece of their pie um but really that just goes into the whole selfish
outlook that those folks unfortunately often tend to harbor um yeah so yeah uh that's that's one
great big hairy deal and of course that also tends to create injustice and it tends to create um
people getting at loggerheads of each other which of course somewhere further down the line leads
to war so really these things are all interconnected um but yeah i'm just really really hoping that we
can get a bunch more people thinking about doing things to help the climate catastrophe you know
it seems clear to me that the governments of this world again like we talked like something
similar to what we mentioned earlier they like to talk a lot about this but they don't seem to
really like to do very much about it um yeah yeah so i think what we need is for everybody to start
uh helping out with the environmental catastrophe just by doing small things and helping out doing
anything they can yeah i would agree and i think one of the key things is i i heard about this
thing that they've they've learned and i think it's in taiwan where they've done some research and
so to drown out negativity for each one negative you have to have 10 positive so i think
i think we need to as a as a species as the human race we need to drown out this because i do think
it's a vocal minority and i've been in so many circumstances where you think that oh so many
people are against this thing or for this other thing but then when you really dig into it you
find out no it's actually a very vocal minority and if all the rest of the people stop standing
by and just looking at it and start speaking up just it we can drown them out very quickly
and i think a lot of people are not really aware of the fact that this is no small thing it's
nothing else is important if we don't have a place to live
essentially so this this should be like the way the people that that everybody in the world came
together to battle covid we need that for climate change climate crisis yep absolutely agree man
well thanks so much chris this was wonderful um i was looking forward to this conversation i'm
glad we could make it happen even though i'm it's low cheating over here and uh it's late
in the evening for both of us but um i'm really grateful that you made some time to speak with me
and i wish you all the best with millstocks i know it's going to be a huge success and i
look forward to to seeing the business grow well cheers man thanks for having me it's uh it's been
great to chat to you skalk and i'll uh i'll talk to you again soon yeah have a good day
thank you for listening to this episode of the my senior network podcast if you're not already
please subscribe store and leave a review for us in your podcatcher of choice this helps others
find us it helps us make a better podcast for you on this course you can also find and follow us on
twitter at network mysyndium enjoy the community on discord all the links are available in the
show notes