Welcome to the Mycelium Network Podcast, a podcast all about early stage web developers
and the mentors and teachers that help them along the way.
Hey, Buisile, thanks so much for joining me for the Mycelium Network Podcast.
The pleasure is mine. I'm happy to be here.
How's yours? How's your day been so far?
It's been a good day. It's been a good day. It's raining here in Zimbabwe,
so you're always welcome. Yeah, that's very true. That's very true.
So, I think let's just get this conversation right off to a start.
So, I know you from way back in the day when we met at a Mozilla event, I believe it was.
I think it might even have been something to do with Firefox OS still back in the day.
Yeah, that was in Johannesburg. That is correct. That is correct.
And after that, I've been following you on Twitter and I've been seeing the conversations
you've been having and all the things you've been up to. And when I started this whole community
and I started the podcast, I've always meant to invite you. So, I'm glad that I finally did
and that you were available and that we can have this conversation. Because I do think that you
have an interesting perspective and that you have a good story to tell and I would love to
give you a voice. So, to get us started, tell us more about who you are, how you got into
development, where did you grow up, anything that in your early years that might have been a catalyst
to kickstart your career, kickstart your interest in tech. And then just as an aside at some point,
I'm always curious when people have like a pseudonym on the internet what the story
behind it is. And like on Github and Twitter, you have this pseudonym called Terra Maiar,
if I'm pronouncing it correctly. So, I'm curious if there's a story behind that.
Okay. All right. That's okay. Let me tell my story. So, I was raised in Zimbabwe.
I've always loved tech and computers. I've always been intrigued by how they work. I'd say I'm a
logical person, I think in a bullet point kind of way, like a very sequential way. Computers
work the same. So, I just understood them. And so, I've always loved computers. And I used to
go to my sister's workplace just to play with her computer back in the day. We didn't have a
computer. I didn't have a personal computer at home. So, the only computers I came across were
computers in people's workplaces. I would always visit friends and family's offices just to use
their computer. That's how I got to learn how to use a computer. And then, once I knew enough,
I started going to internet cafes, messing around on the internet, you know, started joining forums
and chat groups and things like that. And so, that's how my interest in computers was what it
peaked at that point, I'd say. And then after high school, I went to a polytechnic college,
I studied IT. So, I learned formally about computers and information technology. Unfortunately,
I wasn't able to graduate because of financial problems and some other personal reasons that
kept me from completing that course. But I still loved it. And I still carry that knowledge I gained
from them with me. So, after I finished or after college was done, I started contributing to open
source. That's when I started. I found Mozilla. I joined Mozilla community at first. I was just
doing translation. I worked on Firefox OS translation into Hindi, the language I speak here.
And then from there, as I met more people, I got more and more involved in the community,
and then contributed to QA. We used to do QA testing for pre-release Firefox builds and even
Firefox OS at some point. And then that was when I was introduced to programming because a lot of
the QA engineers at Mozilla used Python to automate the tests that they used to against the Firefox
or many of the internal Mozilla websites they were testing. So, that's when I was introduced to Python
and got interested, and I started learning it. So, I started learning. That was around 2013,
2014, I think. And yeah, that's when my Python journey started. And then after that,
after a few years, I learned Python. I watched some YouTube tutorials. I read some books. I
bought some courses, and I got good at it. But unfortunately, I wasn't able to get a job
because something the tech pros on YouTube don't tell you is when you're learning a
tool or programming language, you need to learn something that makes sense for where you are.
And there isn't a big market for Python here in Zimbabwe, so I learned that the hard way.
But yeah, after a while, I eventually found remote jobs. And that's how I got into
software development using Python. Okay. That's interesting. That is an interesting perspective
to think about not only which language, but which language is in demand where you live.
I guess that's to some extent true in South Africa as well. I don't know now. I've not been
super in touch with the workforce in South Africa for quite some time. But I know when I started,
Java was definitely the language du jour. If you wanted a job, you had to know Java.
That's why I always say I have a love-hate relationship with Java because I never
enjoyed the language. But I am grateful for the opportunities that it given me because it
introduced me to open source and it allowed me to get a job, a decent paying job, which allowed me
to explore some other avenues. But I definitely quickly discovered that for me, that wasn't the
language and especially not J2EE. The enterprise stuff was definitely not where my love and interest
lie. But I'm grateful for what it introduced me to. So is there a story behind TerraMajor
or is it just something you picked? Oh, yeah. I forgot to mention. So when I was
fooling around on the internet, I wanted to have a pseudonym I could use across all my socials.
Right. And the name is a pretty common name here in Africa. So most of the time when I try to use
the name, it'll be taken. So I had to come up with something unique, but that also spoke to the kind
of person I was. So TerraMajor is an acronym. I'd say it describes me in a sense. It stands for
Tremendously Exuberant, Risen, and Real Attitude. That's a terra. I think that's what I am,
I'd like to say. And then major is just like a major, like a title from an army.
Oh, okay. Someone who has that attitude and who's also a major. And I just felt it different
weirdly so that I would always be unique. That's very interesting. So I did that with us as young,
just straight out of college. And the name stuck. Unfortunately, I've built my brand, so to speak,
quote unquote, around that name. So I haven't really changed it. So you'll find most of my socials,
I'm TerraMajor on most of my socials. It's like GitHub, Twitter, everywhere.
That's very interesting. Yeah. I always like hearing the stories behind the names. So as you
mentioned, even though Python wasn't the language that you needed in Zimbabwe to get a job, it's
still a language that you learned. And I know that you love Python. That's what I can tell from
your tweets and all this stuff you do. And I have to say, if I had to pick a backend language,
other than Node, i.e. JavaScript, I would probably pick Python as well. I really love the syntax.
I really like the rules of Python. Are you thinking Python? It resonates with me very much.
But you, as somebody who uses Python as your main language, what is it about Python that attracted
you and what do you love about Python? Okay. So like I mentioned, firstly, I learned Python
because that's what all the cool engineers at Mozilla used. That's what first got me into Python.
But then as I learned, it was really easy for me to learn. Unlike languages like C++ or Java,
it read like English. It's very straightforward. You can pick up a Python program and figure out
what it does, even when you're not very experienced with programming. So that was what got me
interested in Python. But really what made me love the language as much as I do is the community.
It is a fantastic community. And as someone who was finding their way, I was on my own. I didn't
have a college degree. I didn't have a lot of support here. So I had to lean on the Python
community to basically get mentorship, get opportunities. And the community was fantastic.
Very friendly people, very helpful, and very accommodating. So that's what really
made me like the language as much as I do. But another thing is, it's a bit of, it's really
sentimental. Because I learned Python, and then I couldn't get a job. So I had to make a choice.
Because either I pick up a language like Java, or one of the.NET languages that are common here,
even wanted to get a job, or I could just stick it out and not give up and just keep pushing
until I got the job. Because I already put in the time to learn this language. So that's what I did.
I chose the second option. You know what? You have already put in this work. Just see it through.
So I went through a very difficult phase where I forced myself to learn enough Python to get a job.
That was my goal. I was like, you know what? Just get a job that way you can use Python, and then
that way I won't feel like a failure for learning it. And so it's one of those things where I just
had to stick through with it. I had to learn the language. I had to learn the language.
I had to make it work. So I did that. I got the job. And now I'm actually trying to move away from
Python and learn different languages. I don't want to be the Python guy. I just want to be able to
code in Python and other languages. Is there any other language specifically that you're thinking
about? Go and Rust on my radar. Yeah, those are good ones. I always mean to learn Rust, but
JavaScript evolves so fast that I'm finding it hard enough to keep up with JavaScript.
Exactly. But I'm just like, oh, my goodness, what's this new thing in JavaScript today? Okay,
wait, let me just figure this one out first before I try a new language. But at some point,
I'd like to learn Rust because I think some of the backend stuff that I'm doing,
especially the one side project I'm working on, if that kicks off and is successful,
I think it would be beneficial if I have the backend written in Rust as opposed to in Node.
I think Rust will allow me to scale much, much better than doing Node. Because with Rust,
if I understand correctly, I'm going to be much closer to the metal instead of having to go
through a translation layer that then speaks to the metal, which is always a good thing if you
want to eke out that extra bit of performance. That's basically how I learn. I put myself in a
situation where I'm like, okay, I'm going to do this project and I'm going to do it in Rust,
and now I have no choice. I have to learn it. I don't know. That's just how I learn. So,
I have to think which area I want to go into. Let's dig into community a little bit.
Among the many things I do is, well, I've started this community called Mercedes Network,
but I'm also the community manager for MDN Web Docs at Mozilla. So, I'm more and more involved
in everything community. One of the reasons for it is, like you said, I think it's often
the differentiator and the enabler for a lot of people where you don't feel alone.
Because I think oftentimes it's not easy to give up, but you're more likely to give up if
you don't have a community that either holds you accountable or simply inspires you or both.
So, what are your feelings? That's how I think about community. What is important to you
about community? Well, it's two things really. Sharing of skills and opportunities. When you're
learning on your own, when you're self-taught, or when you're just figuring stuff out from doing a
bunch of tutorials online, you really don't know what you don't know. It's beneficial to be part
of a community with people who are more experienced than you because they can help you see the things
or figure out the things you're supposed to know that you're not aware that you don't know.
So, that helps a lot. And it helps also, like you mentioned, to see people doing the stuff you want
to do in the real world and actually making an impact using the stuff you're learning. So,
it gives you the motivation to work towards a goal to be like them. Like I mentioned, I learned
Python because the cool engineers at Mozilla were using it and it looked cool and I liked that.
I wanted to be like them and then that's what got me involved. And then along the way, as I was
learning, I had people in the community I could reach out to for help when I needed it. And these
are people who are leaders in respecting different fields. So, I knew I was always getting the right
kind of guidance and the right kind of information. And it helped to have that. Unlike where you just
have to Google like on Stack Overflow or something, it helped to have that human connection.
Yeah, for sure. I totally agree. So, then on a slightly related but tougher topic,
I'd just like to get your input. So, I recently learned that of all contributions to open source,
only 17% comes from Africa. That blew my mind because that's a very, very small number
if you take into account how many people are on this continent. So, my one question is,
why do you think are holding people back from it? And then what role can open source play
in lifting people up and creating opportunity? Because I strongly believe open source has
tremendous possibility to open up doors for people. And I think you've experienced it through
the whole Mozilla thing and you mentioned getting into open source early. So, what are your thoughts
on those topics? Why do you think there's such a small number of people contributing to open
source? And what can we do about that? Man, this one is a tricky one because I think
it's to do with lack of access. So, I'd say there's poorly developed infrastructure
that plays a role. Lack of skills to effectively contribute to some open source project. And
I guess this also falls under infrastructure is that internet access is not widely distributed,
I mean, evenly distributed in Africa. So, you'll find that in landlocked countries, generally,
the internet tends to be slower because they don't have a lot of inland fiber connections. So,
because it's slower, they use technologies like satellite, UHF and whatnot. These are
slow and expensive. So, internet access for the most part is not... A lot of people have access to
high speed internet and if they do have it, it's expensive. That's the first problem. In most of
Africa, there is, of course, the power of problems and a lot of infrastructure problems. Then that
aside, I think the second reason why we don't have a lot of contributions in open source is
time. I'd say one has to be privileged, in a sense, to be able to contribute to open source.
I don't like saying this, but I'll say it here, because you need to have time. You're willing to
give away basically for free because you're not being compensated for the time to work on something.
So, not a lot of people have that time because most people, especially people from disadvantaged
backgrounds, they're more focused on putting food on the table. So, they're doing paid work.
So, that's the second thing. Then I think the third thing would be skills. So, we, Africa,
in general, hasn't had a lot of time to develop skill and talent as much as the West or Asia has.
So, we're still playing catch up with the rest of the world. So, there's still a skills gap
that needs to be filled. I think once that is filled, we'll have developers, our community
members of the community in positions where they can contribute better. So, you'll find that most
of the contributions to open source, I think, don't quote me on this, but I think you'll find
that most of them come from economies that generally perform better than the rest of the
world. Economies that generally perform better, like Nigeria, South Africa, Egypt, or Kenya.
So, the better infrastructure, better economies, and better levels of education, and better access
to hardware, and these opportunities. You have big tech companies setting up lots of startups.
So, it's a very difficult problem, but I think there's definitely lots of opportunity in
contributing to open source. I gained a lot from working in open source. I learned a lot of things
that I wouldn't otherwise have learned just from reading books or watching video tutorials. I've
had opportunities that came as a result of that, but the unfortunate truth is that it's not easy
for everyone to get into it. I also sometimes wonder, because in the few interactions I've had
where during Hectorbofist, we as a community worked on this project that's ongoing, but
we kind of focused on it. It was incredible to find how unfriendly a lot of open source
tools and stuff is if you're on a Windows machine, for example, as opposed to a Mac or even Linux.
I think in Africa, it's probably more prevalent for people to have Windows machines than it is
to have Macs, for sure Macs. Maybe a lot of people don't know about Linux and also don't know which
are the more user-friendly installations of those that has a more Windows-like experience,
but will give you a better... Then, of course, Windows has come a long way in the sense of
a Windows subsystem for Linux, but you need to run the very latest version of Windows. That
sometimes means you have to have a pretty decent machine, so if you can't afford the expensive
computer, you can't run the latest Windows, and so you don't have access to WSL. There you go.
I think that might be another problem. You mentioned hardware access being one of the
problems. I wonder if something like an incubator for open source in Africa would go some way
towards this, because what I'm thinking is it's a means for young, and this is not young in age,
young and experienced people, to have a starting point where they get paid a decent enough salary
to work on open source, and through that, they then can get introduced to more opportunities.
So, the incubator serves as an on-ramp into the industry, so it takes people in,
it skills them up, and through skilling them up, they get paid, but they also contribute
to open source projects, which again, benefits a whole large part of the economy, because
everybody depends on open source these days, but then it gets them to a point where they can then
leave the incubator and either start their own thing or join a company, because now they've
experienced, and they could contribute to open source, because like you said, they can still
put food on the table, because they're actually getting paid to do that. What do you think about
something like that? I actually think it's a good idea, and I'd really prefer it if this came from
the highest level, say, have governments introduce open source policies, that would drive demand for
open source software. Say, for instance, the government were to stipulate that all government
departments would use open source operating systems and open source software, so that would
mean you'd have to have people skilled in installing these operating systems, in managing
these operating systems, and using the software, and it would save them money, which is a good
thing for government, because most of these tools are free, open source is free, and then it would
then create demand for people with skills in using or handling open source software. And then
these incubators would then have a pipeline, like you draw in the talent, you train the talent,
and you have somewhere to move that talent to, because there's demand on the other side.
So I think it would be to be a really good thing for all parties involved. Open source is free,
so that cuts costs, it creates opportunities for people using it, and then it's a win-win for
everyone. Yeah, yeah. I think it's a very good idea for governments to adopt this. My experience
is that it's a hard place to start. It almost feels like industry needs to, I don't know how
exactly this would work, but they have to kind of put pressure on the government to adopt these
things, because I'm not sure that the governments even know. They just pay the licensing fee they've
been paying for 20 years because it's what they've been doing. I don't know if there's enough.
There's a company in South Africa called Open Up, and they do quite a bit of this, where they
actually interface with municipalities and stuff like this, and they are very much into opening
up data, but also the use of open source and that kind of stuff. So I think it's kind of like an
education kind of thing, where there needs to be these companies that show government the benefits
of open source, and show the possibility of creating jobs and developing talent, and maybe
through creating something. Exactly, exactly. And maybe through setting an example, they'd be more
willing to adopt it, and you'd probably have to start on a small scale. You might have to start
with your own municipality and getting them to adopt some open source software, and then them
going to their leaders and saying, hey, my goodness, look, we've been using this thing that we learned
from these other guys, and it's saving us so much money, and there's a bunch of people that's being
trained, that knows how to run these things, and then maybe it goes up the chain and up the chain,
and eventually it gets adopted wider. I think there are some Asian countries that's actually
doing a really good job with this. For some reason, Taiwan always comes to my mind, but I'm not sure
if it's them who has really adopted a complete, and I think even South America, like Brazil and
them, I think they've also adopted open source software quite heavily. So I think there's scope
for that, and I do think that in the end of the day, that would be a good thing, but I do think
industry will need to set an example and offer proof that it's not just talk, it's for real,
like the benefits are real. But yeah, I think that that might be something that
would be nice if one can get a couple of companies together to try this out and see what one can do.
I think there are some education, some places doing education in South Africa, that is kind of
got this idea, but again, there you sit with the problem of the monetary problem, whereas
you're studying, so you're not earning anything yet. And so you have to, and that's definitely
a massive problem. I mean, unemployment in South Africa is something like 50%. So if you have an
unemployment rate of 50%, people don't have a lot of free time to give away of their precious time
that they have. So you have to incentivize them monetarily as well. So on that topic, yep.
I just want to say, this has a positive effect on people actually involved in work, that actually
use the software, because say a municipality needs a certain feature, they could have their employees
build the feature and then release it back into open source. So I mean, it's a hard problem to
solve, but it has lots of benefits if it would be implemented right. Yeah, no, for sure. And I mean,
and talking about that, I know you were a freelancer. I think you recently took a full-time
position. Yeah. Am I correct there? Okay, cool. Yeah. So to dig into that a little bit. So
in the beginning of this year, I officially started my own company. It's an open startup,
which means we are fully transparent in terms of income, in terms of what we pay people,
who our employees are. If the employee is okay with it, of course, we're not going to publish
their stuff publicly if they don't want us to do that. But so far, everybody's fine with that.
But our expenses, everything is open. And of course, we are heavily invested in open source.
The company is completely based around open source. We give back to open source.
We have a mandate of any project we rely on. We have to either financially or through
contributions give back. What's your product? So at the moment, it's mostly around consulting
and education, but we're building two products, one that's developer facing. It's called developer
tool chest. It's a way of collecting a bunch of tools that you use often and giving you easy
access to it. So you can just contribute to it, anything, and you tag it in ways that you'd
obviously want to find it later on. And then it's just like a search interface. And also allow easy
discovery of other tools you might not know about. And then we have some plans for going forward.
The other one is called our backyard. And that is a platform to help small businesses
get in front of people. So it's easy to find big box stores because they have thousands of runs
to spend on advertising and big signs and big buildings. Whereas a lot of small businesses
run from their own little house and they don't have a bunch of money. And so the idea is that
our backyard is literally what the name suggests. It's where you go to find small businesses in
your own community and support local business in your own community. So it's got that good
thing to it. But then down the line, we will look at how we can responsibly make some money from it.
Because, of course, at some point, it needs to make a profit. But we want to do it responsibly.
So privacy is extremely important to us. So we don't want to stick a bunch of advertising
in front of you. We don't want to track you everywhere you go. But we'll find a business
model that works. Maybe it's something as simple as if this service is valuable to you,
to give money to it on a monthly basis. Maybe it's a business model like that. Kind of like
Open Collective. Because it's also built open source. The whole platform is built in the open.
But with that said, it's not easy. It's definitely not easy. And doing it in the
African context brings its own challenges. I heard a talk on a podcast of a guy called
Lex Friedman, where he spoke to a woman that she started a business in Lagos,
and then she started a business in the US. And she was talking about how different the
experience was between the two. And what it boiled down to was that in the United States,
with all its problems, the system is set up for you to succeed. Whereas, in her words,
in Africa, it's set up for you to fail. Because the infrastructure, the support,
it's just not there. More often than not, she got where she did because she knew the
mayor in the town and she could ask for a favor. Whereas if she didn't, you know,
she might never have gotten electricity to her business and the business would have failed.
All these kinds of things. So, I'm curious, because there's another thing,
because I know you struggled with this. So, if you're in a first world country,
and you want to experiment with something, so you want to create a newsletter, and then you want to
put some aspect of it, maybe you want to allow people to post comments on your newsletter,
but only if they're a paid member, for example. Now, there's an array of options to do that.
You can use Substack. You can use Ghost. There's a bunch of things. But if you're from Africa,
you're going to hit a problem. And that is because the only processor they support is Stripe.
And we don't have access to Stripe in Africa, in the entire continent we don't. Now,
Stripe offers this thing called Stripe Atlas. I don't know if you've heard about that.
Yeah, they create an LLC for you in Delaware, in the United States.
But the thing is, it costs $500 to get that set up, and then $100 per year to keep that LLC going.
Now, if you just want to experiment with a newsletter, that's a massive investment of
money for something you don't know if it's going to succeed, and where you're going to
charge people probably like $2 a month for a subscription. So, with all that context that
I've given now, what were the problems that you faced that made you, that put you in a position
where you had to say, you know what, I'm going to have to stop this freelance thing for a while,
and just get a paid job where I'm a little bit more certain of my salary?
So, before I started working as a developer, I used to run a web hosting business
for Hanger Branding for a few years. And the biggest problem I've faced was the changing,
like changes in business environment in Zimbabwe. The regulations are always changing. It's very
hard to plan for your business. And getting money into a bank account is very difficult,
because I think our currency has changed. I think we've changed currencies like five, four or five
times in the past few years. So, one minute we're using US dollars, next minute we're using
something different. So, that lack of consistency just made it very difficult. So, there were
problems that were bigger than me that affected the clients that I had. Everyone was affected by
this business environment. So, you'd have situations where clients weren't able to pay me on time,
or if they were able to pay me, I'd just have problems collecting the money. Because if you
have a client outside Zimbabwe, getting money into Zimbabwe is very difficult because of these
problems with our banking system and everything. So, that was the biggest problem for me is just
moving money. I had cash flow problems because of the changes and lack of consistency.
So, I'd say that was the first one. And then the second one, the second challenge I had is,
we have a number of payment options here. We have mobile money, we have bank transfers, we have
online payments from debit cards and credit cards. But getting support for all those is very
difficult. For instance, mobile money is run by a few telecoms companies, or the biggest one is
Ecocash. And they're not very open to providing their API to small businesses. So, if you're
starting out and you want to accept Ecocash payments or mobile money payments, it's not very
easy to get that. So, that's one of the first problems. And then the second one is the payment
processes we have here charge very high fees, just like Stripe does, the yearly fees. So, it can go
in the way, go against running the business because you end up paying more to these payment
processes that you're actually taking in. And then the last straw for me was the payment process I
was using at the time to shut down. No warning, no compensation, no communication, nothing.
It just shut down one day and it just stopped working. So, migrating the business to a new
payment process, it would have just taken too long. And you're like, hey, you know what,
I don't need this. So, that's when I notified all my customers. I just gave them free service for
about a year while I helped them move their websites to different hosting providers. And
that's when I was really done. Then I started looking for a job. So, yeah, it's hard to run
a business here in Africa because of infrastructure problems and the business environment is just not
set up for, that doesn't set you up for success. So, getting a job was another challenge because
economy in Zimbabwe is not great right now. And that was the first thing. And the second thing
was the skills I had learned where I couldn't get a job for the skills I had. So, I was forced to
get a remote job from international companies. So, that comes with its own challenges. But
unfortunately, I did get a job. I have a job now. I'm happy. So, yeah.
Oh, I'm glad to hear that. So, okay, let's step back into something else. There's a project that
I believe you started. And I believe I saw the tweet when this idea started in your head
that ended up being Pai Pai in a box. Yeah. Do you want to dig into that? Because that's
really, really cool. I read about it a bit more today and it's really cool if you want to tell
us more about that. So, what started this project is part of the problems we've been talking about,
infrastructure problems here in Africa. You go to a meetup, you're running a workshop, you want
people to install some packages, and then the internet goes out or the power goes out. So,
that basically means you can't do anything. You just have to talk through what you would have done.
So, I got to a point where I attend a lot of conferences and I attend meetups and workshops,
and I do trainings at these events. And that was my biggest frustration that I didn't have
a reliable internet access or reliable power to run the workshops I needed to run. So, I thought,
hey, what could I do to allow people in the workshops, guest attendees to install the
software and not be bothered by whether there's internet or not? And then I figured, what if
I could download the packages I needed onto a little computer, build, make it a Wi-Fi hotspot,
have everyone connect to it, and then they could download packages? So, that's when
I started tweeting about it, asking people how I could go about it. I did some research and I
figured it's actually not difficult because firstly, Raspberry Pi is an affordable computer.
At the time, they're still available, they're still affordable. You can buy, I bought one,
I got a very large, like the largest size SD card I could get. I think it was 256 gigs. And then I
cloned the Python package repository. So, it's like the NPM package repository if you're from
JavaScript world. So, that was about, the download was about 100 gigs. So, I downloaded the packages
and I found some software online that can recreate the structure of PyPI, which is the Python package
index. So, it recreated the structure and indexed the packages and then I put a web server in front
of that and then I configured the Raspberry Pi to act as a Wi-Fi hotspot. So, you can now, using
this tool, install, do a pip install package name from a local repository instead of going to the
Python package index. You know, pip, the package manager can do that. It allows you to install from
offline or local package repositories. So, whenever we'd have an event here at Zimbabwe, I'd do that.
I'd set up the Raspberry Pi, everyone would connect to it and they'd run that one command,
they'd be able to install the packages that they needed. It's a, you know, it's a simple device,
but it's really went a long way in making sure I can teach the way I wanted to teach, you know,
whether there's internet or there's power, we always had a little Wi-Fi connection that could
allow people to install software. Yeah, yeah, that's super cool. So, do you put like a
a SIM card in the Raspberry Pi and it uses that to connect to the internet, like mobile?
No, so the Raspberry Pi, the model I have is the latest model. So, it has an Ethernet port
and it has Wi-Fi as well. So, the way I have it set up is I connect it to the internet via the
Ethernet port and then set up a Wi-Fi hotspot on its Wi-Fi adapter. So, I can download packages
using Ethernet and then broadcast Wi-Fi network using the Wi-Fi adapter. Now, alternatively,
you can download packages on your laptop and then transfer them onto its little SD card because it
uses an SD card as a hard drive. So, you can set up everything, all the files you need on your
computer on the SD card and then transfer that to the Raspberry Pi. So, it works just like a normal
computer except without all the fancy bells and whistles you'd expect from a powerful desktop.
Yeah, yeah, that's super interesting. I know there's another project. It's not meant for
Python or anything like that, but it's called Internet in a Box. I don't know if you know about
that. Yes, I came across it when I was working on this. It's a very similar project. They do
basically everything else. It's a digital library of different websites and stuff.
Yeah, like Wikipedia and that kind of stuff. So, if you're in a rural area, you can put that down
somewhere and people can have access to it. And then, if you once a month just do an update
from the internet to make sure you have the latest content, then people don't need internet
access to be able to access all this, which is amazing. I mean, sometimes the thing that stands
between you and success is just having access to that content. So, yeah, it's great. I'm actually
thinking of doing something similar. When I started this, it was just a proof of concept to
see if I could do it. But now, what I want to do is I want to take the same concept and use it to
make my own internet in a box. So, I only do Stack Overflow and Wikipedia. So, I found
a lab tool called Keywigs that allows you to do this very easily. It bundles all the software you
need to serve up clothed content offline easily. So, you just download the content, install this
software, and then it allows you to serve up some Wikipedia or Stack Overflow easily. So,
that's the next thing I'm going to try. Yeah, that sounds really cool. Do you know if there exists
a similar thing to this for NPM, like NPM in a box? I actually haven't heard anything like that.
So, I wouldn't know. I once asked on my Twitter, I've been on you, but I didn't get any responses.
So, I'm not sure if it's there or people just ignore me. I don't know.
Yeah. Would it be, thinking about your experience creating
PyPy in a box, do you think it would be a lot of the work you've done is transferable to
creating something like NPM in a box? With what you've done, would that have a lot of
the infrastructure just reusable for that, or is it very specific to PyPy?
I think it is. The concepts, rather, are reusable because I use a lot of Python packages to do this,
but I think the principles can be applied to NPM. I'm not sure how packaging works in the
JavaScript world, but I imagine JavaScript packages take up much more space than the
Python packages. So, you'd need to find a way to download packages that you can fit into Raspberry
Pi and then a way to index them and then serve them up. So, probably, for serving them up,
you could use a web server like Nginx or something, and then indexing them, I don't know. I'm sure
there's something NPM specific that you could do, but you just need to find the right tools,
but it should definitely be possible. Yeah. So, what do you use for indexing PyPy?
Because I'm thinking, the name is just in my head now, it's hard again.
So, there's this thing called PyPy server. You point it to where you have the Python packages
downloaded. It runs through the list and then creates an index. That makes it easy for the
PIP tool to find the package. You can find the package based on the name or its metadata.
You can figure out what dependencies it depends on. So, indexing really is useful. It saves you
a bunch of time instead of searching through the entire package repo every time you want to do a
PIP install. Yeah. I wonder whether Algolia or something like that, I wonder if you can run that
on a server with NPM and use Algolia to index the NPM registry. That'd be interesting.
I'm really curious if this is possible. Yeah, it could be an interesting problem to
solve. Yeah, for sure. Like you said, I'm sitting here and I was speaking to you and the only reason
I can is because I'm plugged into a big battery because currently we're being load shed. So,
we don't have electricity at the moment. So, I have a big battery that I'm plugged in and because
of that, I still have internet access and I can actually speak to you. I only bought it this week
and it was very expensive. I had to put money aside and thankfully, I have a business. So,
I did some extra work for extra clients and so far, it seems like it was definitely a good buy,
but it's not cheap and it's not something that's accessible to many people, unfortunately. So,
there's a lot of people around me sitting without electricity right now. So,
I did that recently, so I can relate. Yeah. So, I can totally see a situation where you're in the
middle of a workshop and there goes the power and you're like, oh boy, now what do we do? So,
being able to whip out a Raspberry Pi with NPM on it would be super useful. So, I think it's something
that as Mechanical Ink should spend some time on and I might just need to tap your brain for some
knowledge. Yeah, I'm happy to. I'd love to actually see that, because I know that would definitely
have more of a use case here than the Python thing does, because there are generally more
JavaScript developers around than Python ones. Interesting. So, what I also saw is, I think,
maybe PyPy in a box presented an opportunity for yourself, because you recently gave a talk about
it at the Ubuntu Summit in Prague. Yes. How was that experience? So, what happened is, interesting,
I gave a talk about the same project in Namibia at the Python conference in 2020.
When did COVID start? 2020. Yeah, so I gave a conference. Yeah, the last conference I attended
was just before COVID started. So, in 2020, I gave a conference, a talk at Namibia, and one of the
community managers at Canonical was in attendance at the conference. He heard the talk and, hey,
that's actually a good idea. And so, this year, he invited me to speak at the Ubuntu Summit. So,
the Ubuntu Summit is a Ubuntu conference that seeks to invite community members and Canonical
staff, put them in a room together for a few days, and share stories about how people are using
Ubuntu and Linux and open source in general. So, I got to present about how I was using Ubuntu on an
Raspberry Pi to do that. So, giving that talk led to that opportunity to be invited to that conference.
And it was my first time in Europe. I'd never been to Europe, so I got to travel to Europe,
give the talk, meet fantastic people from the Canonical team. It was at a fantastic time.
Yeah, it's always great. I remember the first time I went to the US when I started contracting
at Mozilla. It was also like a complete culture shock. And you can understand how there's so many
tech companies because everywhere around you, like if you sit in a little coffee shop and you're
just talking, everybody around you are talking about their startup and about this problem they're
having with this program. And so, there's this energy in the air that's very, very contagious.
So, I was wondering with that conference that you were able to attend in Prague and now that
we're slowly walking our way out of the pandemic and starting to... But we've also learned some
lessons about the fact that in-person events are great, but it doesn't necessarily... The
world doesn't have to come to a complete standstill if we can't get on a plane and fly somewhere.
So, we can do a lot of these things virtually. So, do you think if we can install a more active
conference circuit, so to speak, in Africa, do you think that would foster a more active startup
culture? Because that's the one thing that I find is very, very active in Europe and in the US.
And I think a lot of great ideas come out of just this concept of trying something and being
willing to fail, but also being willing to pivot. But I do think, like I said, you have to have a
culture, you have to have an active community that encourages this. So, do you think if we can
somehow, maybe starting all virtually, because that's also cheaper than having to fly all over
the place and also better for the environment, do you think if we can install this idea of having
more Africa-focused conferences, speaking about stuff like what me and you have been talking
about now, the challenges and possible solutions, do you think if we can kickstart something like
that, that that'll, by its very nature, install this idea of a startup culture?
I think it would, because we all have similar problems, similar challenges we face. And I think
now physical conferences, like physical meetups, we actually work better than virtual ones, because
I think the networking opportunity that gives you allows people to just share ideas and talk about
problems. Some of the things that people talk about come up, even not in the conference talk,
but in the hallway track, or in the dinners, or in the lunches, whatever. It's like we can share
ideas and conferences or meetups are very good places to talk about stuff or to learn about stuff
you don't really know. Because when you're to the conference, you can learn something you
weren't aware that you didn't know. Like, oh, that could be really useful for this project that I'm
trying to solve. It allows you to make connections and to learn stuff. So I definitely think
that conferences would help, because we don't have enough conferences, I'd say, or meetups,
because most of the conferences I've seen are enterprise conferences where companies are getting
together. They're okay, but they have a bottom line goal most of the time. And I think we need
more community-focused conferences that just allow people to meet and share ideas and figure out a
way to solve common problems. So yeah, I think it would help. Yeah, 100% agree. Yeah, a lot of those
others are more trying to sell you their products and services than really fostering a community of
makers. So yeah, I agree. So you're an AWS certified cloud practitioner. By the way,
congratulations on having achieved that. That's no small feat. But I do see that you also use
a service called Devo. How do those differ or are they more similar than different?
I'd say one is an abstraction over the other. So Devo is an enterprise solution.
What their goal is to unify multiple clouds. So say you have a business, you want to put your
business on the cloud, but you don't want to deal with the complexity of choosing a cloud or you
want to put some information in one region or one cloud and whatnot, they take care of all that for
you. So they just provide you with a platform, you upload your code, and then you can choose through
a drop-down what cloud you want to put this on, what region you want to put this on, and then they
take care of all that. So you could actually have an app that has some data in Azure, some data in
Google, and then some data in AWS in a specific region. They can take care of that for you. So
I'd say that's how they differ. But at the end of the day, Devo does use AWS under the hood. Now,
if I were to release an app, develop an app, there'd be times where I choose Devo and other
times where I prefer to use AWS or another service. So Devo is mostly focused on enterprise. So you'll
find that their paid plans are quite pricey. I think they issued this plan, the last I checked
was like $150 a month or something. But they had a very good free developer plan. So if I was just
building a pit project that needed a home and URLs, load balancing, and a server, I'd use Devo.
It's a very easy platform to use. You download the CLI, you Dockerize your project, you just push
the basis. It's very similar to Heroku. So they have a nice platform, good documentation,
really easy to set up Dockerized applications and give them an online presence. But I'd say
AWS is, if I was running a business, I'd probably put my product on AWS or even Azure or any other
cloud, because you get more options, more fine grain control over what you spend your money on,
you know, AWS. So there's easy solutions to AWS. If you just want to get an application online,
there's solutions, you know, things like Elastic Beanstalk, you know, you can use
Elastic Beanstalk, just put up a website online and then Amazon will take care of auto scaling,
load balancing, security, provisioning, and all that. Or if you have more skills,
you can get a VPS. You can get a VPS from them and do all that yourself. So it really depends on
what you want to do, you know, how much time you have and how much money you're willing to spend.
Because obviously, AWS, like Elastic Beanstalk is more expensive because it's a managed service. So
you get a lot of things out of the box and you pay more for it.
Okay, interesting. So on that topic, I've spoken to somebody before, Chelsea Adams, and she
also does quite a bit of the AWS kind of stuff, but she also does front end and that kind of thing,
but she's well versed when it comes to AWS, for example. And I think one thing that she mentioned
that I found interesting, and it's true, most, I don't want to say all because that would be
unfair, but most of these bootcamps or even like longer term educational institutions that provide
specifically education around front end development, they stop short of, okay,
now I can build a React application, but how do I put it online? Maybe they'll show you how to do it
with like using GitHub pages or something like that. But I mean, if you want to do a production
app, that's not really, you know, the way you're going to go. And so the one thing that she
mentioned is there's a hole there that needs to be filled in the sense that there's not really
any good education, accessible, good education out there to teach front end developers, how do
I put this app of mine online the right way? You know, it's easy to put it online, but how do I
put it online the right way so that if I announced this on my social media network and some famous
person retweets my thing and 10,000 people hit my website, that is not going to go down. And also
that I'm not going to tomorrow morning wake up and somebody's going to say, why is there a bunch of
porn on your URL? Because somebody hacked your website. So do you have any like tips or good
resources or something that you can recommend to people if they want to like know how to do that
stuff the right way? I didn't know front end had this problem as well. I thought it was just a
Python problem. But yeah, deployment is hard, which is actually one of the reasons why I
got into DevOps. I wanted to learn more about deployment and how to do it and automate stuff to
make it easy. But in terms of general tips, I don't have any resources I can think of right now,
but I have a few tips that I'd like to give. Like there's certain things that I think
most people aren't taught in these boot camps about how to make deployments go well. The first
thing I think is to think about security from the get go. Don't start thinking about security
when you're ready to deploy. So that will help you avoid making mistakes that could later burn you.
So you mentioned that you're setting up a website and putting porn. People can do that. And one of
the reasons why some of these things are possible is say you put up your code in Git. So first thing,
learn how to use Git correctly. If your project doesn't need to be open source,
don't make your code publicly available. Keep it private. That helps hide mistakes you may have
made. Whereas if your project is publicly available and people can see information,
sensitive information, you don't want them to see that. That gives them keys to doing bad stuff on
your website. But in a more general sense, I'd say that the first thing to watch out for is just
make sure you handle credentials correctly. Like don't hard code passwords and credentials into
your code. That's easy to do when you're just mucking around locally, but you can forget to
remove that stuff. So don't put credentials in the code. And if you're using environment files,
try and avoid adding them to Git. Don't track them. Don't push them up to GitHub, wherever
you're pushing your code. So try and keep your code separate from your credentials.
So there are services you can use. You could use password managers to manage your passwords. You
can use password vaults that would inject the credentials into your environment while you have
it running locally, so that you never have your credentials available in an unencrypted text file,
for instance. So there's things like that. I think KeePass has an open source tool you can
install in your environments that can manage credentials for you. There's something called
HashiCorp Vault. You can install that on your server. It manages secrets for you. And then
once you're ready to deploy, I'd say make use of environment variables on the deployment server.
So whatever service you're deploying to, put your passwords there, the secrets and credentials there
instead of hard coding. So that's the first thing that would help reduce the risk of being hacked.
It's not the only thing, but it really helps. And then I'd say the second thing is,
if you can afford it, try and get a service that allows you to auto scale easily.
If you look at cloud solutions like AWS or Azure, there are tools that allow you to auto scale. So
if you put up your website and it gets popular, all those auto scaling solutions will allow your
traffic, will keep your website running even if it gets hit by like 10,000 requests or a lot of
people start using it. It will cost you money, but you won't have to think about it because
it's done for you. So if you can afford it, look into something like that. And then I think the
last thing I'd say is try and make your deployments repeatable. And I know for front-end
developers, this might mean learning some skills that they may not generally want to learn, but
learn something about CI, CD and how that works. If you can get an automated deployment pipeline
going, do that because having that deploying code for you will allow you to run checks on your code
to make sure that the tool catches any errors you could introduce early before you actually do the
deployment. So you can look into that and try and make the deployments as automated and as repeatable
as possible. Yeah. So I think GitHub is doing a lot to make this more accessible through
GitHub, CI, CD, your GitHub actions and that kind of stuff. Do you use something like Terraform?
Not for the current project I work on, no. Okay. Yeah. I know it's some folks that Mozilla uses
Terraform and then Kubernetes, I think is one of the other things that people use. Yeah, I use
Kubernetes, but not Terraform. Okay. Okay. Yeah. But yeah, I think those are all great tips and
I would highly recommend people look that up and I'll add links to all of these things
when we publish this episode. So in closing, something fun. In your bio on your website,
you said you like cutting wood. Yes. Tell me more about that. Tell me more about that.
Okay. So software development is very stressful and you need an outlet to release that stress.
Cutting wood is a very good outlet. Wood doesn't complain. Wood can take a beating. So
I like to cut wood. But on a serious note, it's very similar to software development. You need
to think about what you want to make. You need to design what you want to build. You need to choose
the right tools and you need to follow a logical sequence of steps to get to make whatever it is
you want to make. And so it's a very, I'd say it's a good hobby to pursue if you're in software
development because many of the skills you learn, you know, from developing software are easily
transferable to woodworking. You just need to find the right tools, determine what you want
to build. Like I don't make any fancy furniture or anything like that. I can't do that. I make very
simple tables and desks, you know, like flat things, not flat corners, you know, but it's a really
nice fulfilling feeling to work on something you actually built yourself. Yeah, for sure. And like
I said, if you're stressed, you can hammer it with all day and all night because you're probably
going to make something good out of it. I really enjoy doing that and watching videos of experienced
carpenters and woodworkers doing DIY stuff. I'm really heavily into DIY. I believe every person
should at least know how to fix something. Yeah, for sure. So I really enjoy watching that stuff
and trying it on my own when I have the time. Yeah, yeah. I love those videos of the people
that do the woodturning where they have, you know, those big fancy machines that like take this
rough piece of wood and they just turn it and it's this beautiful shapes and just these gradients
that the colors of the wood forms. And it's so meditative to watch that stuff. It's just beautiful.
So I can imagine if, you know, if you can get to that point where you can actually do that
yourself, it'll be an amazing experience. But I think even starting with a pocket knife and a
piece of wood can be a nice start. Definitely, definitely. I have a friend who actually started
that way. You know, he used to make these little walking sticks and now he runs a business and
makes furniture. So you can start as a hobby and turn into a business. Yeah, for sure. That's great.
Well, thank you so much for this conversation. I really, really enjoyed it. It was
lovely to talk to somebody in Africa that shares a lot of the pain that I go through as well.
But I think you also have some unique challenges that we in South Africa might not always face.
But still, I think there's a lot of opportunities and I think we should connect more
and cross-pollinate. And I'm definitely going to hit you up about the whole NPM in the box.
I'm definitely going to contact you. And let's chat about that and make that a thing. I think
that'll be super interesting to do, but also super useful. So thanks so much for the conversation and
have a lovely rest of your day. And all the best for the future. And I'm looking forward to seeing
all the wonderful things you do. Thanks a lot. Cheers.
Thank you for listening to this episode of the Mycenae Network Podcast. If you're not already,
please subscribe, star, and leave a review for us in your podcatcher of choice. This helps others
find us and helps us make a better podcast for you on this course. You can also find and follow us on
Twitter at networkmycenae and join the community on Discord. All the links are available in the
show notes.