Welcome to the Mycelium Network Podcast,
a podcast all about early stage web developers and
the mentors and teachers that help them along the way.
Today, we are joined by Soham Shah,
a software engineer based out of India,
a front-end developer who plays around with React,
Next, JavaScript on a daily basis,
also an open-source contributor,
and I've been a Linux Foundation mentee,
and has served as a collaborator at Chakra UI in the past.
Welcome, Soham.
Hi. Yeah, thank you for having me at the podcast.
It's really great that you are
doing so amazing stuff for the community, so yeah.
It's my pleasure. So I think to get this started off,
maybe tell me where you're currently at,
and fun fact about yourself.
Yeah, sure. So currently,
I'm working as a software engineer at Marvin,
and my major work revolves around React and the JavaScript frameworks.
So currently, I am having alignment towards the front-end side,
but I'm passionate about software engineering in general.
So yeah, that is what I do on a daily basis.
Yeah, fun fact could be like I am
a sucker for the programming tease and the swags,
like I have them a lot.
Like I can show like I'm having
programming code written on my T-shirt right now as well.
So yeah, I just love these coding and the nerdy stuff. So yeah.
I'm a sucker for that too.
I completely understand.
So it seems like you're really involved in the open source world,
and I actually know about you from your contributions to MDN.
So can you maybe tell us a few words about your open source experience?
Yeah. So open source has been one of
the parts where I got the confidence into what I'm learning.
So generally, when you are learning something,
you need to implement.
So there are a lot of things that open source has helped me.
Again, one of the major things that I found is the mentorship part,
because everyone who has written this code,
if we are contributing,
then our quality is evaluated and reviewed.
So that is something that I have got a lot of learning from that.
So even what PR I made at MDN,
that just small thing,
I still remember what I wrote.
It was related to this screen reader visibility.
So I still remember that,
and whenever I write code for that,
I remember what fundamentals that you need to follow.
So also like at Chakra UI,
I had a good opportunity to do the issue triaging.
So that was also something that I could understand this large code base,
and everyone is so helpful.
So I feel very blessed even specifically as a very new into this space,
everyone is so much supportive and that mentorship part has a lot much on me.
So that is one thing that I have particularly loved about open source.
Apart from that, you build a very good network with the folks.
So that is what I have truly enjoyed.
We used to have a long,
long just chitchatting with the contributors and the collaborators,
just knowing each other.
So that was also something that you don't really just do work.
You also do something that connects you.
So the open source is for everyone,
and whatever the technologies,
whatever things are being built,
they are all indebted to open source.
So even small contribution is making such big impact,
and that is also something that excites you to write more and more better code,
or it could be more contributions whenever you are available.
So yeah, that's my personal alignment to open source.
Now that you've been active,
you've been active down the software industry for a while.
But maybe you can tell us a little bit about your background
and what made you decide to get involved in this industry in the first place.
Yeah. So if I talk about my high school,
so I was a science student,
so there were a lot of options for me.
I chose software engineering because that was
the best option that I could get because what I have seen,
it has a lot of opportunities.
You can literally go into a lot of areas,
and that too involves a lot of research as well.
If you're into research,
if you're into doing something new,
then AI and everything are there which are under aggressive research.
Today, like blockchain and the other metaverse technologies
are there for a lot of research.
So that was my reason for choosing software engineering,
but I was literally clueless.
I was just going to college and coming back,
doing those assignments and all.
But I always had that fear that,
will I be able to go at a really good company?
So that phase of mine where I was just in the bubble of my college and that small network,
I had that competitive mindset that,
okay, this person is doing better than me,
so will I be able to do even better?
So that competitive mindset actually was inside me that,
am I doing better?
Even I used to see more GitHub contributions,
I used to get that envy feeling that,
will I be able to get that?
I was always having that fear under my head that,
what after college?
What after my graduation?
Everything was that.
Then I decided, okay,
let's not get into this mindset and let's come out and see what
the other people are doing on the Internet.
Then slowly and gradually,
I started joining this Discord servers of different communities.
I joined this React Flux,
which is very popular where you see job posting,
where you see different questions.
So that was something I saw people are just helping out.
You are just asking a question and a lot of people who are
very popular people in the maintainer and open source world,
they are helping to solve even small, small bugs.
So that made me realize that,
okay, it is not that you are into competition,
but there I learned the importance like open source fundamental,
that it is about collaboration first and code second mindset.
So that actually made me understand,
okay, there is a lot more to it.
Then I first stepped into machine learning side of things.
So I did a lot of learning on that side and I really enjoyed it.
But after a certain point,
I was getting into proper research.
But then due to some reason,
my friend just told me like,
you can try web development.
I'm doing this. So it was sort of a freelance work.
So I did that and I really enjoyed it.
I didn't know that CSS could be this interesting.
Generally, it is a mindset that when you start learning,
then you have to do it.
So CSS was challenging,
but also interesting at the same time.
So I was getting that alignment.
Then I saw web development has,
if we see on a larger scale,
it has a lot of job opportunities.
Plus, I found out that my software engineering fundamentals
are clearly seen practical in that part more,
compared to what I was doing in other side.
For example, if I say client server architecture,
that is one main paradigm of software engineering.
So I could see that in practice in web development.
So that just gave me that kick.
Plus, one thing that you can build stuff.
So you can even build small application
for your day-to-day real usage.
So that actually gave me that confidence.
At that point, I realized that I can switch
my focus and attention to just one thing,
at least for now, I can go with web development.
It is not confined to just this field,
but I will do this.
So in AI, I did some research and review papers as well.
But I decided that this is not going to be,
at least for now, this is not going to be my career path.
And I started learning JavaScript.
I started learning React and all.
So this was my way I divide the trajectory.
Basically, I got into web development.
And then I started just being involved in the community.
So by that, I learned a lot of things.
That's very interesting.
Yeah.
And so throughout this whole process
of learning and experimenting and kind of switching even,
switching careers, if you want to call it,
what have you found the most challenging about the industry
and about learning?
OK.
I guess the most challenging part is the start point,
the head start.
So when I was just into web development,
so first thing that I faced was the tutorial hell.
Anyone who is into just starting out any technology,
if one just sees the YouTube videos
and just do the line by line implementation,
then the learning is actually cut off.
And that is just literally you are getting that fake dopamine
hit that you have made something.
But that is actually that is just
you are doing from YouTube video.
So that I did for a long time.
I used to watch like, OK, I want to learn, for example, React
table, right?
I want to learn table stuff on React.
So I used to watch that whole video.
In reality, it should be I should read the documentation
or I should read blogs.
So this was a big, big issue.
I used to spend hours and hours of watching videos,
even the different courses on Udemy and all.
I took them.
And I was just watching and watching
and very less implementation was there and very less mind
I was putting into it.
So that actually was a big challenge.
Even in machine learning, I realized
that what I was doing previously was just
like looking at different YouTube videos
or Udemy or different courses.
And then I was just coding it out on my ID
and just making the output come.
But I feel that this is actually not the right way to learn.
So then I realized that I should focus.
I should pressure myself a little bit
that I go to these documentation sites or the blog sites
or even if I'm watching a tutorial video,
I should be mindful that I am using my own brain
to make something, giving things time.
So then this was a big challenge for me at least.
Like I spent more than four months
and even I got internship with that particular knowledge
that I was doing.
But even after the internship, I realized that I still
lack the fundamentals.
So this was something very insightful.
And then I came across a boot camp called Neoji Camp.
So this web development boot camp actually
helped me a lot in my career.
What I have learned from there, the community and everything,
I am totally indebted to what I have learned in that boot camp.
So there can be any different sort of these resources.
But the idea is that even there you
do this tutorial copy pasting or this type of thing,
then again, that would be an issue.
So yeah, one idea that I have followed that first thing
that I have to do is think by my mind,
then go to documentation, understand it thoroughly.
And then if I'm getting nothing, then I
go to maybe just the YouTube video and just quickly see.
But it is not that follow that thing.
So yeah, that was a little bit thing
I could share about my experience.
Yeah, that's interesting.
Yeah, I think for myself also, what I have found
is I find it hard to learn something
if I don't have anywhere to use it in the moment,
if you know what I mean.
So I find if I can think of a need,
like the way they say scratching your own itch, that thing.
So I think of an idea, and I'm like, OK, cool.
So I have this idea.
So what technologies are out there that I'd like to learn?
And then I would pick one of these technologies
that I'm not as familiar with.
And I would learn it and use it to build this thing
that I didn't want to build for myself.
I kind of feel like that is a better way for me
personally of learning, other than just building yet another
to-do application or something like that.
That is very spot on.
The one which you mentioned, the way
to go is understanding the problem
and then searching for the available solutions,
implemented solution in the market.
For example, if I had to implement a graph library,
I won't be going to a tutorial where the guy uses a graph
library.
But it would be like what my design says,
what my future product requirement says,
or what I have at least imagined for my project
that I would be implementing this stuff in my graph.
And then I see different options,
like how do you go for shopping?
It is exactly like that.
You see different things that are similar for your use case,
but you choose whatever fits your need,
not what the shopkeeper gives us.
So that is the idea that I feel everywhere I have seen.
In fact, when my professional thing started,
we had to write these design documents
for different implementations.
So we used to research on various options
and the library which we want to introduce.
So because that takes up the bundle size,
so the practice should be very mindful about the feature
and not the technology.
I agree 100%.
Yeah.
So you've mentioned a couple of resources,
but if you had to pull together a couple of things
that you found particularly useful up to now,
what are those resources?
Right.
For resource, I would say that first thing
that the best resource, I would say,
is the MDN documentation, at least for web development.
That is the way that should come into practice.
Even if it is difficult for one as a beginner,
still it is something that you need to get used to it,
at least the starting part.
Because all other resources are sort
of an extract from this resource only.
So not just this, but the very source of truth,
in the community, I guess it is the MDN docs.
So other resources are an extract of this.
So one thing that if you need anything,
then this is going to be your source of truth.
You can quote it.
It is given at MDN.
So there is a high possibility that we
need to just reconsider our belief about XYZ thing
that we are knowing about JavaScript or web in general.
But apart from this, the fundamentals
should be very, very clear about any language.
This I have realized when I got some challenging work.
So on building simple Figma screens,
implementation into code is very simple.
We can just make some CSS changes
and just make the thing work.
But when there is complexity, when
there is making things as scale, or any more complexity
will be introduced, then you will realize, OK,
this concept should be known.
Else, on a longer run, the code will be spaghetti.
So that concept, JavaScript React concepts
are very important.
So I would say JavaScript.info is the website
that I have admired a lot.
They have put everything so much structured and nicely
with very good example.
So for a beginner, this is the resource.
Even it has helped a lot in interviews
where you have to crisp.
You want crisp info.
So JavaScript info is very good for beginners.
Apart from that, there is a YouTube playlist
called Namaste JS, which is by Akshay Saini.
So he also explains the JavaScript concepts and all
in very, very good depth.
And also, one thing that I realized,
that even if you are doing that tutorial healthing in this
as well, it applies the same.
So this resource is also good.
But if you're not implementing, then it
is, again, the same story.
But the reason why I love this playlist or the videos
of Namaste JavaScript is the way that is being explained
is from the core, so that I particularly like.
It is not just syntax, but it is how it works on the behind.
So yeah.
But apart from that, if you really
want to work on particular things like Next.js or Webpack
or something like that, then there
is Frontend Master's course, which are pretty good.
I got it from GitHub pack.
So if you are a student, then definitely you
should exercise your GitHub student pack
and get Frontend Master's, or else you can buy as well.
But Frontend Master's course are really, really quality courses.
So definitely, I would consider buying or even
for resource or for the learning.
So yeah, you just need to search the right things,
and Google will make the SEO work for you.
So just like searching, keep building, SEO will work.
Yeah.
Yeah, I have to agree.
Frontend Master's is really good.
I use that as well.
So you've mentioned a whole bunch of resources,
and they sound great.
But I'm wondering, what do you find missing or stuff
that can be improved?
OK, in these resources, one thing
that if we see blog-based resource, for example,
JavaScript Info, so if you just read those blogs
and just make the examples that they give,
you just implement them, then I guess it won't be enough.
So when you read a book, if you just read the whole book
without thinking or implementing about it,
then it won't make any sense.
So it is the same with JavaScript Info.
For example, if you have learned about closures.
But the ideal or a good way, I would say,
it won't be just stopping at that point.
You can just give yourself some time to digest.
Then you can look for other blogs available maybe
on Medium or Hashnode, these blogging websites,
and know how other concepts that you might have missed.
For example, the disadvantages of closures.
This is a topic that might have not
been covered at JavaScript Info.
So you can just see.
So when you give yourself time to digest things,
then only it will actually fruit.
Else, you will forget.
If you read the whole JavaScript Info in one day,
then it won't result into anything.
So that is one thing that is being missing.
The other thing, I feel that they are lacking code.
They are not having enough code examples
that you need to become a master or at least a good level
at the particular technology.
Not pointing at any one, all the other resource
because they have limitation of number of examples
because they don't want that content to be very long.
So as a developer, what I used to do,
I used to Google JavaScript questions on closures.
There will be 10 different websites.
I just used to pick and put it on my GitHub repo
so I can refer them later.
So this is the way we can just compensate that
because code is everything, right?
Enough number of lines of text is not that much,
how much 10-liner code can explain.
So that's why code is something that you
need to have in abundance when you are learning.
And one thing that JavaScript Info example I gave, right?
So one thing I used to do with my friend,
we used to do pair learning.
So what we used to do, we used to pick
some topics of our interview questions, right?
JavaScript fundamental questions.
For example, it could be closures or promises.
We used to just divide amongst each other.
And then we used to explain those to each other.
And then we used to have discussions.
And we used to have debates.
And then we ran across Google and searched
what was the real right answer.
So those conversations, I feel they
were a lot more productive than anything else.
So the human connect is something different
that I have realized that when you
have friends who are into the same path you are going towards,
then it is very helpful.
And that is also a big, big benefit of being in a community.
You just text on Discord that, OK, I've learned this.
I want to explain that to anyone who wants to join.
Go on the channel and just start discussing, right?
So this is one thing that has helped me a lot in my interview
learning process.
And yeah, that is one fond memory.
And I also made very good friendship
with the bond as well.
That is really, really interesting.
I've never heard people say that before.
The specific having a debate and that whole thing,
that's super interesting.
And I can imagine that'll work really well.
I was just telling that we had a big, I guess,
one and a half hour debate on JavaScript is interpreted
language or a compiled language.
Because there is not exactly one stamp answer to that.
There are a lot of complexity on what perspective you are talking.
So that was a really amazing discussion.
So yeah, please go ahead.
No, no, thanks for sharing that.
That's really interesting.
So I was thinking, you've been through the interview process.
So what do you think about interviews in the tech industry?
It's a little scary, and maybe you think should be changed?
Or how do you think it can be improved?
Yeah, so one thing that I recently gave a lot of interviews.
So one thing that in common which I realized
that was a little bit of blocker was I was not even
having enough context of what I will be giving interview
for that, right?
So just an example.
So some companies like ask something very, very advanced
in the first round itself.
And some of them just ask basics.
Or even if we are doing for a front end role,
I was asked something very unexpected about system design.
So that is one thing that there should be a little bit clarity
upon what skills you will be assessed in a particular round.
So you are prepared.
For example, if I was asked about web performance, right?
But at that point, I was not remembering
what I learned about web performance,
at least at the time of the interview.
So I had to ask that, could you let me Google?
So they did let me, but what if they didn't?
So I was not remembering the names like FID or the terms.
So that could lead that I am not knowing.
But in reality, I was knowing.
I had learned about or experimented
about these things before.
So yeah, these type of things.
I was once asked like dynamic programming question.
So generally, I at least don't expect a lot of this
complex algorithm as a fresher into front end
that we are asked a lot more this typical data structure
algorithm question.
But even if they're coming, then I
should know that, OK, I should be prepared.
So this is one thing.
Else I have a feeling that for interviews,
if you are prepared enough, then things are very, very simple.
But it is not the case for every time and everyone.
Some people might be a little bit nervous
or that is into nature because that depends.
So for that, I feel that practice
is something that gives you confidence.
But we as a human, we need validation.
So even if I have solved 100 questions
and I practice a lot, but that is not validated by someone.
So I need someone to validate that, OK, I'm
at least ready to appear for interview.
So peers helped a lot.
I used to give mock interviews with my friends on Twitter.
So two, three people on Twitter helped me for mock interviews.
So even that person is not as equal experience as us,
but at least we can be confident that am I able to explain.
So that part I can add.
Apart from that, I always have that one sort of fear
that whatever I am knowing that in one interview,
I was asked, do you know CSS?
Then I literally had no answer.
If I say yes and that I'm asked very, very difficult
or in-depth question of CSS, then what will happen?
So that thing, I always am not sure
that how much in-depth knowledge you want or you
need for a particular role, because that is very variable.
So that was very, very.
And I've seen in interviews, you are asked yourself
to rate on some numbers, which I particularly find weird,
because I am generally asked, out of 10,
how much you rate yourself.
So I don't know how, because even if you are reactive,
you are not Dan Abramo, right?
So you don't know everything.
So you cannot tell you are above eight or nine.
So yeah, that sometimes.
But it's fine.
I don't think that is any issue.
That's just a way to see if you are confident enough.
Yeah, I guess.
Yeah, yeah.
So just a pop quiz question.
Would you rather start your own business
or rather join a company?
Yeah, this is actually a question
that I actually don't have any right answer, at least
for now, a little bit tricky for me.
But I really want to start my own business.
But the key is if I get the right idea or a product,
that particularly I believe in.
So if I want to do something and I
reach to that particular stage where I can actually
implement that, given that all the factors you need,
so then definitely I would go for my startup or something.
But apart from that, even anywhere I'm at,
if my work, whatever I'm doing is valued,
and if I'm satisfied at the end of the day,
then I guess that is really cool.
You are doing good at work.
And life is also, apart from work,
you want to do what you're passionate about, maybe
some hobby or something that you do for fun.
So that balance is also some people look for.
That is totally depending on person to person.
But I would like to also keep my hobbies as priority.
So I don't want to be super, super workaholic.
I also want to have the balance between both.
That's good.
And that leads nicely into the next question, which is,
what do you like to do when you don't code or learn to code?
So I would say I do different stuff.
I just try experimenting different things.
For example, sometimes I see my friends learning something.
I just ask, from where you are learning?
So recently, my friend was learning music and guitar
and stuff.
So I have an interest in singing.
I'm not a good singer.
But he explained me in more technical terms of music.
So I have been into that.
I love doing that.
Also, from this new year, Jan, I decided
I would focus more on my health as well.
So I've been doing yoga and meditation
and have continued that habit till now.
So that is also a win for me.
But I really enjoy doing yoga and all these things.
A lot good for mental health and peace.
So also for stretch and everything,
I really feel energetic throughout the day.
Apart from that, I'm having a very, not exactly hobby,
but I love experimenting with my habits.
So even small, small things, like you
refrain from something for one week.
Are you able to control yourself from doing that?
It could be as simple as not watching TV.
This is a habit, right?
You are challenging yourself that, OK,
I'm not going to do something.
It is more towards that part.
Are we not getting a lot much slaves of our own mind?
So that is an exercise that I like doing whenever I like.
So if you could recommend a single resource, that
could be a book, a course, YouTube channel, a community,
whatever, what would you recommend?
So for a book, I'm not much into reading self-help books,
first of all.
But I have read Atomic Habits.
So that was a really, really good book, if you implement.
So whatever is said in that book,
it has actually helped me a lot to think back
and on what I'm currently doing, what my habits are.
And that is where I have got this motivation
to try out different stuff and improve our habits.
So that is one book I would definitely
recommend to implement.
Apart from that, Neoji Camp Bootcamp
is something that has changed my trajectory about the career.
If I had not done that, if I had not got the community there
and the friends and the mentorship, everything there,
then I am not sure what I would have been doing.
But yeah, it is sort of very close to my heart.
And I am very indebted to that.
So you can check that out.
It is a very, very good cohort of learning web development.
So yeah, that is what I strongly recommend.
It is more about you learn together.
And also, they help you in placements as well.
If you intend to get a job, then they
help you with that as well.
So yeah, it has helped me a lot, so definitely.
But else, resources-wise, I guess if we see properly,
then we will find things around.
Just being connected with the community,
because people has a lot of stories to tell.
So if you connect with someone today,
that person will tell you his or her 10 resources.
And then you know a lot of things,
and then you can evaluate what fits best for you.
But that information comes by communicating.
So that is one thing that I would say as a resource,
I would say.
And apart from that, you asked about community.
So I told about Discord groups.
They are amazing.
Whenever you want to hang out, you should.
At least in the tech community, networking
is a very, very crucial part.
Because I have seen that directly applying
at a company's portal versus getting a referral
is a very big difference, and also not a referral.
But you can at least ask the person,
is the company really good?
Is it fitting your requirements?
So that's why networking is crucial in all different terms.
And yeah, I have been attending and being involved
with the meetup groups in my, like I have been involved
with React, the technology that I am interested in.
So there's React Bangalore, JavaScript Bangalore meetups.
So these are the meetup groups that I have been involved.
I've also given a couple of talks.
But overall, what I focus is on learning.
So yeah, tech meetup groups are definitely a place to go.
Sometimes some Saturday when you are free,
you should hop in to the live meetings, or talks,
or workshops, whatever you like.
Yeah, I 100% agree.
Community is super important.
So if you could nominate someone that you
think I should speak to on this podcast,
who would you nominate?
Right.
Yeah, first thing that I feel that you should definitely
talk with is Sage.
He is the creator of Chakra UI framework,
which is a very popular front-end framework.
So the reason, because I had been in the meetings
previously when I was involved with Chakra UI actively,
he is a very humble person and very knowledgeable, very expert
in this domain.
And I'm really inspired from what work he has put
and what things he does for the community.
So that is my nomination, if you would say that.
But Sage is the person that I would say.
Apart from that, Johnny Berger, I'm not sure you know him.
I've seen him or not.
But he is a creator of Remotion.
And I have also made a couple of small contributions
and have been on the Discord.
So he's also a very passionate person
about open source and overall.
So yeah, definitely them.
And if you want to talk more about student-centric or
learner-centric side, so then I would
recommend that you can talk with Tanay Pratap.
He's the founder of Invact.
And he was also involved with NeojiCamp.
He used to help mentor us and teach us.
So yeah, definitely he's an amazing person
for the students.
And yeah, this is really, this can
be very helpful for anyone learning, getting started.
Yeah, those sound all like great people.
I'll definitely reach out to them.
So before we wrap this up, please tell us about any projects
you would like our audience to know about,
any work opportunities you're open to,
what kind you're interested in, and how people can contact you.
Yeah, sure.
So first thing, to be honest, I have
done a couple of projects and all.
But one project that has been very close to me
was the one that I did in December.
It was done in November.
So basically, it is a mock backend
for the front-end developers who are just
learning and making projects.
So it is just for learning purpose.
But the thing is, if you are making an e-commerce
application, so the problem is, if you just make the front-end,
if we are making just front-end and putting just dummy data,
then it is not making any use of the API call
or the client server thing.
Or if I want to do something complex,
if I want to call different APIs in sequence,
if I want to do something complex with the API calling,
I want to show loading states, stuff like that.
So how I will be able to do that?
And if I'm not doing, then real work of a front-end person
is not just making screens, but it is also
about state management or data, how data will be loaded,
and everything like that.
So for that, I built mock me.
So it gives different templates for different projects.
So there are more than eight, nine templates are there.
So for e-commerce or video library or social media
and all, so people are really using them
and finding it very helpful.
So we also built what problem we realized with the library
that we are using under mock me.
So it is a Mirage.js-based project.
So Mirage.js is a library for mocking the APIs.
But the problem with Mirage.js is you cannot do stuff
that you do with the real APIs.
You can go to Postman or some tool
and make the fetch call and see what is the response.
That you cannot do with that interface is not available to you
when you're doing with Mirage.js or the mock me sort of.
Not going into much technicalities,
but for this problem statement, we actually
built another sister project called mock man.
So basically, this is exactly same as Postman,
but Postman are some, I guess, the different tools
are available for API testing.
So exactly same, but for mock APIs.
So we built this for Mirage.js.
So that particular project is powering more than 2,000
active GitHub projects.
And overall, these mock me and different templates
are having, today, more than 18,000 downloads.
So yeah, that is most impactful project.
And people like DM me, put it on Twitter
that they are getting jobs because they
had it in their mock back end.
Because the interviewer can see the projects they
are having real functionality.
So yeah, my project has been on back end,
and it is helping people on the back end backstage side.
So I'm very happy and proud about this project.
But I really want to maintain it as well in the future.
That's very cool.
Yeah, thanks.
Very, very nice.
Well, thank you so much for joining me today, Saham.
I really enjoyed the conversation.
And I wish you all of the best for the future,
and looking forward to see all the great things you build.
Yeah, thank you so much once again for having me.
It was really good, and good luck for the amazing things
that you are doing for the community,
and all hail Mycelium Network.
Thank you for listening to this episode of the Mycelium Network
podcast.
If you're not already, please subscribe, star,
and leave a review for us in your podcatcher of choice.
This helps others find us and helps
us make a better podcast for you on this course.
You can also find and follow us on Twitter at networdmycelium,
and join the community on Discord.
All the links are available in the show notes.